<?xml version="1.0"?>
<picture-set title="Saab 9-5: Control Arm Bushings">

  <description>
  <p>Lower control arm removal and bushing replacement on a 1999 Saab 9-5.
  The original bushings were worn and cracked, the hydraulic rear
  bushings went dry and lost most of the oil, so a fresh set was
  needed.</p>

  <p>Saab sells replacement rear bushings as a complete assembly with a new
  aluminium housing, but we're installing a polyurethane insert, so the old
  bushing needs to be pressed out of the housing.
  A hydraulic press should greatly speed up the rear bushing removal, but
  since it's not a common household appliance, we will be using a hacksaw
  and a gear puller.</p>

  <h2>Tools:</h2>
  <ul>
    <li>18 mm socket: rear bushing retainer nut, ball joint nut (optional);</li>
    <li>17 mm socket: wheel bolts;</li>
    <li>15 mm socket: control arm bolts;</li>
    <li>13 mm socket: ball joint screws (optional);</li>
    <li>8 mm socket: plastic shield screws;</li>
    <li>torque wrench;</li>
    <li>car jack and axle stands;</li>
    <li>breaker bar;</li>
    <li>gear puller;</li>
    <li>hacksaw;</li>
    <li>hammer and rubber mallet.</li>
  </ul>
  </description>

  <picture name="20070926a.Wheel_off.jpg" title="Wheel off" date="26.09.2007">
    Raise the car and secure it on jack stands. Take off the front wheel.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070926b.Plastic_shield.jpg" title="Plastic shield" date="26.09.2007">
    Remove the plastic shield covering the belt and the front fender area.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070926c.Ball_joint_nut.jpg" title="Ball joint nut" date="26.09.2007">
    Undo the ball joint nut, pull the bolt and remove the ball joint out of
    its socket. Alternatively, unscrew the ball joint from the control arm
    (there won't be enough clearance to remove these bolts until the arm is
    detached from the subframe though).
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070926d.Control_arm_bolts.jpg" title="Control arm bolts" date="26.09.2007">
    Undo three bolts holding the control arm to the subframe. One is at the
    front of the arm, and two more hold the aluminium housing of the big rear
    bushing. It might also be a good idea to slacken the rear bushing retainer
    nut - you have more leverage while it's still on the car.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070926e.Front_bushing.jpg" title="Front bushing" date="26.09.2007">
    The front bushing is easy to press out with a gear puller or a similar tool.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070926f.Rear_bushing_nut.jpg" title="Rear bushing nut" date="26.09.2007">
    The rear is more complicated. Start by removing the retainer nut and sliding
    the busing off its pivot.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070926g.Rim_cut.jpg" title="Rim cut" date="26.09.2007">
    Cut the rolled rim of the big bushing - hacksaw works well, Dremel might
    be faster. Pry out the metal cover that was held by the rim.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070926h.Gear_puller.jpg" title="Gear puller" date="26.09.2007">
    Use the gear puller to push out the inner part of the bushing, watch
    for hydraulic fluid leaks (have a pan ready).
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070926i.Cutting_the_sleeve.jpg" title="Cutting the sleeve" date="26.09.2007">
    Put the bushing housing in a vice, assemble a hacksaw with a blade inside 
    the housing and cut through the metal sleeve.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070926j.Inner_sleeve_removed.jpg" title="Inner sleeve removed" date="26.09.2007">
    Turn the housing upside down and make another cut on the opposite side of
    the sleeve. Chisel the sleeve out.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070926k.New_bushings.jpg" title="New bushings" date="26.09.2007">
    I used polyurethane bushings by Powerflex. They are easy to install or
    remove, all you need is a rubber mallet and some anti-seize (a small packet
    of grease is usually supplied with the bushings).
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070926l.Bushings_installed.jpg" title="Bushings installed" date="26.09.2007">
    Lubricate the bushings, slide them in, then insert the metal sleeves.
    Put the big bushing back onto its pivot and tighten the nut to 77 ft-lbs.
    <image width="800" height="587" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070926m.Ball_joint_bolts.jpg" title="Ball joint bolts" date="26.09.2007">
    Fit the ball joint back in and tighten the bolt to 70 ft-lbs (or 36 ft-lbs on 2002+ cars).
    Alternatively, install three small bolts holding the ball joint to the
    control arm.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070926n.Attached.jpg" title="Attached" date="26.09.2007">
    Connect the control arm to the subframe. Slide the bolts in, but do not
    tighten them yet. Tighten three small ball joint bolts to 22 ft-lbs
    (if applicable).
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070926o.Leveled.jpg" title="Raised" date="26.09.2007">
    Place a jack under a ball joint and raise it until it takes the weight
    of the car, and the control arm is 1 degree below horizontal. Secure the
    arm to the subframe at 70 ft-lbs.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070926p.Done.jpg" title="Done" date="26.09.2007">
    Remove the jack under the ball joint. Fit the plastic shield. Tighten the
    wheel bolts to 81 ft-lbs and lower the car to the ground.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
</picture-set>
