<?xml version="1.0"?>
<picture-set title="Saab Trionic 7: Trionic 7 CAN Bus Connection">

  <description>
  <p>Here's a brief guide on how to connect to the CAN bus on a Trionic7 ECU.</p>

  <p>CAN bus connection offers a fast and convenient way to read or flash the
  firmware in the ECU. However, keep in mind that there's a slight chance it
  may fail while writing the memory, especially if you're flashing in the car.
  When that happens, you end up with a dead ECU, which no longer responds to
  a CAN connection. The only way to revive it in this case is by using a
  <a href="#/content/saab/20090306-trionic7-can-bus-connection">BDM interface</a>.</p>

  <p>See also:
  <a href="https://txsuite.org/">Trionic Suite</a>,
  <a href="https://www.trionictuning.com/forum/">Trionic Tuning Community</a>
  </p>
  </description>

  <picture name="20090306a.CANUSB.jpg" title="CANUSB" date="06.03.2009">
    <a href="https://canusb.com/">Lawicel CANUSB</a> seems to remain as
    the best (if not the only) CAN-USB adapter supported by the community
    right now. You can also try RS-232 devices, but you may be
    hard pressed to find a laptop with a serial port these days.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20090306b.9-pin_adapter.jpg" title="9-pin adapter" date="06.03.2009">
    Next, you need a female 9-pin D-sub connector. You're only interested in
    two pins here: #2 (CAN low) and #7 (CAN high). I'm using white and
    green wires to match the colors of CAN low and CAN high leads on the
    instrumentation bus in the Saab.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20090306c.Power_cable.jpg" title="Power cable" date="06.03.2009">
    If you plan to connect to the ECU on the bench, you will also need to power
    it up. There are three pins each where you need to apply ground
    (#25, #47, #62) and +12V power (#1, #23, #43). I made this simple
    harness with insulated alligator clips.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20090306d.Bench_testing.jpg" title="Bench testing" date="06.03.2009">
    Hook up both the power harness and the CAN harness (pin #19 is CAN low,
    #66 is CAN high). Attach a power supply. It may not hurt to
    have slighly more voltage - these 16V IBM ThinkPad AC adapters seem to work
    great. Once it's powered up, start your software and proceed with
    connecting to the ECU.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20090306e.ACC_unit_harness.jpg" title="ACC unit harness" date="06.03.2009">
    There is a number of locations in the car where you can access the
    instrumentation bus: the SID, the stereo, the ACC, the CD changer, etc.
    I chose to unplug the ACC panel since I can live without it while tuning.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20090306f.In-car_connection.jpg" title="In-car connection" date="06.03.2009">
    <p>Connect your green "CAN high" wire to pin #33 on the ACC harness, and
    your white "CAN low" wire to pin #34. Turn the ignition key, and enjoy
    a live connection to your ECU.</p>
    <p>P.S. Perhaps it's time to clean the screen on my laptop ;]</p>
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
</picture-set>
