<?xml version="1.0"?>
<picture-set title="Saab Trionic 7: BDM Connection">

  <description>
  <p>Here's a brief guide on how to connect a BDM interface to a Trionic7 ECU.</p>

  <p>BDM (stands for Background Debug Mode) is an electronic interface for
  debugging microcontrollers and other embedded systems. It allows direct
  access to circuit components. In our case, we will be using it to 
  overwrite the flash memory on the Trionic ECU. Normally,
  <a href="#/content/saab/20090306-trionic7-can-bus-connection">connecting via the CAN 
  bus</a> is a more convenient way to flash it, but if that process fails, you
  end up with a dead ECU. The only way to revive it is by attaching a BDM
  controller. Guess what happened to me ;].</p>

  <p>See also:
  <a href="https://txsuite.org/">Trionic Suite</a>,
  <a href="https://www.trionictuning.com/forum/">Trionic Tuning Community</a>
  </p>
  </description>

  <picture name="20090313a.BDM.jpg" title="BDM" date="13.03.2009">
    There's a variety of BDM interfaces available on the market. However,
    this one proved to be most reliable and cost effective. It looks like it's
    made in someone's garage, but it works perfectly, and for EUR 9.50 you
    can't really go wrong.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20090313b.Connectors.jpg" title="Connectors" date="13.03.2009">
    The BDM has a 10-pin connector, but not all pins are actually used, so
    what you really need is a 2x4 connector. I found this old PC motherboard
    and desoldered a couple of jumper bridges out of it.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20090313c.ECU.jpg" title="ECU" date="13.03.2009">
    The ECU circuit has a clearly visible location for a BDM connector. Pins
    1 (marked by the arrow) and 2 are not used, so you don't need to solder
    anything there.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20090313d.Soldered.jpg" title="Soldered" date="13.03.2009">
    Take care while soldering, don't apply too much heat as not to damage the
    leads or the coating. Once finished, check the connections with a tester
    if you have one.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20090313e.Connections.jpg" title="Connections" date="13.03.2009">
    Connect the BDM to the parallel port of your computer. Attach the ribbon
    cable to the ECU, making sure the polarity is correct. The ECU needs to be
    powered up, see <a href="#/content/saab/20090306-trionic7-can-bus-connection">this 
    guide</a> for DC power harness information.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20090313f.In_progress.jpg" title="In progress" date="13.03.2009">
    Finding a PC with a proper LPT port could be challenging these days. In my
    household the only option was this headless Linux server. I had to create
    a bootable USB stick with DOS and BD32 to flash the
    ECU while watching the progress on a projector screen, no less ;]
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
</picture-set>
