<?xml version="1.0"?>
<picture-set title="Saab NG900/9-3: Subframe Brace">

  <description>
  <p>Two-point front suspension brace installation on the 1996 Saab 900 (applies to all 1994-1998 900 and 1999-2002 9-3).</p>

  <h2>Tools:</h2>
  <ul>
    <li>11 mm socket;</li>
    <li>short 11 mm wrench;</li>
    <li>plastic cutting tools;</li>
    <li>ramps or car jack and stands;</li>
    <li>ratchet handle.</li>
  </ul>
  </description>

  <picture name="20050401a.Brace.jpg" title="Brace" date="01.04.2005">
    The brace is just a long metal rod with bolt holes on the ends. It's
    designed is to reinforce the front subframe. There's also a
    <a href="https://www.genuinesaab.com/catalog/product_info.php?products_id=35">6-point
    version</a> avaliable for more serious applications.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050401b.Scissors.jpg" title="Scissors" date="01.04.2005">
    Raise the car.
    Cut the end of the plastic shield on the driver's side to gain the access
    to the opening in the subframe just in front of the control arm attachment
    point. The pruning scissors from the garden work well.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050401c.Bolt.jpg" title="Bolt" date="01.04.2005">
    Locate a small oval hole in the subframe that used to be under the
    shield you just cut. Insert the bolt with a big washer supplied with the
    brace. The purpose of the washer is to distribute the load evently.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050401d.Hole.jpg" title="Hole" date="01.04.2005">
    On the passenger side, there are two shields overlapping. You need to cut
    the end of the lower shield just like you did it on the other side, and
    then make a hole in the belt shield.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050401e.Brace.jpg" title="Brace" date="01.04.2005">
    Attach the brace on one side without tightening the nut, then on the
    other side. Tighten the nuts while holding the bolts with a short
    spanner from inside the subframe.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050401f.Installed.jpg" title="Installed" date="01.04.2005">
    The brace installed. I had to use a couple of washers on both attachment
    points to lower the brace slightly so it clears the downpipe.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
</picture-set>
