<?xml version="1.0"?>
<picture-set title="Saab NG900/9-3: Airbox Inlet Funnel">

  <description>
  An airbox modification performed on a 1996 Saab 900 (applies to all
  1994-1998 900 and 1999-2002 9-3). The alleged goal of this
  silly upgrade was to enlarge the airbox inlet pipe and reduce the airflow
  restriction caused by the narrow original pipe. In reality, it does not
  offer much performance benefit, but amplifies the intake sound just enough
  so you can enjoy it (yet not as loud as an open intake would).
  </description>

  <picture name="20050527a.Airbox.jpg" title="Airbox" date="27.05.2005">
    Locate the airbox, take off the cover and remove the air filter insert.
    Unbolt the bottom half of the airbox (three 10 mm nuts) and pull it out of
    the car.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050527b.Pipe_removed.jpg" title="Pipe removed" date="27.05.2005">
    The original inlet pipe just snaps into its base. Once you unlock the
    two latches, the pipe just slides out.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050527c.Soldering_iron.jpg" title="Soldering iron" date="27.05.2005">
    Cut the base of the pipe. If you don't have a Dremel, a thin soldering
    iron does a great job of melting the plastic...
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050527d.Hole.jpg" title="Hole" date="27.05.2005">
    ...and the base falls out leaving a gaping hole. Use a round file to
    make the edge smoother.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050527e.Funnel.jpg" title="Funnel" date="27.05.2005">
    This $3 funnel from a hardware store will serve as replacement for
    the stock pipe.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050527f.Funnel_cut.jpg" title="Funnel cut" date="27.05.2005">
    The funnel cut to the size. Inner diameter 3", outer 4.5". This is
    the biggest size you can fit between the fender and the headlight.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050527g.Finished.jpg" title="Finished" date="27.05.2005">
    The same soldering iron can be used to "weld" the funnel to the airbox.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050527h.Inside.jpg" title="Inside" date="27.05.2005">
    A thick bead of glue/sealant completes the job from the inside.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20051018.Airbox_inlet.jpg" title="Airbox inlet" date="18.10.2005">
    A close-up of the modified inlet pipe with a headlight removed.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
</picture-set>
