<?xml version="1.0"?>
<picture-set title="Saab 9-5: ACC Air Distribution Motor">

  <description>
  <p>Air distribution motor and lever replacement on a 1999 Saab 9-5. The
  climate control system in the car operates a large air distribution flap,
  which directs the air to the dashboard vents, defrost vents or the
  floor.</p>
  <p>When the system detects a problem with the air distribution flap, it sets
  error code 12 (motor short or open circuit) or 13 (flap jammed) at ACC
  calibration. Most of the time it's the motor itself or the plastic lever
  connecting it to the shaft. This article shows how to remove and replace
  both. You need to re-calibrate the ACC by pressing AUTO+OFF after the work
  is done.</p>
  <h2>Tools:</h2>
  <ul>
    <li>Torx T25 screwdriver: glovebox screws;</li>
    <li>Phillips screwdriver or 8mm socket: stepping motor screws;</li>
    <li>needle-nose pliers: testing the shaft.</li>
  </ul>
  </description>

  <picture name="20080730a.Passenger_footwell.jpg" title="Passenger footwell" date="30.07.2008">
    Unlatch three plastic pins and remove the piece of carpet on the left.
    Then undo four screws holding the plastic panel under the glovebox.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20080730b.Lower_screws.jpg" title="Lower screws" date="30.07.2008">
    Undo the screws under the glovebox.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20080730c.Upper_screws.jpg" title="Upper screws" date="30.07.2008">
    Open the glovebox and undo three more screws along the top.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20080730d.Glovebox.jpg" title="Glovebox" date="30.07.2008">
    Pull the glovebox out. Unplug the lamp connector and disconnect the
    cooling hose from the ACC.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20080730e.Stepping_motor.jpg" title="Stepping motor" date="30.07.2008">
    Unscrew the motor, it's held by two screws with a 8mm hex head and a
    Phillips groove (you choose). Unplug the connector and carefully lift the motor.
    Note the position of the shaft.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20080730f.Plastic_lever.jpg" title="Plastic lever" date="30.07.2008">
    The yellow lever is connected to the rod operating the latches on the floor
    - unhook it first. Pull the lever out of its socket - it takes some effort,
    but you can do it with your fingers.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20080730g.Levers_and_motor.jpg" title="Levers and motor" date="30.07.2008">
    Test motor and inspect the lever. In my case the lever was broken at the
    point where it connects to the shaft operating the flaps. A new lever
    (left) was $16 at the dealer (part 5334693). I had to transfer the little rod socket to
    the new lever. Apply some grease on the outer surface.
    <image width="799" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20080730h.New_lever.jpg" title="New lever" date="30.07.2008">
    Before installing the new lever, reach into the socket with strong
    needle-nose pliers and try turning the shaft to make sure it is not jammed
    completely. You can even pull the shaft out (it's a 8" long square metal
    rod) and spray some lubricant into the hole. Then insert the lever, hook
    up the lower rod and re-assemble everything.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20090621a.Broken_again.jpg" title="Broken again" date="21.06.2009">
    Less than a year later, the lever broke again. As the air
    distribution unit wears with age, these levers
    prove to be too weak to handle the increased friction.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20090621b.Copper_tube.jpg" title="Copper tube" date="21.06.2009">
    I cut a short piece of a 3/8" copper tube and used a soldering iron
    to firmly seat it on the remaining part of the lever.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20090621c.Filled.jpg" title="Filled" date="21.06.2009">
    The tube was then filled with epoxy. I used this wooden stick to shape a
    hole, so the shaft would fit firmly.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
</picture-set>
