<?xml version="1.0"?>
<picture-set title="Saab NG900/9-3: Front Seat Upholstery">

  <description>
  <p>The front seat upholstery repair on a 1996 Saab 900 (should be very similar
  on other Saabs too). The previous owner left a huge tear on a side bolster,
  and the condition of the seat back in whole wasn't the best, so it seemed
  like a good idea to reskin it. We used fabric instead of leather to provide
  superior back support during the club's driving events. It is possible to
  pull the upholstery while the seat is in the car, but it's much easier if
  you <a href="#/content/saab/20041218-saab-ng900-front-seat-removal">remove the seat
  first</a>.</p>

  <b>Tools and supplies:</b>
  <ul>
    <li>two pairs of strong needle nose pliers: to bend the staples;</li>
    <li>long flat screwdriver: to remove the headrest sleeves and lumbar knob;</li>
    <li>upholstery fabric and thread;</li>
    <li>soft foam backing of fiber-fill;</li>
    <li>general sewing supplies.</li>
  </ul>
  </description>

  <picture name="20041218a.The_seat.jpg" title="The seat" date="18.12.2004">
    Here's the seat after I brought it home. You can see that the left bolster
    surface is worn badly and has a huge hole in the middle.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20041218b.Head_support_sleeves.jpg" title="Head support sleeves" date="18.12.2004">
    First, remove the headrest and its support sleeves. Insert a screwdriver
    a couple of centimeters down along the sleeve, press a tab and pull the
    sleeve out.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20041218c.Staples.jpg" title="Staples" date="18.12.2004">
    On the bottom of the seat back, there are five staples that hold the ends
    of the upholstery together. The staples are rather thick, you need two
    pairs of needle nose pliers to handle them.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20041218d.Tension_rod.jpg" title="Tension rod" date="18.12.2004">
    After the staples are gone, pull the fabric apart slightly and disconnect
    the tension rods from the seat frame (there are two of them).
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20041218e.Lumbar_knob.jpg" title="Lumbar knob" date="18.12.2004">
    Remove the lumbar support knob. It comes right off if you give it a good
    pull.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20041218f.Inside_out.jpg" title="Inside out" date="18.12.2004">
    Starting from the bottom of the seat, turn the edges of the skin inside
    out and pull it upward to remove from the frame.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20041218g.More_staples.jpg" title="More staples" date="18.12.2004">
    You will encounter more staples on your way. They connect the tension rods
    to the thick wires attached to the seat frame.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20041218h.Last_staples.jpg" title="Last staples" date="18.12.2004">
    The last couple of staples at the next seam, and the seat cover is
    free. Memorize the locations of the staples, you will have to put them
    back later.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20041218i.Rear_view.jpg" title="Rear view" date="18.12.2004">
    This is how the lumbar adjustment mechanism looks like.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20041218j.Leather_skin.jpg" title="Leather skin" date="18.12.2004">
    The skin is finally removed from the seat. Looks rather untidy.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20041218k.The_seat.jpg" title="The seat" date="18.12.2004">
    The seat without its backrest upholstery. If your seat heaters do not
    work, it's a good time to inspect the heating pads for torn wires (they
    are the two grey squares in the middle).
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20041218l.Seams_undone.jpg" title="Seams undone" date="18.12.2004">
    I'm only replacing the front surface of the seat, so the back remains
    untouched. Undo the seams and note how everything was put together,
    including the tension wire.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20041218m.Layers.jpg" title="Layers" date="18.12.2004">
    It helps to sign the parts on the back. The original upholstery consisted
    of two layers: the leather top and the foam backing.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20041218n.Ribbons.jpg" title="Ribbons" date="18.12.2004">
    These ribbons work as sleeves for the tension wire. Ironing them should help
    later when you will be sewing the fabric back together.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20041218o.Fabric.jpg" title="Fabric" date="18.12.2004">
    Here's some thick upholstery fabric from BouClair, in a reasonably matching shade.
    We bought a bit more in case we'll need to do the other seats in the future.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20041218p.Cut_to_shape.jpg" title="Cut to shape" date="18.12.2004">
    Use the old pieces of leather to cut the fabric to the desired shape.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20041218q.Singer.jpg" title="Singer" date="18.12.2004">
    A trusty old sewing machine.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20041218r.Thread.jpg" title="Thread" date="18.12.2004">
    A spool of strong unholstery thread.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20041218s.Layers.jpg" title="Layers" date="18.12.2004">
    We did not want to reuse the old smelly foam backing, so we used a layer
    of polyester fiber-fill covered with thin fabric in a funny pattern
    for the heck of it.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20041218t.Helga.jpg" title="Helga" date="18.12.2004">
    The essential element of the whole adventure. Helga agreed to help
    out despite having a cold and a sore throat.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20041218u.Stitching.jpg" title="Stitching" date="18.12.2004">
    It is a two-step process. First you sew the upholstery fabric to the
    backing, and then stitch the pieces to each other with the tension wire
    sleeves on the back.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20041218v.Front_complete.jpg" title="Front complete" date="18.12.2004">
    Here's the front section finished. Do not forget that strip at the bottom
    with a wire on it.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20041218w.Back_side.jpg" title="Back side" date="18.12.2004">
    Now you need to attach the new front section to the leather back.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20041218x.Hand_stitching.jpg" title="Hand stitching" date="18.12.2004">
    I'm doing it by hand, using the perforation of the old seams in the
    original leather parts.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20041218y.Dmitry.jpg" title="Dmitry" date="18.12.2004">
    It took me over an hour to do it the right way, but now I can brag that my
    car has <em>"hand-stitched leather"</em> ;). And make that <em>"sport seating
    surfaces"</em> too.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20041218z0.Skin_finished.jpg" title="Top finished" date="18.12.2004">
    Here's the renewed skin finished, waiting to be put back on.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050612a.Bottom.jpg" title="Bottom" date="12.06.2005">
    The bottom is much easier, it is smaller, and there are fewer staples.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050612b.Undone.jpg" title="Undone" date="12.06.2005">
    The only difficult part is the plastic trim around the edge. It makes it
    much harder to sew the side section on later.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050612c.New_fabric.jpg" title="New fabric" date="12.06.2005">
    The fabric is cut to the shape of the old parts.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050612d.Bottom_finished.jpg" title="Bottom finished" date="12.06.2005">
    The new parts are sewn together.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20041218z1.Fitting_the_top.jpg" title="Fitting the top" date="18.12.2004">
    Fitting is the reverse of the removal. Start with the top, fit the headrest
    sleeves to hold the fabric and work your way down restoring the staples
    and making sure the tension wires follow the grooves in the seat foam.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050612e.Done.jpg" title="Done" date="12.06.2005">
    The job is complete. The fabric fits the seat nicely. It also holds you
    better in sharp turns and feels more friendly in very cold or hot weather.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
</picture-set>
