<?xml version="1.0"?>
<picture-set title="Saab NG900/9-3: Control Arm">

  <description>
  <p>Lower control arm replacement on a 1996-1998 Saab 900 and 1999-2002 Saab 9-3.
  The guide also covers polyurethane bushings and ball joint boots. It's not
  necessary to unbolt the caliper (some pictures show it removed), but it gives
  you some extra room around the ball joint.</p>

  <h2>Tools:</h2>
  <ul>
    <li>32 mm (1.25") socket: axle nut;</li>
    <li>24 mm socket: outer poly bushing nut;</li>
    <li>24 mm wrench: outer poly busing bolt;</li>
    <li>18 mm wrench: ball joint nut;</li>
    <li>17 mm socket: wheel bolts;</li>
    <li>15 mm socket: control arm to subframe bolt;</li>
    <li>13 mm socket: lower sway bar link nut, strut mount nuts;</li>
    <li>11 mm wrench: upper part of sway bar link;</li>
    <li>10 mm Allen key: caliper bolts (optional);</li>
    <li>Torx T55 key: original outer bushing bolt;</li>
    <li>torque wrench;</li>
    <li>car jack and axle stands;</li>
    <li>ball joint separator;</li>
    <li>breaker bar;</li>
    <li>two pairs of long nose pliers;</li>
    <li>hacksaw;</li>
    <li>hammer and rubber mallet.</li>
  </ul>
  </description>

  <picture name="20070522a.Axle_nut.jpg" title="Axle nut" date="22.05.2007">
    While the car is still on the ground, pop the cover in the middle of the
    wheel and loosen the axle nut using a 32 mm socket on a large breaker bar.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070522b.Wheel.jpg" title="Wheel" date="22.05.2007">
    Raise the car, secure it on jack stands and remove the front wheel.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070522c.Nuts.jpg" title="Nuts" date="22.05.2007">
    Undo the nuts on the sway bar link, outer bushing and the ball joint.
    If you have OEM outer bushings, you won't be able to undo the bolt just
    yet since the CV joint it blocking it.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070522d.Ball_joint.jpg" title="Ball joint" date="22.05.2007">
    Separate the ball joint using a proper separator. On the other hand, if
    you're planning to replace the arm anyway, you can go ahead and use the
    fork separator.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070522e.Subframe_bolt.jpg" title="Subframe bolt" date="22.05.2007">
    Unbolt the control arm from the subframe. You can see that the 6-point
    brace mounting bar severily limits the access to the control arm bolt.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070522f.Detached.jpg" title="Detached" date="22.05.2007">
    Detach the control arm from the subframe. If you have OEM outer
    bushing bolts, you should have enough clearance to unbolt it now.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070522g.Used_replacement.jpg" title="Used replacement" date="22.05.2007">
    I'm using a replacement from a junk yard - it comes with a tight ball joint.
    The bushings aren't as good, but they will have to go anyway.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070522h.Bad_boot.jpg" title="Bad boot" date="22.05.2007">
    This is what happens when the ball joint boot cracks and runs out of grease.
    The whole arm is junk now.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070522i.Inner_bushing.jpg" title="Inner bushing" date="22.05.2007">
    I need to transfer poly bushings from the old arm, so the rubber ones have
    to go. A small gear puller easily takes care of the inner one.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070522j.Outer_bushing.jpg" title="Outer bushing" date="22.05.2007">
    The bigger outer bushing can also be pressed out with a gear puller, at least
    the rubber part of it. Use a pan to catch the hydraulic oil that will leak
    out.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070522k.Hacksaw.jpg" title="Hacksaw" date="22.05.2007">
    The metal sleeve of the outer bushing is a tougher task. Start by assembling
    a hacksaw inside the bushing and cutting through the sleeve.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070522l.Sleeve_cut.jpg" title="Sleeve cut" date="22.05.2007">
    Then flip the arm around and cut the sleeve on the opposite side. After
    that you can chisel out the two halves of the sleeve.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070522m.Poly_bushings.jpg" title="Poly bushings" date="22.05.2007">
    Spread some lubricant on the poly bushings and use a rubber mallet to
    drive them in. Discard the old ball joint boot.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070522n.New_boot.jpg" title="New boot" date="22.05.2007">
    Pack the joint with fresh grease and slide a new boot on.
    Make sure the boot is seated correctly on the rim and use a pair of long
    nose pliers to fit the retaining ring. Take extra care not to rip the boot.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070522o.Back_in.jpg" title="Back in" date="22.05.2007">
    Tighten the subframe bolt to 85 ft-lbs and the outer bolt to 120 ft-lbs
    (68 ft-lbs if you have an OEM bolt).
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070522p.Ball_joint.jpg" title="Ball joint" date="22.05.2007">
    Connect the ball joint and tighten the nut to 55 ft-lbs, sway bar link to
    7 ft-lbs, wheels bolt to 81 ft-lbs and axle nut to 214 ft-lbs.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
</picture-set>
