<?xml version="1.0"?>
<picture-set title="Saab NG900/9-3: Front Seat Removal">

  <description>
  <p>The front seat removal procedure for a 1996 Saab 900. I had to take the
  driver's seat out on my project car to replace the upholstery torn by the
  previous owner. The installation is the reverse of removal. When fitting the
  bolts, tighten the inner side first (factory recommended torque 22 ft-lbs).</p>

  <h2>Tools:</h2>
  <ul>
    <li>Torx T40 socket: seat track bolts;</li>
    <li>Torx T27 socket or screwdriver: cowl screws;</li>
    <li>long flat screwdriver: to reach the seatbelt latch release;</li>
    <li>small wire cutters: to cut a zip tie under the seat;</li>
    <li>a new zip tie;</li>
    <li>torque wrench.</li>
  </ul>
  </description>

  <picture name="20041218a.Rear_bolts.jpg" title="Rear bolts" date="18.12.2004">
    Move the seat forward as much as possible and undo the rear bolts (Torx T40).
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20041218b.Front_bolts.jpg" title="Front bolts" date="18.12.2004">
    Move the seat back and undo the front bolts. Be careful as the seat
    may fall backwards at this point.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20041218c.Connectors.jpg" title="Connectors" date="18.12.2004">
    If you have seat airbags, disconnect the battery now. Otherwise you will get
    an Airbag warning light once you unplug the seat.
    Detach the electrical connectors and cut the zip tie securing the cable. You can lift
    the seat now. The only thing that still ties it to the car is the seat belt.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20041218d.Cowl_front.jpg" title="Cowl front" date="18.12.2004">
    Remove the screws in front of the cowl and in the middle (Torx T27).
    The clearance is tight, you need a long screwdriver, but it won't
    fit straight.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20041218e.Cowl_rear.jpg" title="Cowl rear" date="18.12.2004">
    The last screw in the rear. The cowl removal is not really necessary, but
    it gives you a detailed view of the seat belt attachment. You can clearly
    see the torn part of my seat cover here.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20041218f.Seatbelt.jpg" title="Seatbelt" date="18.12.2004">
    Press the tab in the middle and unhook the belt. You can normally reach
    this tab with a long flat screwdriver without removing the cowl. The seat
    is free now.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
</picture-set>
