<?xml version="1.0"?>
<picture-set title="Saab 9-5: Serpentine Belt">

  <description>
  <p>Serpentine belt and pulley replacement on a 4-cylinder Saab 9-5.</p>

  <h2>Tools and supplies:</h2>
  <ul>
    <li>serpentine belt: short (Saab #5590344, NAPA #25060950) or standard
      (Saab #4899548);</li>
    <li>pulleys: small idle pulley (#4356127) and tensioner pulley (#5172184);</li>
    <li>jack stands;</li>
    <li>18 mm socket: engine mount central nut;</li>
    <li>16 mm socket: engine mount side bolts;</li>
    <li>13 mm socket: idle pulley bolt;</li>
    <li>10 mm socket: power steering hose clamp;</li>
    <li>8 mm socket: belt shield screws;</li>
    <li>8 mm Allen key: belt tensioner bolt;</li>
    <li>6 mm Allen key: belt tensioner pulley bolt;</li>
    <li>3 mm long Allen key: belt tensioner lock;</li>
    <li>1/2" socket extension: for use as a tension release lever;</li>
    <li>torque wrench.</li>
  </ul>
  </description>

  <picture name="20040929a.Start.jpg" title="Start" date="29.09.2004">
    Raise the car and remove the right front wheel. The pictures are a bit
    dark, it was 23:00 ;)
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20040929b.Belt_shield.jpg" title="Belt shield" date="29.09.2004">
    Remove the plastic belt shield: 5 screws with 8 mm hex head.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20040929c.Engine_mount.jpg" title="Engine mount" date="29.09.2004">
    Remove the bracket on top of the engine mount: the central nut is 18 mm, and
    the four bolts on the sides need a 16 mm socket.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20040929d.Steering_hose.jpg" title="Steering hose" date="29.09.2004">
    Unbolt a hose clamp under the crankshaft pulley so you can fit a wedge
    under the power steering line (10 mm socket).
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20040929e.Engine_support.jpg" title="Engine support" date="29.09.2004">
    WIS recommends inserting a wedge between the engine and the frame (I used
    this big wrench). It seems that you still need to jack up the engine from
    below as you might need to move it a bit later to align the enging mount
    holes.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20040929g.Pulleys.jpg" title="Pulleys" date="29.09.2004">
    A 1/2" socket extension fits perfectly as a lever to relieve the strain
    off the belt tensioner. Once the belt is off, check these two pulleys --
    their bearings will likely be worn, loose and rattling if the car is
    over 100K km.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20040929h.Allen_8_mm.jpg" title="Allen 8 mm" date="29.09.2004">
    The clearance around the tensioner pulley is very tight, so it's often
    easier to remove the entire tensioner. You'll need an 8 mm Allen key for
    that. Mounting torque 33 ft-lbs.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20040929i.Tensioner.jpg" title="Tensioner" date="29.09.2004">
    Once the tensioner is off, soak the pulley bolt with a good solvent before
    taking on it. The 6 mm Allen key socket on the bolt is very shallow and
    easy to strip.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20040929j.Pulley.jpg" title="Pulley" date="29.09.2004">
    Luckily, the replacement tensioner pulley comes with new bolt that has a
    good old hex head.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20040929k.Idler.jpg" title="Idler" date="29.09.2004">
    The small idler hasn't changed. You need a 13 mm socket for that bolt.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20040929l.Belt.jpg" title="Belt" date="29.09.2004">
    The new belt is shorter than the old one. My local dealership didn't
    have this part in stock, so I picked up a belt from a NAPA store
    (part #25060950).
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20040929m.Belt.jpg" title="Belt" date="29.09.2004">
    Note how the new belt goes directly from the small idler to the steering
    pump, bypassing the big idler in the middle (the idler is hiding behind
    the engine mount).
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20040929n.Engine_mount.jpg" title="Engine mount" date="29.09.2004">
    Fit the engine mount bracket with a tightening torque of 39 ft-lbs for the
    bolts and 78 ft-lbs for the central nut. Fit the belt shield, the wheel,
    and lower the car to the floor.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
</picture-set>
