<?xml version="1.0"?>
<picture-set title="Saab 9-5: Rear Anti-Roll Bar">

  <description>
  <p>Rear anti-roll bar installation on a Saab 9-5. The thin original bar on this
  Linear model gets replaced with a thicker and stiffer Aero anti-roll bar
  to help reduce body roll and improve cornering.</p>

  <h2>Tools:</h2>
  <ul>
    <li>17 mm socket: wheel bolts;</li>
    <li>16 mm socket: link bolts;</li>
    <li>15 mm wrench: bushing clamp nuts;</li>
    <li>torque wrench;</li>
    <li>car jack and axle stands.</li>
  </ul>
  </description>

  <picture name="20070930a.Jack_stands.jpg" title="Jack stands" date="30.09.2007">
    Raise the car, secure it on jack stands and take the wheels off. Both sides
    need to be in the air, so the rear suspension is level.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070930b.Link.jpg" title="Link" date="30.09.2007">
    Detach the bolt holding the anti-roll bar link to the trailing arm. Unclip
    the ABS sensor wire. Undo the nut on the bushing using a wrench (a socket
    won't fit in there).
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070930c.Out.jpg" title="Out" date="30.09.2007">
    Pull the anti-roll bar out through the right side of the car. See the tip
    below on how to wiggle it through.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070930d.Old_vs_new.jpg" title="Old vs new" date="30.09.2007">
    The original bar on the 1999 Linear was 15 mm thick. The Aero bar is 17 mm.
    It comes with new bushings and links attached.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070930e.Tight_fit.jpg" title="Tight fit" date="30.09.2007">
    Fit the new bar back in. Rotate the driver side bushing backwards so it
    can squeeze between the exhaust pipe and the subframe. If it's not going
    through, unhook the muffler hangers and lower the muffler to pass the
    bar through.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070930f.Installed.jpg" title="Installed" date="30.09.2007">
    Re-connect the anti-roll bar to the suspension and tighten the bushing nuts
    and the link bolts to 40 ft-lbs. Attach the cable clips. Fit the wheels,
    tighten the lug bolts to 81 ft-lbs and lower the car to the ground.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
</picture-set>
