<?xml version="1.0"?>
<picture-set title="Saab B204/B234: Crankshaft and Pistons">

  <description>
  <p>Piston and crankshaft installation on a Saab B204/B234 engine. This engine
  is found in all four-cylinder Saab 900 and 9000 from 1994 to 1998, as well
  as 1999 9-3. Newer cars have lighter pistons and a slightly different
  block but the procedure is still the same.</p>

  <h2>Tools and supplies:</h2>
  <ul>
    <li>Torx E16 socket: main crankshaft cap bolts;</li>
    <li>12-point 14 mm socket: connecting rod cap nuts;</li>
    <li>6-point 14 mm socket: oil jets;</li>
    <li>torque wrench;</li>
    <li>piston ring compressor;</li>
    <li>piston ring expander;</li>
    <li>fresh engine oil.</li>
  </ul>
  </description>

  <picture name="20060621a.Cleaning.jpg" title="Cleaning" date="21.06.2006">
    Before installing new piston rings, clean the pistons and scrape all
    the ring grooves with an old ring to remove all dirt and reposits.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060621b.Rings.jpg" title="Rings" date="21.06.2006">
    Aftermarket rings often come as a complete set, bagged and labelled for an
    easy installation. Saab OEM rings would come as a "per piston" set.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060621c.Testing.jpg" title="Testing" date="21.06.2006">
    Oil the cylinder bores slightly and push the rings in with a piston top
    one by one. Check the fit and measure the gap between the ring ends.
    The factory specifies a 0.30-0.50 mm gap for the first compression ring
    and a 0.16-0.65 mm for the second. If the rings were ordered correctly for
    your application (e.g. standard size), you should not have to adjust them.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060621e.Rings_ready.jpg" title="Rings ready" date="21.06.2006">
    The first compression ring is a solid metal ring. The second is a scraper
    type and might come with an expander ring (Saab OEM kits don't have
    expander rings). The third ring is a multi-piece oil scraper, which has
    two thin rails with a spacer between them, as well as an optional expander.
    Have some oil ready to lubricate the rings before installation.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060621d.Ring_compressor.jpg" title="Ring tool" date="21.06.2006">
    Although it's possible to install compression rings with your bare hands, it's much
    easier with a ring expander. Use some old rings to practice. The #2s
    seem to be more fragile, I broke a couple checking how far they would stretch ;)
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060621f.Expander_A.jpg" title="Expander A" date="21.06.2006">
    The key point in installing piston rings is to fit them so the gaps of the
    neighbor rings are as far from each other as possible. Start with the oil
    scraper ring. Turn the piston so you're looking at the connecting rod pin,
    and fit the expander ring (if you have it).
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060621g.Rail_B.jpg" title="Rail B" date="21.06.2006">
    Turn the piston 90 degrees and fit the lower scraper rail.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060621h.Spacer_C.jpg" title="Spacer C" date="21.06.2006">
    Turn the piston another 90 degrees and fit the spacer so its gap is
    on the opposite side from the expander ring.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060621i.Rail_D.jpg" title="Rail D" date="21.06.2006">
    Finally, turn the piston yet another 90 degrees and fit the upper scraper
    rail.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060621j.Ring_2_Expander.jpg" title="Ring 2 Expander" date="21.06.2006">
    Go back to the wrist pin and fit the expander ring for the compression
    ring #2 (if you have it).
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060621k.Compression_Ring_2.jpg" title="Compression Ring 2" date="21.06.2006">
    Turn the piston 180 degrees and fit the lower compression ring. The ridge
    on the ring should look down (the ring will likely have "top/bottom"
    markings on it).
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060621l.Compression_Ring_1.jpg" title="Compression Ring 1" date="21.06.2006">
    Fit the remaining top compression ring so the gap on it is on the opposite
    side from the compression ring #2.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060621m.Crankshaft_bearings.jpg" title="Crankshaft bearings" date="21.06.2006">
    Crankshaft bearings come as thin semi-round metal shells with special
    coating on them. Be sure to verify the label on the box before opening
    as no supplier will take them back if you remove the protective film.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060621n.Engine_block.jpg" title="Engine block" date="21.06.2006">
    Secure the engine block on the stand and throroughly clean the mating
    surfaces.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060621o.Oil_jets.jpg" title="Oil jets" date="21.06.2006">
    Attach the piston cooling oil jets (14 mm socket), ensuring their
    correct orientation.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060621p.Main_bearings.jpg" title="Main bearings" date="21.06.2006">
    Carefully place five main bearing shells in their sockets, matching
    the notch on one side. Avoid touching their surface with anything,
    including your bare hands, as it would introduce dirt.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060621q.Thrust_washers.jpg" title="Thrust washers" date="21.06.2006">
    Install the thrust washers on both sides of the #3 bearing. The side
    where the part number is embossed should face the bearing.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060621r.Crankshaft.jpg" title="Crankshaft" date="21.06.2006">
    Lubricate the bearings and place the crankshaft in position. Mind the
    thrust washers as they like to drop on the floor at the first touch of
    the crankshaft.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060621s.Main_caps.jpg" title="Main caps" date="21.06.2006">
    Clean and prepare the main bearing caps. They are numbered 1 to 5,
    starting from the timing cover.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060621t.Main_bearing_tops.jpg" title="Main bearing tops" date="21.06.2006">
    Place the remaining main bearings into their caps, lubricate them and
    install the caps (they only fit one way).
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060621u.Bolts.jpg" title="Bolts" date="21.06.2006">
    Tighten the bolts to 81 ft-lbs (Torx E16 socket).
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060621v.Connecting_rod.jpg" title="Connecting rod" date="21.06.2006">
    On to the piston installation. Wrap the studs on the connecting rods
    to avoid scratching the crankshaft while the piston is being inserted.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060621w.Piston_ring_compressor.jpg" title="Piston ring compressor" date="21.06.2006">
    Put the piston half-way into the cylinder and compress the rings with
    a special tool.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060621x.Piston_in.jpg" title="Piston in" date="21.06.2006">
    Tap the piston gently with a rubber hammer handle until it fully enters
    the cylinder.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060621y.Rod_cap.jpg" title="Rod cap" date="21.06.2006">
    Place the bearing shell into the rod, oil it and tap the piston further
    until the rod is in full contact with the crankshaft. Place the other
    shell into the cap and put the cap on.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060621z.Complete.jpg" title="Complete" date="21.06.2006">
    Install the remaining three pistons. The rods and rod caps are numbered
    1 to 4 from the timing cover. The nuts need a 12-point 14 mm socket,
    tighten to 35 ft-lbs.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
</picture-set>
