<?xml version="1.0"?>
<picture-set title="Saab NG900: Audio Upgrade">

  <description>
  <p>Audio system upgrade on a 1995 Saab 900 SE convertible. The goal of this
  project was to improve the sound in the car. I kept the factory head
  unit because it has a reasonable sound quality, integrates with the SID
  and has a nice stock look. The remaining components were, however, replaced
  completely - new speakers, new wiring and a more powerful four-channel
  amplifier.</p>

  <p>The job was done as a part of the car rebuild, so the interior is shown
  partially stripped. For dash removal and other interior disassembly
  issues refer to other documents.</p>
  </description>

  <picture name="20060715a.Front_speakers.jpg" title="Front speakers" date="15.07.2006">
    Infinity Reference 6010cs component speakers. The tweeters will go up
    on the dash, and the woofers are a perfect match for the factory 6.5"
    mounting locations in the doors.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060715b.Rear_speakers.jpg" title="Rear speakers" date="15.07.2006">
    Infinity Reference 9613i three-way speakers. These 9x6" speakers were
    purchased to hatchback specifications, but I'm hoping to fit them
    instead of the 5.25" factory speakers in the rear.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060715c.Amplifier.jpg" title="Amplifier" date="15.07.2006">
    Infinity Reference 7541a four-channel amplifier. This should have the
    power to produce a sufficient volume at highway speeds with the roof down,
    and has just the right size to fit into the ski pass-through.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060715d.Wiring_kit.jpg" title="Wiring kit" date="15.07.2006">
    An amplifier wiring kit from eBay. It contains shielded interconnects,
    12 gauge OFC speaker wire, 4 gauge power lines, fuses, connectors, wire
    ties and everything else you will need to rewire your stereo.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060806a.Interconnects.jpg" title="Interconnects" date="06.08.2006">
    The head unit has a proper pre-amp output. A DIN-8 jack might be
    hard to locate, but I was fortunate to find a female connector that
    plugs right into the factory amplifier cable. Solder it to the interconnect
    cable, you will need the four channels and the "amp turn-on" signal. Most
    interconnects will already come with an integrated turn-on wire.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060806b.Stock_amp.jpg" title="Stock amp" date="06.08.2006">
    If you have an SE model, it will come with an external 40 Watt amplifier.
    It has three harnesses connected to it: a DIN-8 cable from the head unit,
    door speaker wires and power. Keep the wiring and remove the amp. They
    are in demand since these SE audio kits (amplifier and door speakers) cost
    good money at the dealer. Consider selling it to a fellow Saab owner.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060806c.Connected.jpg" title="Connected" date="06.08.2006">
    Plug the interconnects into the DIN-8 jack and route the cable to your
    preferred amplifier location.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060806d.Door_harness.jpg" title="Door harness" date="06.08.2006">
    The doors have a fancy weather-proof harness for all electrical wiring,
    so there's no way to feed a new speaker cable through. The only option
    is to use factory wiring.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060806e.Speaker_wire.jpg" title="Speaker wire" date="06.08.2006">
    It looks like a good idea to keep the original connectors. If they don't
    fit your speakers, splice into the wires or use a short extention cable.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060806f.Door_speaker.jpg" title="Door speaker" date="06.08.2006">
    The 6.5" speakers fit perfectly into the factory mounting
    brackets. There's more than enough room inside the door, so don't
    worry about your speakers being too deep.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060806g.Adapters.jpg" title="Adapters" date="06.08.2006">
    Small tweeters obviously won't mount that easily into the 3.5"
    speaker socket up on the dash. I cut a pair of plastic adapters using
    an old speaker as a template. Some manufacturers offer similar plates
    with their speaker mounting kits.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060806h.Tweeter.jpg" title="Tweeter" date="06.08.2006">
    Tweeter on the dash. The Infinity kit came with a clever mount that
    allowed to rotate the speakers and tilt them forward for better
    sound stage positioning.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060806i.Crossover.jpg" title="Crossover" date="06.08.2006">
    There's just enough rooms to fit the crossovers under the tweeters so
    you won't have to extend short tweeter wires.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060806j.Crossover.jpg" title="Crossover" date="06.08.2006">
    Connect all the speaker wires and secure the crossovers so they don't
    rattle. I found it convenient to zip-tie them to the air vents.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060806k.Harness.jpg" title="Harness" date="06.08.2006">
    Feed the woofer leads from the crossovers and plug them into the old door
    speaker harness that used to be connected to the factory amplifier.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060808a.New_vs_old.jpg" title="New vs old" date="08.08.2006">
    The rear speakers presented a challenge, since my replacements were
    almost twice as big as the originals.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060808b.Template.jpg" title="Template" date="08.08.2006">
    A paper template attached to the side panel shows that the magnets won't
    fit into the old hole, and some of the metal has to be trimmed.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060808c.Hole_cut.jpg" title="Hole cut" date="08.08.2006">
    A couple of minutes with heavy duty Dremel cut-off wheels gets the job
    done. Prime and paint the cut to prevent the rust from spreading.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060808d.Supports.jpg" title="Supports" date="08.08.2006">
    Due to the way the speaker should be tilted, all the support brackets
    should have a different length. I used some basic Home Depot parts and
    cut them to size.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060808e.Rear_speaker.jpg" title="Rear speaker" date="08.08.2006">
    The rear speaker is mounted securely. It was a tight fit with the panel
    cover, but it did fit with no struggle. I just had to trim some foam inside
    the panel cover.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060808f.Positive_cable.jpg" title="Positive cable" date="08.08.2006">
    The power for the amplifier has to come directly from the battery. Route
    the cable to the battery and install a fuse matching the current specified
    for your amplifier.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060808g.Firewall.jpg" title="Firewall" date="08.08.2006">
    The rubber grommet by the driver side strut tower looks like a perfect
    spot to pass the cable through the firewall.
    <a href="#/content/saab/20051105-saab-ng900-boost-gauge">This
    guide</a> shows how to remove the fuse box that hides the grommet.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060808h.Cable_routing.jpg" title="Cable routing" date="08.08.2006">
    Route the cable down to the floor and further back along the door sill.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060808i.Cables.jpg" title="Cables" date="08.08.2006">
    There's a grounding point on the driver side rear panel - a great location
    to hook up the negative cable for the amplifier.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060808j.Amplifier.jpg" title="Amplifier" date="08.08.2006">
    Mount the amplifier (mine was a perfect size for the ski pass-through) and
    connect all the wires.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060808k.Connected.jpg" title="Connected" date="08.08.2006">
    Bolt the positive cable to the battery and turn the system on. Enjoy your
    music!
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
</picture-set>
