<?xml version="1.0"?>
<picture-set title="Saab NG900/9-3: Rear Suspension">

  <description>
  <p>A rear suspension upgrade performed on a 1996 Saab 900SE turbo.</p>
  
  <p>The goal
  was to replace the old and worn components with new parts. The
  pictures show the work done at the right left corner. The job is much easier
  than <a href="#/content/saab/20050210-saab-ng900-front-suspension">the front</a>,
  and takes a couple of hours if you are prepared. Parts from
  <a href="https://www.shox.com">shox.com</a> and eBay.</p>

  <b>Tools and supplies:</b>
  <ul>
    <li>17 mm socket: wheel bolts, lower damper nuts;</li>
    <li>17 mm open wrench: Bilstein upper damper nut;</li>
    <li>16 mm wrench and socket: original upper damper nut;</li>
    <li>5 mm Allen key: top of the Bilstein damper rod;</li>
    <li>car jack and axle stands;</li>
    <li>breaker bar;</li>
    <li>torque wrench;</li>
    <li>impact wrench (recommended);</li>
    <li>vice grips;</li>
    <li>several thin metal strips and two pry bars;</li>
    <li>sharp knife or cardboard cutter;</li>
    <li>anti-seize, soap solution, rust solvent.</li>
  </ul>
  </description>

  <picture name="20050215a.Knife.jpg" title="Knife" date="15.02.2005">
    If this is the first time the rear shocks are being replaced on your car,
    you need to cut out the flaps in the trunk upholstery. They are clearly
    marked, and are easy to cut with a sharp knife.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050215b.Impact_wrench.jpg" title="Impact wrench" date="15.02.2005">
    If the car has a considerable age, there's a good chance the top of the
    damper rod would be covered with rust. An impact wrench is a quick and
    easy way to move the stuck upper nut (16 mm socket). Do not remove the nut
    completely yet.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050215c.Car_jacked_up.jpg" title="Car jacked up" date="15.02.2005">
    Jack up the car and take the wheels off. Yes, this is salt on the car
    (even though it's been washed just a couple of days before it went to
    the garage).
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050215d.Lower_nut.jpg" title="Lower nut" date="15.02.2005">
    Support the rear axle and undo the lower nut on the damper (17 mm socket).
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050215e.Springs.jpg" title="Springs" date="15.02.2005">
    Once both dampers are disconnected from the suspension, you can lower the
    rear axle and remove the springs from their seats.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050215f.Upper_nut.jpg" title="Upper nut" date="15.02.2005">
    Take off the upper nut and the washer. There's no need to replace the rubber
    bushing if it's in a good shape (or stuck to the body :). Some shock kits will include replacement bushings
    and washers.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050215g.Damper.jpg" title="Damper" date="15.02.2005">
    Remove the old damper. Note the position of the washer and the lower rubber
    bushing.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050215h.Bump_stop.jpg" title="Bump stop" date="15.02.2005">
    The bump stop was a huge pain to remove. I struggled for a whlie using thin metal strips
    as guides between the bump stop and the spring (e.g. thin spanners), and
    kept spraying it with soapy water or silicone while trying to pry
    it out. <EM>Here's a
    <a href="#/content/saab/20061014-saab-ng900-rear-springs-intrax-vs-eibach">simple alternative</a>
    suggested by a reader.</EM>
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050215i.New_vs_old.jpg" title="New vs old" date="15.02.2005">
    The comparison between the old and new parts. Not much to comment here,
    the Intrax springs are shorter (and of the progressive design), while
    the Bilstein dampers are stiffer and visibly stronger.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050215j.Bump_stop.jpg" title="Bump stop" date="15.02.2005">
    It helps to use the weight of the car to push the bump stop into the
    new springs. Use a jack on the rear axle and keep spraying the bump stop
    with soapy water. It goes half-way in, then you need to take it out and
    push it in the rest of the way by hand.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050215k.Fitting.jpg" title="Fitting" date="15.02.2005">
    Fit new springs and dampers. Note the location of the coil ends on the
    old springs (they were positioned with colour markings looking rearward),
    and place the new springs accordingly. Tighten the lower damper nut
    to 45 ft-lbs (17 mm socket).
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050215l.Upper_nut.jpg" title="Upper nut" date="15.02.2005">
    Put the wheels on, lower the car and tighten the upper nut on the dampers
    to 15 ft-lbs (5 mm Allen key and 17 mm wrench). Close the flaps you cut
    in the trunk upholstery. This was much easier than
    <a href="#/content/saab/20050210-saab-ng900-front-suspension">the front</a>,
    wasn't it? ;)
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
</picture-set>
