<?xml version="1.0"?>
<picture-set title="Saab NG900/9-3: DIY Short Shifter Housing">

  <description>
  <p>Short shifter modification on the 1995 Saab 900. This was done on a budget
  using a leftover scrap piece of an exhaust pipe, but proved surprisingly effective.
  The procedure also works on all 1994-1998 900, 1999-2002 9-3 and most 9-5 models.</p>

  <p>The shifter housing
  has to be removed from the car to perform the modification. For removal
  instructions on NG900 and 9-3, refer to
  <a href="#/content/saab/20070617-saab-ng900-shifter-housing-removal/">this guide</a>.
  A careful <a href="#/content/saab/20050325-saab-ng900-shifter-alignment/">alignment</a>
  has to be performed after re-installation, so it's perfectly centered and
  does not rub inside the housing. The reverse lock remains fully
  functional with this modification.</p>

  <p>The main idea is to raise the fulcrum point of the shifter by moving the
  ball up on the stalk and lifting the ball socket on the housing. This
  results in a noticeably shorter longtitudinal throw and "meatier" shifter
  feel. If overdone, however, the shifter becomes too heavy to operate
  comfortably (at least when you're used to the feel of the stock shifter).
  Use care and consideration when choosing the adjustment amount.</p>

  <p>The biggest amount you can raise the ball by is 30 mm. This will shorten
  the throw almost by half. I measured the knob travel between the 3rd and
  4th gear at 6" in stock configuration and 3.25" when shortened
  to the max. This much adjustment already pushes the limits of the shifter
  housing, so it needs to be trimmed some, and the action becomes quite heavy.
  The recommended adjustment for most people would be about 20 mm.</p>
  </description>

  <picture name="20070617a.Reverse_lock.jpg" title="Reverse lock" date="17.06.2007">
    Undo the screw holding the reverse lock plate (Torx T30). Detach the
    plastic lever leading to the ignition lock from its ball socket and
    remove the plate.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070617b.Linkage_rod.jpg" title="Linkage rod" date="17.06.2007">
    Undo the bolt holding the long linkage rod to the bottom of the shifter.
    Older cars use a bolt with a Torx T30 head, newer bolts come with a 13 mm
    hex head.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070617c.Spring.jpg" title="Spring" date="17.06.2007">
    Use needle nose pliers to unhook the spring from the plastic housing.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070617d.Stick.jpg" title="Stick" date="17.06.2007">
    Turn the plastic retainer that holds the ball and lift the shifter rod out.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070617e.Knob.jpg" title="Knob" date="17.06.2007">
    Pulling the knob off the rod takes considerable force, be careful not to
    break it. In most cases you won't even need to do that. Just cut 20-30 mm
    off the bottom of the plastic sleeve.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070617f.Ball.jpg" title="Ball" date="17.06.2007">
    The ball is secured with two snap rings. Unseat the snap rings from
    their grooves, and you can push the ball back and forth along the rod.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070617g.Relocating.jpg" title="Relocating" date="17.06.2007">
    One option is to cut a new groove 30 mm away from the old upper groove.
    This is the limit the shifter can be adjusted to. 30 mm will already be
    pushing the limits of the shifter housing, and the shifter will be very
    heavy.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070617h.Cutting.jpg" title="Cutting" date="17.06.2007">
    The better option would be to cut TWO new grooves about 20-25 mm up from the
    old ones. This way you will have more clearance inside the housing,
    and the shifter will feel a bit lighter. A rotary cutter does the job here.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070617i.New_position.jpg" title="New position" date="17.06.2007">
    Move the ball into the new position and secure the snap rings in their
    grooves.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070617i2.MP_shifter.jpg" title="MP shifter" date="17.06.2007">
    A third option would be to use an adjustable shifter rod from MP Performance
    if you still can source one - they don't make those anymore.
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070617j.Pipe.jpg" title="Pipe" date="17.06.2007">
    This 2.75" O.D. piece of pipe will serve to raise the fulcrum point.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070617k.Marking_up.jpg" title="Marking up" date="17.06.2007">
    Mark the pipe to make the flaps that will extend above the plastic latches.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070617l.First_cut.jpg" title="First cut" date="17.06.2007">
    Cut away excess metal. Try to be precise, the flaps must closely match
    the width of the grooves they go into for a tighter fit.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070617m.Cut_off_line.jpg" title="Cut off line" date="17.06.2007">
    Mark the bottom flaps and rectangular slots for plastic latches. Take
    precise measurements, so there won't be any slack with the latches
    locked. The height of the extender should be equal to the distance you
    moved the ball, i.e. 20-25 mm.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070617n.Cutting_finished.jpg" title="Cutting finished" date="17.06.2007">
    Cutting a fancy profile in a thick mild steel pipe is not a lot of fun.
    I used up a dozen cut-off wheels and switched to the old good hack saw for
    the final horizontal cut.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070617o.Deburring.jpg" title="Deburring" date="17.06.2007">
    Take your time cleaning and deburring the extender. Check the fit with the
    plastic ball socket and adjust if needed.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070617p.Ready_to_fit.jpg" title="Ready to fit" date="17.06.2007">
    The lower flaps should be cut a bit deeper into the body of the extender
    so they can be bent inward in the middle.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070617q.In_position.jpg" title="In position" date="17.06.2007">
    Position the extender in the shifter housing so the lower flaps fit the holes
    previously occupied by plastic latches.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070617r.Flaps_bent.jpg" title="Flaps bent" date="17.06.2007">
    Bend the flaps outward to secure the extender in place. If you need extra
    strength, you can make the flaps longer, drill through and screw them onto
    the housing, but I've found they hold pretty well when bent like this.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070701a.Screws.jpg" title="Screws" date="01.07.2007">
    Here's an alternative version where the extender is secured by four screws.
    The opening in the shifter housing is trimmed to allow for extra movement.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070617s.Plastic_socket.jpg" title="Plastic socket" date="17.06.2007">
    Slide the plastic ball socket in until the latches click. It should fit
    tightly if you followed the measurements. Again, you can drill through the
    flaps and secure them to the plastic housing with small screws. 
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070617u.Trimming.jpg" title="Trimming" date="17.06.2007">
    If you went to the full 30 mm on the shifter rod, you might have to not
    only trim the housing, but also grind the lower bolt so it's flush
    with the surface of the nut on the linkage rod.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070617t.Old_vs_new.jpg" title="Old vs new" date="17.06.2007">
    I had a luxury of having an extra housing to experiment with. Here's the
    original housing next to the modified version.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070617v.New_handle.jpg" title="New handle" date="17.06.2007">
    My wooden knob is transferred to the new housing. The plastic sleeve is cut
    about 25 mm shorter at the bottom.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070617w.Ignition_lock.jpg" title="Ignition lock" date="17.06.2007">
    The ignition lock is installed into the modified housing.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070617x.Reverse_lock.jpg" title="Reverse lock" date="17.06.2007">
    Next, the reverse locking plate goes in. Check if it works correctly
    before installing the shifter back into the car.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070617z.5th_gear_catch.jpg" title="5th gear catch" date="17.06.2007">
    The bottom part of the plastic stalk sleeve can be re-attached using glue or
    a small hose clamp. And the flimsy 5th gear catch needs to be reinforced so 
    you don't bend it every time you shift into 5th.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070701b.New_version.jpg" title="New version" date="01.07.2007">
    An updated version of the modified housing with a metal 5th gear catch.
    The plastic ball socket is bolted to the extender for extra strength.
    <image width="800" height="599" />
  </picture>
</picture-set>
