<?xml version="1.0"?>
<picture-set title="Saab NG900/9-3: Engine Removal">

  <description>
  <p>Engine removal on a 1995 Saab 900 SE turbo.</p>

  <p>This job was performed as a part of a car rebuild, so you see more parts
  taken off the car than it's usually required to pull just the engine.
  It also makes it easier to access everything and see where things are
  (which is good for a photoshoot).</p>

  <p>Before the engine can be removed from the car, it has to be freed
  from all the wires and hoses connecting it to other components inside the
  engine compartment. This section covers most of those, although you need
  to use your common sense and mind any design differences applicable to
  your model. It might not cover trivial procedures like belts or hoses,
  it's assumed that if you're taking on the engine, you have
  sufficient mechanical knowledge about the car.</p>

  <p>Once everything is disconnected, the engine is ready for removal.
  There are multiple options for engine extraction, which mostly depend on the
  equipment available to you:</p>

  <ol>
    <li>If you have a lift and a support table, you can raise the car,
      roll the table under the subframe, unbolt the subframe and side
      engine mounts, and lower the whole engine and transmission assembly
      resting on the subframe onto the table without taking it apart.</li>
    <li>If you have a lift and a crane, you can suspend the engine with the
      support beam, raise the car, unbolt and drop the subframe, and then
      use the crane to lower the engine and transmission to the floor.</li>
    <li>And finally, if you're doing it on jack stands, the only way is
      to remove the engine is through the top. You can attempt it without
      removing the transmission, but the space is rather tight, and unbolting
      the transmission is easy, so lifting the engine separately sounds
      like a better approach.</li>
  </ol>
  
  <p>I was doing this job in my own garage at home, so I'll be describing the
  procedure #3. For subframe and gearbox removal refer to
  <a href="#/content/saab/20060121-saab-ng900-manual-transmission-removal">this guide</a>.</p>
  
  <h2>Tools:</h2>
  <ul>
    <li>22 mm wrench: oil cooler lines;</li>
    <li>19 mm socket: flywheel;</li>
    <li>19 mm wrench: brake booster hose;</li>
    <li>16 mm socket: A/C compressor;</li>
    <li>15 mm socket: passenger side engine mount;</li>
    <li>13 mm socket: oil drain plug;</li>
    <li>13 mm wrench: steering pump bolts, radiator drain plug;</li>
    <li>12 mm socket: pressure plate;</li>
    <li>10 mm socket: cruise control unit;</li>
    <li>8 mm socket: MAP sensor;</li>
    <li>7 mm socket: hose clamps;</li>
    <li>Torx T25 screwdriver: BPC;</li>
    <li>long 1/2" extension: belt tensioner release;</li>
    <li>engine support beam;</li>
    <li>shop crane;</li>
    <li>car jacks and axle stands;</li>
    <li>8 mm (5/16") fuel line disconnect tool;</li>
    <li>needle nose pliers (curved nose preferred).</li>
  </ul>
  </description>

  <picture name="20060515a.Engine_support.jpg" title="Engine support" date="15.05.2006">
    The car is on jack stands. The subframe and gearbox are already
    <a href="#/content/saab/20060121-saab-ng900-manual-transmission-removal">removed</a>,
    and the engine is hanging on the support beam.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060509a.MAP.jpg" title="MAP" date="09.05.2006">
    Unplug the connector and the vacuum hose from the manifold absolute
    pressure sensor. Alternatively, you can unbolt the sensor. I just removed
    it with the strut bar to free up some room.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060512a.Airbox.jpg" title="Airbox" date="12.05.2006">
    Remove the airbox and the rubber part of the turbo inlet hose.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060512b.Belt.jpg" title="Belt" date="12.05.2006">
    Insert a long 1/2" extention into the tensioner socket and
    release the belt. Lock it with a 2 mm Allen key or a nail. Remove the belt.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060512c.Steering_pump.jpg" title="Steering pump" date="12.05.2006">
    Undo three bolts holding the steering pump to the engine (13 mm wrench).
    Bend the hoses and move the pump out of the way.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060512d.BPC.jpg" title="BPC" date="12.05.2006">
    Unscrew the boost pressure control valve (Torx T25) and detach its cable
    from the fender. Put the valve and the cable on the engine.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060519b.Cruise_control_unit.jpg" title="Cruise control unit" date="19.05.2006">
    Unplug the cruise control unit connector. Detach the control unit (two
    plastic 10 mm nuts), lift it and move it aside.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060518a.Fuel_tank_vent_line.jpg" title="Fuel tank vent line" date="18.05.2006">
    Release the clamp and detach the fuel tank vent hose from the back of the
    throttle body.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060518b.Fuel_lines.jpg" title="Fuel lines" date="18.05.2006">
    The rubber fuel lines are attached to the fuel rail via a special locking
    joint. The release mechanism is covered by a rubber plug.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060518c.Fuel_line_cap.jpg" title="Fuel line cap" date="18.05.2006">
    Use curved needle nose pliers to pull the rubber plug out of the joint
    and move it up the pipe so it doesn't get in the way.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060518d.Disconnect_tool.jpg" title="Disconnect tool" date="18.05.2006">
    Get a 8 mm (5/16") fuel disconnect tool (it looks like a hollow plastic
    cone with a rim) and put it on the line. Push it down the joint until you
    hear a click.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060518e.Disconnected.jpg" title="Disconnected" date="18.05.2006">
    Wiggle the hose while pushing the disconnect tool in, and the joint will
    come apart. There might be some fuel left in the lines so have a catch
    can ready. Repeat with the second line, plug the hoses.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060519a.Throttle_cables.jpg" title="Throttle cables" date="19.05.2006">
    Detach the accelerator cable from the throttle body. Detach the cruise
    control cable.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060520a.Brake_booster_hose.jpg" title="Brake booster hose" date="20.05.2006">
    Unbolt the brake booster hose from the intake manifold.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060519c.Clutch.jpg" title="Clutch" date="19.05.2006">
    If you need the access to the flywheel or the main seal, remove the pressure
    plate now (12 mm socket). Most engine stands bolt to the gearbox mouting
    holes, and there will be little room to reach the clutch.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060519d.Flywheel.jpg" title="Flywheel" date="19.05.2006">
    The flywheel is held by eight big 19 mm bolts. In order to get them off, you
    need to attach a flywheel stop or otherwise ensure that the crankshaft
    won't move.
    
    <image width="800" height="599" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060519e.Coolant.jpg" title="Coolant" date="19.05.2006">
    Unscrew the radiator drain plug (13 mm wrench) and drain the coolant.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060519f.Coolant_hoses.jpg" title="Coolant hoses" date="19.05.2006">
    Detach coolant hoses from the driver's side of the engine (flat screwdriver
    or 7 mm socket). More coolant will come out of the heater core hoses,
    so have a pan ready.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060519g.Lower_hose.jpg" title="Lower hose" date="19.05.2006">
    Remove the lower radiator hose from the passenger side of the engine. If
    you unhook the lower part of the hose, be ready for more coolant spills.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060519l.Turbo.jpg" title="Turbo" date="19.05.2006">
    Remove the intercooler hose from the compressor outlet on the turbo.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060519h.Oil.jpg" title="Oil" date="19.05.2006">
    Drain engine oil (13 mm socket). Don't pour it down the drain, bring it
    to the nearby recycling facility (around here, Canadian Tire collects
    used oil free of charge).
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060519i.Oil_cooler_lines.jpg" title="Oil cooler lines" date="19.05.2006">
    Unbolt the oil cooler lines from the oil filter housing (22 mm wrench).
    Some oil will drain from those. Undo the lower A/C compressor bolt (16 mm).
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060519j.AC_compressor.jpg" title="A/C compressor" date="19.05.2006">
    Unbolt the two upper A/C compressor bolts. Unplug the compressor clutch
    control wire from the connector on the radiator.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060519k.AC_compressor.jpg" title="A/C compressor" date="19.05.2006">
    Lower the compressor (it's quite heavy) and hang it off the towing hook.
    Be careful not to bend the lines too much.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060520c.ECU_harness.jpg" title="ECU harness" date="20.05.2006">
    Inside the car, remove the glovebox and locate the wire cluster coming
    from the engine. One half goes to the ECU, while another feeds the data
    to the dashboard. Unplug both.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060520e.ECU_harness.jpg" title="ECU harness" date="20.05.2006">
    Pull the rubber gromet in the firewall and carefully retrieve the ECU
    harness through the opening. Put it on the engine.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060520f.EVAP_valve.jpg" title="EVAP valve" date="20.05.2006">
    Unplug the connector from the EVAP valve.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060520d.Positive_cable.jpg" title="Positive cable" date="20.05.2006">
    Detach the positive battery cable from the fuse box (10 mm socket).
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060520b.Axle.jpg" title="Axle" date="20.05.2006">
    Remove the passenger side axle by tapping it gently from behind, until
    it comes off the shaft.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060520g.Crane.jpg" title="Crane" date="20.05.2006">
    Bring the crane and lift the engine slightly so it takes the weight
    off the support beam and the remaining engine mount.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060520h.Engine_mount.jpg" title="Engine mount" date="20.05.2006">
    Unbolt the passenger side engine mount (15 mm socket). Be careful as the engine
    might shift suddenly when you remove the last bolt.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060520i.Beam_removed.jpg" title="Beam removed" date="20.05.2006">
    With the crane holding the engine, you don't need the support beam anymore.
    Remove the beam (in my case the lifting hook got stuck in the chain, so
    we just left it there).
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060520j.Engine_out.jpg" title="Engine out" date="20.05.2006">
    Lift the engine out of the car. Watch closely while lifting it, to
    ensure you won't break anything.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060520k.Plate_attached.jpg" title="Plate attached" date="20.05.2006">
    Attach the lifting plate from the engine stand (if you're planning to put
    the engine on the stand). Some of the bolt holes required unusually long
    bolts, the ones that came with my stand were too short.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060520l.Engine_stand.jpg" title="Engine stand" date="20.05.2006">
    Lower the engine and secure it on the stand. I had a friend helping out
    with the engine removal. It's always a good idea to have a second
    pair of hands while doing serious work like this.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060520m.On_the_stand.jpg" title="On the stand" date="20.05.2006">
    Engine out. Job done.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
</picture-set>
