<?xml version="1.0"?>
<picture-set title="Saab NG900/9-3: Intercooler Upgrade">

  <description>
  <p>Crossflow intercooler upgrade on the 1996 Saab 900 (applies to all 1994-1998 900 and 1999-2002 9-3).
  Parts from long gone MP Performance, notorious for bargain prices and questionable quality.</p>

  <h2>Tools:</h2>
  <ul>
    <li>16 mm socket: bumper bolts;</li>
    <li>10 mm socket: old intercooler bolts;</li>
    <li>8 mm socket: headlight wiper nuts and lower shield screws;</li>
    <li>7 mm socket: hose clamp screws;</li>
    <li>long socket extensions;</li>
    <li>ratchet handle;</li>
    <li>flat screwdriver;</li>
    <li>Torx T25 screwdriver;</li>
    <li>hacksaw and files;</li>
    <li>sharp knife;</li>
    <li>measuring tools;</li>
    <li>car jacks and stands or ramps.</li>
  </ul>
  </description>

  <picture name="2005052328.Grille.jpg" title="Grille" date="23.05.2005">
    Raise the front of the car and open the hood. Remove the grille by
    detaching two tabs on top.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="2005052329.Blinker.jpg" title="Blinker" date="23.05.2005">
    Undo the Torx T25 screw on the turn signal assembly, remove the housing and
    unplug the wires.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="2005052331.Headlight.jpg" title="Headlight" date="23.05.2005">
    Remove the headlights (three Torx T25 screws). Unplug the wires, use a flat
    screwdriver to release the locking tab on the harness.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="2005052332.Wiper.jpg" title="Wiper" date="23.05.2005">
    Lift the covers over the nuts on the headlight wiper arms and
    remove the arms (8 mm socket). Detach the washer fluid hose from the bumper (there is
    a couple of metal tabs holding it).
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="2005052340.Lower_shields.jpg" title="Lower shields" date="23.05.2005">
    Remove the plastic shields from below. Each side is held by half a dozen
    screws with a 8 mm hex head.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="2005052334.Foglight.jpg" title="Foglight" date="23.05.2005">
    Unplug the wires from the foglights.        
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="2005052339.Sensor.jpg" title="Sensor" date="23.05.2005">
    Detach the temperature sensor under the bumper. That horrible rusty thing
    is the license plate holder.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="2005052342.Screw.jpg" title="Screw" date="23.05.2005">
    Remove the Torx T25 screw under the fender (one on each side).
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="2005052345.Bumper_bolts.jpg" title="Bumper bolts" date="23.05.2005">
    Undo two long bumper bolts located next to the headlight wipers (16 mm
    socket).
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="2005052347.Bumper.jpg" title="Bumper" date="23.05.2005">
    Pull the bumper forward and remove it from the car. Mind the sides of the
    bumper cover while pulling: they are latched to the fenders on each side.
    You need to pry it outwards slightly.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="2005052349.Intercooler.jpg" title="Intercooler" date="23.05.2005">
    The intercooler is held by two long (and likely rusty) bolts. Use a
    10 mm socket to remove those. If you have an old style non-crossflow intercooler,
    then both hoses would be attached on the driver's side,
    the clamps can be released through the headlight opening with either
    a 7 mm socket or a flat screwdriver (and a lot of rust solvent).
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="2005052354.Old_intercooler.jpg" title="Old intercooler" date="23.05.2005">
    Remove the intercooler from the car. Detach the hoses from the delivery
    pipe and the turbo.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="2005052355.Old_vs_new.jpg" title="Old vs new" date="23.05.2005">
    The old intercooler was a two-pass design, the new one is a cross-flow.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="2005052356.Old_vs_new.jpg" title="Old vs new" date="23.05.2005">
    The upgraded intercooler core is made by Spearco and has a 3"x7" cross
    section with a flow area of 5.30 square inches. This is 60% more than a
    cross-flow Viggen intercooler has, and 4 times more than my base unit.
    There are also 5 times more fins for a much greater cooling capacity.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="2005052359.Old_vs_new.jpg" title="Old vs new" date="23.05.2005">
    The end tanks are made by MP. You can see an extra weld spot: this was
    a discounted defective unit. I had to take it to an alloy welder for
    repair first. We found four pinholes in the welds. Quality units
    should not have these problems, but it never hurts to do a pressure test.
    Also check for metal shavings in the end tanks: I had a lot of those.
    You don't want any in your intake manifold.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="2005052358.Old_vs_new.jpg" title="Old vs new" date="23.05.2005">
    Better intercoolers will have additional grooves machined on
    the inlet pipes to help secure the hoses better. Mine didn't have that,
    and the pipes were unequal length, but then again, I knew what I was
    getting, and it's hard to complain considering the discount they offered.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="2005052366.Lower_radiator_hose.jpg" title="Lower radiator hose" date="23.05.2005">
    Saab 900 models have an older lower radiator hose that gets in the way of
    the intercooler inlet hose. It has to be replaced by a new 9-3 design (Saab
    part #4963872).
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="2005052362.Draining_coolant.jpg" title="Draining coolant" date="23.05.2005">
    With the intercooler removed, you now have the access to the radiator
    drain plug. Use a PVC tube or fold piece of aluminium foil and
    drain the coolant into a clean bucket so you can reuse it later (assuming
    your coolant does not require replacement yet).
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="2005052367.900_vs_9-3.jpg" title="900 vs 9-3" date="23.05.2005">
    Here's the old hose next to the new style. MP used to
    source hoses from a junk yard, and unfortunately this one had a crack on the back.
    I've noticed it too late and had to reinstall the old hose since it was
    a holiday and the dealership was closed.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="2005052363.Coolant_tank.jpg" title="Coolant tank" date="23.05.2005">
    To not make my coolant drain a total waste of time, I cleaned the coolant
    expansion tank (it looks rather dirty on this picture). A quarter cup of
    rice, some soap water and 10 minutes of vigorous shaking made it shine like
    new! If you do that, wash it well: you don't want any rice in your coolant
    pipes ;).
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="2005052370.Old_inlet_pipe.jpg" title="Old inlet pipe" date="23.05.2005">
    Normally, the intercooler kit includes Viggen inlet hoses which are almost
    a direct fit. Some custom made piping would've been even better.
    Unfortunately I had neither - my cheap intercooler didn't come with any,
    and the stores were closed. So I decided to make the most of the stuff
    I had.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="2005052372.Test_fit.jpg" title="Test fit" date="23.05.2005">
    I had one extra elbow that helped to form the inlet section.
    The test fit looks promising.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="2005052375.Inlet_hose.jpg" title="Inlet hose" date="23.05.2005">
    The intercooler is put in place and the turbo hose is attached. This
    actually looks better than the Viggen hose, as the Viggen elbow forms
    a nasty bend on the T25 turbo because the T25 is angled differently.
    And there's enough clearance even with the original radiator hose.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="2005052377.Radiator_fan.jpg" title="Radiator fan" date="23.05.2005">
    The new hose did not fit with the radiator fan frame, so I had to hack
    a nasty chunk of the frame off. This should not be necessary if you have
    OEM crossflow hoses and a TD04.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="2005052379.Fan_installed.jpg" title="Fan installed" date="23.05.2005">
    The fan is attached with two screws at the top. Everything seems to
    fit well. Make sure all clamps are very tight, especially if you used soap
    or silicone to put them on. You don't want any of those coming
    off on the road.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="2005052380.Hose.jpg" title="Hose" date="23.05.2005">
    This is the hose from the intercooler to the delivery pipe. It had to
    be extended an inch and a half. The clamps are easier to reach from under
    the car.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20051105a.New_hoses.jpg" title="New hoses" date="05.11.2005">
    This is an updated hose arrangement used with a Mitsubishi TD04 turbo
    (aka "Viggen turbo").
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20051105b.Turbo_pipes.jpg" title="Turbo pipes" date="05.11.2005">
    The compressor outlet on TD04 is angled differently, which allows
    for a shorter hose.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="2005052381.Zip_ties.jpg" title="Zip ties" date="23.05.2005">
    The intercooler is not bolted on like the old unit, but it's held by the
    hoses quite firmly and is not going anywhere. I added giant zip ties on
    each side, as well as a couple of rubber strips to prevent it from rubbing
    against the radiator.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20051105c.No_bumper.jpg" title="No bumper" date="05.11.2005">
    A view of the intercooler with the bumper removed.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20051105d.Bumper_on.jpg" title="Bumper on" date="05.11.2005">
    The bumper is a rather close fit. Leave the intercooler sticking out
    too far, and it will rub against the bumper rail.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="2005052383.Coolant.jpg" title="Coolant" date="23.05.2005">
    Time to fill the coolant.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="2005052386.Installed.jpg" title="Installed" date="23.05.2005">
    Install the lower shields, headlights and grille. The only
    sore spot left is my rusty license plate holder, which also blocks the
    intercooler.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="2005052386.License_plate.jpg" title="License plate" date="23.05.2005">
    A final touch, the license plate is moved higher,
    the intercooler can be seen through the bumper opening.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
</picture-set>
