<?xml version="1.0"?>
<picture-set title="Saab NG900/9-3: Stanchion Arm Bushings">

  <description>
  <p>Stanchion arm bushing replacement on a 1996 Saab 900SE turbo (applies to all 1994-1998 900 and 1999-2002 9-3).</p>

  <p>My old worn out bushings are being replaced with upgraded polyurethane bushings made by Powerflex.</p>

  <p>NOTE: it is not entirely necessary to pull the driveshaft or disconnect
  the control arms. You can even deal with the bushings
  right on the car, but the room would be rather tight.</p>

  <b>Tools and supplies:</b>
  <ul>
    <li>32 mm (1.25") socket: hub centre nut;</li>
    <li>24 mm wrench and socket: stanchion arm to control arm bolts (for Taliaferro bushings);</li>
    <li>17 mm socket: wheel bolts;</li>
    <li>16 mm socket: stanchion arm to subframe bolts;</li>
    <li>15 mm socket: control arm to subframe bolts;</li>
    <li>13 mm socket: lower sway bar link nut;</li>
    <li>11 mm open wrench: upper part of sway bar link;</li>
    <li>10 mm Allen key: caliper bolts;</li>
    <li>5 mm Allen key: rotor index screw;</li>
    <li>Torx T55 socket: stanchion arm to control arm bolts (for stock bushings);</li>
    <li>gear puller and a hacksaw (for old bushing removal);</li>
    <li>torque wrench;</li>
    <li>car jack and axle stands;</li>
    <li>breaker bar.</li>
  </ul>
  </description>

  <picture name="20051013m.Wheel_removed.jpg" title="Wheel removed" date="13.10.2005">
    With the car still on the ground, remove the centre cap from the wheel and
    loosen the hub nut using a 32 mm socket (a 1.25" will do) and a
    breaker bar. Loosen the wheel bolts while you're at it too (17 mm socket).
    Raise the car and remove the wheel. 
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20051013n.Subframe_bolt.jpg" title="Subframe bolt" date="13.10.2005">
    Unbolt the rearmost subframe bolt holding the stanchion arms (16 mm socket).
    These bolts tend to wear out on the bottom end, so consider a pair of new
    ones. Pull the arm out of the subframe.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20051013o.Control_arm.jpg" title="Control arm" date="13.10.2005">
    Remove the caliper and the brake rotor if they are in the way.
    Disconnect the control arm from the subframe (15 mm socket). Unbolt the
    sway bar link from the control arm.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20051013p.Separated.jpg" title="Separated" date="13.10.2005">
    Unbolt the stanchion arm from the control arm and remove it from the car.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20051013q.Worn_bushings.jpg" title="Worn bushings" date="13.10.2005">
    With 276K km on the clock, these bushings look completely destroyed.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20051013s.Apart.jpg" title="Apart" date="13.10.2005">
    If you ever wondered what's inside, here's your answer. And there also was
    hydraulic oil... a long time ago.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20051013t.Sleeve.jpg" title="Sleeve" date="13.10.2005">
    The remaining steel sleeve can be removed with a help of a hacksaw and
    a cold chisel.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20051013u.Powerflex.jpg" title="Powerflex" date="13.10.2005">
    The Powerflex bushings are a solid two-piece design, and they are worth
    your attention for the ease of installation alone.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20051013v.Spring_sleeves.jpg" title="Spring sleeves" date="13.10.2005">
    Lubricate the bushings with supplied grease and slide them into the arms.
    You will also need a pair of new springs sleeves for EACH arm. If your
    original bushings were dead as mine, chances are the spring sleeves are
    a heap of rust by now.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20051030.Bolts.jpg" title="Bolts" date="30.10.2005">
    This is what happens when you run your car with worn stanchion arm
    bushings and rusted spring sleeves. The bolt looks like someone
    chewed on it. A new bolt is pictured below.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20051013w.Installed.jpg" title="Installed" date="13.10.2005">
    You might need to slightly widen the opening in the subframe to fit
    the new bushings in, otherwise the installation is straightforward.
    Refer to <a href="#/content/saab/20050210-saab-ng900-front-suspension">this guide</a> for tightening torque values.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
</picture-set>
