<?xml version="1.0"?>
<picture-set title="Saab 9-5: Front Suspension">

  <description>
  <p>Front suspension replacement on a 1999 Saab 9-5. The old and tired original
  dampers and springs are being upgraded with Bilstein Sport dampers and
  Eibach Pro Kit lowering springs. Strut mounts and bearings are also
  getting replaced.</p>

  <h2>Tools:</h2>
  <ul>
    <li>22 mm socket: Bilstein retainer nut (optional);</li>
    <li>21 mm socket: original retainer nut;</li>
    <li>18 mm socket: knuckle housing bolts, anti-roll bar link nut;</li>
    <li>18 mm wrench: new style anti-roll bar link nut;</li>
    <li>17 mm socket: wheel bolts;</li>
    <li>17 mm wrench: old style anti-roll bar link pin;</li>
    <li>10 mm socket: strut mount bolts;</li>
    <li>7 mm socket: new style anti-roll bar link pin;</li>
    <li>7 mm Allen socket: damper rod;</li>
    <li>torque wrench;</li>
    <li>vice-grips;</li>
    <li>car jack and axle stands;</li>
    <li>spring compressor.</li>
  </ul>
  </description>

  <picture name="20070929a.Jack_stands.jpg" title="Jack stands" date="29.09.2007">
    Secure the car on jack stands, take the front wheel off. Both wheels need
    to be in the air, otherwise it becomes difficult to align the anti-roll
    bar link with its mounting hole on the strut. Spray the bolts with rust
    solvent and wire brush the threads on the anti-roll bar link and knuckle
    housing bolts.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070929b.Link.jpg" title="Link" date="29.09.2007">
    Unscrew the anti-roll bar link from the strut. The old version had a grip
    behind the strut, so you could use a 17 mm spanner on it. The new version
    has a smaller hex pin protruding in the front, which requires you to use
    a spanner on the nut itself, while holding the pin with a small socket.
    <image width="800" height="598" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070929c.Bracket.jpg" title="Bracket" date="29.09.2007">
    Detach the brake line and the ABS sensor wire from the bracket on the
    side of the strut.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070929d.Knuckle.jpg" title="Knuckle" date="29.09.2007">
    Undo two bolts holding the strut to the knuckle housing. Remove the nuts
    and pull the bolts out.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070929e.Disconnected.jpg" title="Disconnected" date="29.09.2007">
    Detach the knuckle housing from the strut. It might be a good idea to
    support the control arm from below so it doesn't strain the brake line with
    its weight.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070929f.Strut_tower.jpg" title="Strut tower" date="29.09.2007">
    Undo three bolts holding the strut mount to the top of the tower.
    While loosening the last bolt, catch the strut before it falls down and damages
    the CV joint boot.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070929g.Strut.jpg" title="Strut" date="29.09.2007">
    Lower the strut to the ground.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070929h.Spring_compressor.jpg" title="Spring compressor" date="29.09.2007">
    Attach a spring compressor to relieve the load on the spring seat.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070929i.Retainer_nut.jpg" title="Retainer nut" date="29.09.2007">
    Grab the damper rod with vice-grips and undo the retainer nut on top
    of the strut. You can use a regular ratchet, but the impact wrench makes
    the job more satisfying and saves a lot of time.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070929j.Apart.jpg" title="Apart" date="29.09.2007">
    The strut apart (counter-clockwise): damper, spring, bump stop, 
    dust cover with upper spring seat, thrust bearing, strut mount, retainer nut.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070929k.New_vs_old.jpg" title="New vs old" date="29.09.2007">
    The Bilstein monotube damper features it's famous massive rod, and the
    "Sport" version is a bit shorter, being designed to match the ride height
    with lowering springs. The Eibach spring has the same number of coils as
    OEM, but is wound tighter, and has slightly thicker coils. It's obviously
    shorter too, the posted lowering amount is 35 mm.
    <image width="800" height="598" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070929l.Strut_mounts.jpg" title="Strut mounts" date="29.09.2007">
    An aftermarket strut mount kit comes with everything you need to refresh
    the mounts, including a new bearing and a set of bolts. It's made in India,
    but looks reasonably solid. Unfortunately I could not use the 22 mm nut
    supplied with Bilstein dampers, because my 22 mm socket did not fit into the
    narrow opening in the strut mount, so I had to reuse the old 21 mm nut.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070929m.Dust_shield.jpg" title="Dust shield" date="29.09.2007">
    The old strut mount came with a little rubber skirt to protect the bearing from
    dirt. It can be removed and transferred to the new mount.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070929n.Thrust_bearings.jpg" title="Thrust bearings" date="29.09.2007">
    The thrust bearing is tight, shiny and certainly more presentable than the
    tired old one, although they came looking a little dry, so I added some
    bearing grease just in case.
    <image width="797" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070929o.Ready_for_assembly.jpg" title="Ready for assembly" date="29.09.2007">
    Bilstein dampers come with integrated bump stops, so you don't need to
    reuse your old one. The spring needs to be compressed, and the strut mount
    is already assembled with the skirt and the bearing on.
    <image width="800" height="599" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070929p.Fit_together.jpg" title="Fit together" date="29.09.2007">
    Slide the spring over the damper rod, making sure that it's not upside down,
    and that the end of the last coil matches the little stop on the lower
    spring support. Install the upper seat, the mount, and screw the nut on.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070929q.Tightening.jpg" title="Tightening" date="29.09.2007">
    This is how you are supposed to tighten the retainer nut - hold the damper
    rod with a thin Allen wrench and tighten the nut. Unfortunately, the shallow
    Allen socket is easy to strip, making the required 76 ft-lbs hard to achieve.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070929r.Tightening.jpg" title="Tightening" date="29.09.2007">
    Alternatively, you can grab the damper rod with vice-grips and use a good
    sized torque wrench on the nut. Just wrap the rod with something so it
    won't get scratched (I use a nylon belt). An impact wrench also works well on the top nut.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070929s.Strut_tower.jpg" title="Strut tower" date="29.09.2007">
    Lift the strut to the underside of the strut tower. Align the smallest hole
    first, put the cover on and screw the bolt in. Fit the remaining two bolts
    and tighten all three to 13 ft-lbs.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070929t.Knuckle_housing.jpg" title="Knuckle housing" date="29.09.2007">
    Lift the knuckle housing to match the holes on the damper. You will have
    to raise it higher than before, because the strut is shorter now.
    <image width="800" height="599" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070929u.Big_bolts.jpg" title="Big bolts" date="29.09.2007">
    Insert the two bolts, don't forget to fit the brake line bracket.
    Mind the camber setting if you use adjuster bolts. Tighten the nuts to 75
    ft-lbs +45 degrees.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070929v.Bracket.jpg" title="Bracket" date="29.09.2007">
    Attach the ABS sensor cable and the brake line to the bracket.
    <image width="800" height="598" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070929w.Link.jpg" title="Link" date="29.09.2007">
    Fit the anti-roll bar link and tighten the nut to 62 ft-lbs.
    <image width="799" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070929x.Lowered.jpg" title="Lowered" date="29.09.2007">
    Install the wheels, tighten the lug bolts to 81 ft-lbs and lower the
    car to the ground.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
</picture-set>
