<?xml version="1.0"?>
<picture-set title="Saab 9-5: Oil Pressure Gauge">

  <description>
  Oil pressure gauge installation on a Saab 9-5,
  contributed by <a href="mailto:pdurgin@comcast.net">Philip Durgin</a>.
  </description>

  <picture name="20090208a.Glow_Shift_adapter.jpg" title="Glow Shift adapter" date="08.02.2009">
    <p>The 4 cylinder 9-5 is prone to low oil pressure problems, so I wanted to put 
    in a gauge to monitor the pressure.  Hopefully then I could catch any 
    potential problems before the OEM low pressure light would come on (at about 
    6 psi).  Putting the gauge in was easy and only cost about $100, including 
    shipping.</p>

    <p>I purchased a 3/4 unf-16 oil filter 
    <a href="http://www.glowshiftdirect.com/oilfilter-sender-adapter-34unf-16.aspx">sandwich adapter</a>,
    black 7-color oil pressure gauge, and the universal single pillar pod all 
    from <a href="http://www.glowshift.com">GlowShift</a>.  This is easier than
    tapping into the factory oil pressure sending unit and allows you to keep 
    the factory oil pressure warning light without having to add some kind of 
    a junction box.</p>
    <image width="497" height="400" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20090208b.Filter_sandwich.jpg" title="Filter sandwich" date="08.02.2009">
    <p>GlowShift recommends the adapter nut be tightened to a little more than 
    hand tight.  That didn't feel tight enough to me, so I tightened it a 
    little more than that.  But don't tighten it too much or it will distort 
    the rubber washer that comes with it and leak.  The adapter has four ports.
    Because I was only adding a pressure gauge, I plugged three (the adapter
    comes with plugs) and screwed the pressure sender (the sender comes with 
    the gauge) into the fourth.  Use Teflon tape around the threads of the 
    plugs and sender to prevent leaks.</p>

    <p>I oriented the adapter so the sending unit was protected by the plastic 
    stone guard.  That makes it a little difficult to connect the wires and 
    see the terminal markings, so connect the wires up before installing the 
    adapter.  Be sure to mark which wire is the ground and which is the sender
    wire.  I took the ground wire up to a ground terminal in front of the 
    battery; the sender wire goes into the cabin as shown in the next picture.</p>
    <image width="640" height="479" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20090208c.Firewall.jpg" title="Firewall" date="08.02.2009">
    My plan was to take the sender wire through the firewall, but I couldn't
    find anyplace that looked easy.  But I did notice that the hood release 
    cable comes through at about the right spot.  After pushing the rubber 
    grommet back a bit with a screwdriver, it was easy to fish a stiff wire 
    through the hole, and it came out at just the right spot under the dash.  
    I taped the sender wire to the stiff wire, but it was too tight a fit, so 
    I had to drill the hole a little bigger to get everything through.  
    The main problem was the sender wire was now pushed tight up against the 
    sharp edge of the sheet metal.  I used electrical tape to make a pad and 
    stuffed it between the sheet metal and the sender wire.  If that doesn't 
    hold up, I'll have to come up with a more permanent solution. 
    <em>(DP: consider <a href="#/content/saab/20040417-saab-9-5-boost-gauge-install">the grommet under the fuse box</a>).</em>
    <image width="640" height="479" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20090208d.Gauge_pod.jpg" title="Gauge pod" date="08.02.2009">
    <p>To install the gauge, first remove the trim from the A pillar.  I used a 
    door trim removal tool I got from the local auto parts place for about $5.
    The trim comes off easily. I thought the gauge looked best when positioned
    low on the A pillar.  Both the gauge and the pod are light, so I decided to
    attach everything with Velcro.  I Gorilla-glued the Velcro on the pod and 
    drilled a small hole through the trim to feed the wires through.  I used 
    double-sided sticky tape to hold the gauge in position.  I kept the tape a 
    little loose so I could fine-tune the gauge's position after it was 
    installed.</p>
    <p>There's plenty of space at the bottom of the A pillar to feed the gauge 
    wires through. The yellow wire of the gauge is attached to a circuit with 
    constant current and the red wire is attached to a switched circuit that 
    is only hot when the car is running.  Constant current is needed because 
    the gauge needs to remember which of the seven colors you prefer.</p>
    <image width="541" height="480" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20090208e.Fuse.jpg" title="Fuse" date="08.02.2009">
    Rather than tap directly into a wire, I used fuse blades.  They go around 
    one prong of the fuse.  I don't know if it matters, but I put the blade 
    around the upper prong of the fuse. Before you start pulling any fuses, 
    disconnect the cable from the negative battery post.
    <image width="640" height="479" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20090208f.Fuse_panel.jpg" title="Fuse panel" date="08.02.2009">
    For the yellow (constant) wire, I used the fuse for the electric-operated
    driver's seat (fuse #25).  For the red (switched) wire, I used the fuse 
    for the cigarette lighter (fuse #34).  The fuses are clearly marked on the
    plastic fuse box cover by the driver's side door.  Because of the extra
    thickness of the blade, you have to apply some extra force to push the 
    fuses in. Bend the blades just enough to get the fuse box cover back on.
    <image width="640" height="479" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20090208g.Ground.jpg" title="Ground" date="08.02.2009">
    The green wire of the gauge gets hooked up to the sender wire you brought
    through the cable hole.  The gauge's black wire needs to go to a good 
    ground.  There's a grounding terminal behind the dash about 8 inches 
    away from where the sending wire comes through into the cabin.
    <image width="640" height="479" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20090208h.Installed.jpg" title="Installed" date="08.02.2009">
    When the engine is fully warmed up, my gauge shows about 40 psi at 2000 rpm
    and about 20 psi at idle.  There's a little button to press to change the 
    gauge color.  I like the green/yellow color during the day, red at night.
    <image width="640" height="479" />
  </picture>
</picture-set>
