<?xml version="1.0"?>
<picture-set title="Saab 9-5: Theft Alarm Module">

  <description>
  <p>Theft alarm repair on a Saab 9-5.</p>

  <p>The theft alarm module on the 9-5 is equipped with its own power source,
  so it can operate even when the main battery is disconnected. It uses two
  Sanyo CR17335 3V Lithium batteries, which get recharged while the car
  is running. However, the batteries lose their capacity with age, and
  the current eventually drops below a certain value, which triggers a
  warning in the self-diagnostic system.</p>

  <p>If the batteries need replacement, you will start getting the following
  message on the SID every once in a while:
  <span style="background:#000;color:#FA0;font-family:Courier;font-weight:bold">
   "SERVICE THEFT ALARM"
  </span></p>

  <p>Saab does not sell replacement batteries, you can only order a complete
  new module, which is a waste of money. Fortunately, you can find the
  batteries from an electronics supplier and replace them yourself, if you're
  handy with a soldering iron. The batteries need to be of the exactly
  the same type and model as the originals.</p>

  <p>Do NOT solder the batteries directly! Direct contact with a soldering
  iron might heat the battery up too much and cause it to explode. Instead,
  make sure the batteries you buy come with external leads attached.</p>

  <h2>Tools:</h2>
  <ul>
    <li>17 mm socket: wheel bolts;</li>
    <li>10 mm socket: alarm module nuts, bumper lip screw;</li>
    <li>8 mm socket: wheel lining screws;</li>
    <li>Torx T25 socket: wheel lining screws;</li>
    <li>torque wrench;</li>
    <li>car jack and axle stands;</li>
    <li>soldering iron;</li>
    <li>Phillips screwdriver.</li>
  </ul>
  </description>

  <picture name="20071020a.Wheel_off.jpg" title="Wheel off" date="20.10.2007">
    Raise the left front corner of the car and secure it on jack stands.
    Take the wheel off.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20071020b.Lining.jpg" title="Lining" date="20.10.2007">
    Undo the screws on the wheel well lining. There are two Torx screws along
    the bumper edge, two 8 mm on the inside, and one 10 mm under the lower lip.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20071020c.Nuts.jpg" title="Nuts" date="20.10.2007">
    Bend the lining away and unbolt the alarm module located right next to
    the washer fluid tank. There's a 10 mm nut at the top and a screw at the
    bottom.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20071020d.Connector.jpg" title="Connector" date="20.10.2007">
    Unplug the connector from the module. Make sure the car is unlocked at this
    point, otherwise the alarm will go off if theft protection was active.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20071020e.Module.jpg" title="Module" date="20.10.2007">
    The two halves of the module are held together by six Phillips screws.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20071020f.Open.jpg" title="Open" date="20.10.2007">
    The cover is glued on with rubbery sealant, so you might need a knife
    or a flat screwdriver to crack it open.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20071020g.Board.jpg" title="Board" date="20.10.2007">
    Detach the board carefully - the batteries are glued to the bottom cover,
    so you will need to pry them off. Pull the red jumper to cut the power
    from the circuit.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20071020h.Desoldering.jpg" title="Desoldering" date="20.10.2007">
    Desolder the old batteries. Be careful not to apply too much heat. Do not
    solder the batteries directly. Instead, detach their leads from the board.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20071020i.Batteries.jpg" title="Batteries" date="20.10.2007">
    The old pair of batteries (orange) next to a new set (beige). It looks
    like the batteries are good for about 5 years, accordings to the markings.
    <image width="799" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20071020j.Soldering.jpg" title="Soldering" date="20.10.2007">
    Solder the new batteries on, follow the polarity marked on the board.
    Fit the jumper, assemble the module and re-install in reverse order.
    <image width="799" height="600" />
  </picture>
</picture-set>
