<?xml version="1.0"?>
<picture-set title="Saab 9-5: Complete 3 inch Exhaust">

  <description>
  <p>Complete exhaust system replacement on a 1999 Saab 9-5 (applies to all
  four cylinder 9-5 models). The original exhaust rusted through, and is now
  replaced with a three inch straight through
  system built by Jak Stoll. It is made of 3" aluminized steel piping and includes a downpipe,
  sport catalitic converter, two flex joints, resonator and a rear muffler.</p>
  <p>Jak's fabrication quality got better over the years. Welds and transitions
  were much smoother than on the
  <a href="#/content/saab/20050119-saab-ng900-downpipe-with-sportcat">NG900 downpipe</a>
  I bought from him a few years ago. Other than his choice of a resonator, I
  didn't really have anothing to complain about. The fit was nearly flawless
  too. He actually mentioned that he doesn't have a jig for 9-5 exhausts at his
  shop. Instead, he gets his mother in-law's Aero up on the lift and makes a
  tailored job every time. I suppose this kind of dedication had to pay off ;].</p>

  <h2>Tools:</h2>
  <ul>
    <li>22 mm (7/8") crowfoot socket: O2 sensors (or specialized O2 sensor socket);</li>
    <li>14 mm socket: reinforcement panel, exhaust clamps and joints (could differ depending on
      the supplier);</li>
    <li>13 mm socket or wrench: downpipe to turbo nuts;</li>
    <li>flat screwdriver: O2 sensor connectors;</li>
    <li>torque wrench;</li>
    <li>ramps and jack stands;</li>
    <li>anti-seize lubricant;</li>
    <li>exhaust sealant.</li>
  </ul>
  </description>

  <picture name="20080916.Just_arrived.jpg" title="Just arrived" date="16.09.2008">
    The system arrived in a huge box filled with packing peanuts. All flanges
    were carefully wrapped and taped up, so the peanuts wouldn't get inside.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20080917a.Unwrapped.jpg" title="Unwrapped" date="17.09.2008">
    The whole exhaust is over four meters (14 feet) long. It was split into
    four sections for easier shipping, and came with clamps and a chrome tip.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20080917b.Downpipe_and_cat.jpg" title="Downpipe and cat" date="17.09.2008">
    The downpipe looks smoother than 
    <a href="#/content/saab/20050119-saab-ng900-downpipe-with-sportcat">the one</a>
    I bought from Jak three years ago. It comes with a sport cat and two
    flex joints before and after cat for better strain resistance (most
    aftermarket systems have only one flex pipe).
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20080917c.Middle_section.jpg" title="Middle section" date="17.09.2008">
    The middle section is a simple straight pipe with an odd noname resonator
    welded in. As it turned out, it didn't work very well, producing an awful
    drone between 2-3K RPM. It resonated through the whole car, making the
    highway ride almost unbearable.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20080917d.Resonator.jpg" title="Resonator" date="17.09.2008">
    The resonator is just an empty can with baffles designed to reflect and
    eliminate certain sound frequences. In reality, it only made things worse
    and had to be replaced with a better one soon after (see below).
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20080917e.Curved_section.jpg" title="Curved section" date="17.09.2008">
    The curved section snakes past the fuel tank and under the rear axle.
    Older cars had an extra pair of hangers at the beginning of this section.
    Jak skipped it as he used a 2004 Aero for a test fit, but I added them
    during the install.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20080917f.Muffler.jpg" title="Muffler" date="17.09.2008">
    The rear muffler is Flo-Pro Max, in an 18" long stainless 4"x9" oval body
    with a pair of hangers attached.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20080917g.Straight_through.jpg" title="Straight through" date="17.09.2008">
    This picture shows the straight through perforated pipe inside the muffler.
    It's wrapped in steel mesh and sound absorbing material.
    <image width="800" height="599" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20080917h.Clamps_and_tip.jpg" title="Clamps and tip" date="17.09.2008">
    Also included were three Easy Seal clamps and a chrome tip with "Magnaflow"
    stamped on it.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20080917i.Jacks.jpg" title="Jacks" date="17.09.2008">
    For exhaust installation, the whole car should be up in the air. I used
    ramps at the front and jacks in the rear.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20080917j.O2_sensor_connector.jpg" title="O2 sensor connector" date="17.09.2008">
    The rear O2 sensor is often hard to undo on the car. Instead, unplug its
    connector and drop the wires down.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20080917k.Heat_shield.jpg" title="Heat shield" date="17.09.2008">
    Remove the heat shield over the turbo. Detach the return pipe from the
    bypass valve if it's in the way.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20080917l.Downpipe.jpg" title="Downpipe" date="17.09.2008">
    Use a crowfoot or a specialized socket to remove the front O2 sensor.
    Undo the two upper nuts on the downpipe.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20080917m.Lower_nut.jpg" title="Lower nut" date="17.09.2008">
    Mount your creeper, slide under the car and undo the lower nut holding
    the downpipe. This one needs a 13 mm spanner as there's not enough room
    for a ratchet.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20080917n.Reinforcement.jpg" title="Reinforcement" date="17.09.2008">
    Use a 14 mm socket to unbolt the reinforcement panel under the flex pipe.
    Slide the panel out.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20080917o.Muffler_hangers.jpg" title="Muffler hangers" date="17.09.2008">
    Remove two rubber supports at the rear muffler. You can see the right side
    hanger already disappeared some time ago.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20080917p.More_hangers.jpg" title="More hangers" date="17.09.2008">
    All the remaining hangers point forward, so if you give it a good tug
    towards the back, the whole thing will just drop on the ground.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20080917q.Down.jpg" title="Down" date="17.09.2008">
    Drag the exhaust from under of the car. Watch the top of the downpipe so
    it doesn't mess up any cables or hoses while being dragged.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20080917r.Old_exhaust.jpg" title="Old exhaust" date="17.09.2008">
    Such a sorry sight. Big chunks of rust coming off the mufflers, the middle
    flex pipe's been already replaced at least once, and the front flex is
    loosing its braiding too.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20080917s.O2_sensor.jpg" title="O2 sensor" date="17.09.2008">
    Once the exhaust is on the ground, it should be easy to undo the rear O2
    sensor. Again, use a crowfoot or a specialized socket on it.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20080917t.New_vs_old.jpg" title="New vs old" date="17.09.2008">
    The new system is shinier, cleaner and noticeably thicker than the original.
    The original piping is 60 mm (2 3/8"), while new is 76 mm (3").
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20080917u.Scrap_collector.jpg" title="Scrap collector" date="17.09.2008">
    To our surprise, a scrap metal collector showed up while we were working
    on the car. That solved the problem of disposing of the old exhaust.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20080917v.Front_section.jpg" title="Front section" date="17.09.2008">
    Start the assembly by connecting the two front sections. Make sure the
    hangers are aligned evenly.
    <image width="800" height="599" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20080917w.O2_sensor_and_clamp.jpg" title="O2 sensor and clamp" date="17.09.2008">
    Install the rear O2 sensor with some anti-seize on the threads and tighten
    to 40 ft-lbs. Apply a bead of exhaust sealant on the joint and put the clamp on.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20080917x.Downpipe_hangers.jpg" title="Downpipe hangers" date="17.09.2008">
    Fit the downpipe in the front rubber hangers.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20080917y.Resonator_hangers.jpg" title="Resonator hangers" date="17.09.2008">
    Hook up the hangers supporting the resonator.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20080917z0.Downpipe.jpg" title="Downpipe" date="17.09.2008">
    Slide the downpipe flange onto the turbo, make sure it doesn't rub
    against the oil pan and the gearbox.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20080917z1.Rear_section.jpg" title="Rear section" date="17.09.2008">
    Assemble the two rear sections together. Spread some exhaust sealant, but
    not tighten the clamp yet.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20080917z2.Muffler_hangers.jpg" title="Muffler hangers" date="17.09.2008">
    Fit the muffler and slide the hangers into the rubber supports.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20080917z3.Rear_joint.jpg" title="Rear joint" date="17.09.2008">
    Jak made all the hangers to point forward, so it was easy to fit the
    pipe in place.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20080917z4.Middle_joint.jpg" title="Middle joint" date="17.09.2008">
    Connect the last joint in the middle and move the pipe around to ensure
    it's perfectly centered along the entire exhaust duct.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20080917z5.Reinforcement.jpg" title="Reinforcement" date="17.09.2008">
    Secure all the clamps and attach the reinforcement plate at the front.
    Tighten to 50 ft-lbs.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20080917z6.Downpipe.jpg" title="Downpipe" date="17.09.2008">
    Tighten the downpipe nuts to 18 ft-lbs. Use new locking nuts if the old
    ones feel loose.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20080917z7.O2_sensor.jpg" title="O2 sensor" date="17.09.2008">
    Install the front O2 sensor, don't forget the anti-seize.
    Tighten to 40 ft-lbs. Plug in the rear sensor connector.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20080917z8.Heat_shield.jpg" title="Heat shield" date="17.09.2008">
    Restore the heat shield and the return line from the bypass valve.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20080917z9.Muffler_tip.jpg" title="Muffler tip" date="17.09.2008">
    Attach the muffler tip, make sure it's centered in the bumper cut-out.
    Start the car and enjoy the new exhaust.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20081017a.Small_vs_large.jpg" title="Small vs large" date="17.10.2008">
    Unfortunately, as I described above, the resonator was not up to the job,
    so I got this straight through Magnaflow muffler instead.
    At 30 inches long and 6 inches wide, it was significantly larger.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20081017c.Installed.jpg" title="Installed" date="17.10.2008">
    It had barely enough room to fit under
    the car, but the result was definitely worth it. The car became
    virtually as quiet as stock when cruising, with a nice angry note
    on the throttle.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
</picture-set>
