<?xml version="1.0"?>
<picture-set title="Saab 9-3/9-5: Throttle Body">

  <description>
  <p>Throttle body removal and replacement on a 4-cylinder Saab 9-5,
  applies to most 9-3 and 9-5 models with B205/B235 engines.</p>

  <h2>Tools and supplies:</h2>
  <ul>
    <li>10 mm socket: throttle body and cable cover bolts;</li>
    <li>13 mm or 1/2" wrench: negative battery clamp;</li>
    <li>flat screwdriver: delivery pipe boot clamps, limp home mechanism reset;</li>
    <li>pliers: coolant hose clamps;</li>
    <li>new rubber seal (#9176918) and vaseline;</li>
    <li>torque wrench.</li>
  </ul>
  </description>

  <picture name="20041006a.Engine.jpg" title="Engine" date="06.10.2004">
    The throttle body is located under the plastic engine cover -- it's
    where the delivery pipe leads to.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20041006b.Battery.jpg" title="Battery" date="06.10.2004">
    Disconnect the battery and unscrew the cap on the coolant expansion tank
    to ease the pressure. Put the cap back on.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20041006c.Boot.jpg" title="Boot" date="06.10.2004">
    Undo the clamps on the delivery pipe and take the rubber boot off. On
    newer cars with a plastic delivery pipe (and no rubber boot) you might have
    to first slacken the delivery pipe retaining bolt on the cylinder head.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20041006d.Cable_cover.jpg" title="Cable cover" date="06.10.2004">
    If you were to clean the throttle body, then you'd stop here, just clean it
    inside and put the pipe back. However, to replace the throttle body, you
    need to do more. Continue with removing the cover over the throttle cable
    (two 10 mm bolts).
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20041006e.Cable.jpg" title="Cable" date="06.10.2004">
    Disconnect the accelerator pedal cable from the throttle body's pedal arm.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20041006f.Wires.jpg" title="Wires" date="06.10.2004">
    Unplug the wiring connectors from the limp-home solenoid and the throttle
    body.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20041006g.Hoses.jpg" title="Hoses" date="06.10.2004">
    Detach four hoses entering the throttle body. The two bigger hoses may
    contain some coolant, so be careful if the engine is hot. WIS recommends
    clamping them first to prevent coolant spillage.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20041006h.Bolts.jpg" title="Bolts" date="06.10.2004">
    Undo three 10 mm bolts and lift the throttle body off the intake manifold.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20041006i.Last_hose.jpg" title="Last hose" date="06.10.2004">
    Undo the hose clamp on the back of the throttle body and detach the hose.
    Congratulations, you have just removed your throttle body ;).
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20041006j.Old_and_new.jpg" title="Old and new" date="06.10.2004">
    Two throttle bodies side by side. I'm installing a used unit (right), and it
    actually appears to be dirtier on the outside. Cleaner on the inside though.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20041006k.New_and_old.jpg" title="New and old" date="06.10.2004">
    Note how the end of the spring is caught in the triangular tab on the old
    unit (right). It's an indication that the limp-home solenoid has fired and
    locked the pedal arm to the throttle butterfly.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20041006l.Limp_home_reset.jpg" title="Limp home reset" date="06.10.2004">
    If you ever need to reset a previously activated limp-home mode, it can
    be done directly on the car. Move the end of the spring towards the
    throttle body to release it from the tab on the pedal arm, and then turn
    the black toothed disc anti-clockwise, about  a centimeter, until it clicks.
    Now try moving the black plastic pedal arm to make sure that the metal
    throttle body arm (the lever pointing to the right) is not following it
    anymore.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20041006m.Seal.jpg" title="Seal" date="06.10.2004">
    Install a fresh rubber seal and coat it with vaseline.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20041006n.Installation.jpg" title="Installation" date="06.10.2004">
    Start by connecting the hose on the back of the throttle body and continue
    in reverse order. The bolt tightening torque is 7.4 ft-lbs.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
</picture-set>
