<?xml version="1.0"?>
<picture-set title="Saab NG900: Old Style Shifter Linkage">

  <description>
  <p>A rebuild of the gearshift linkage on the 1996 Saab 900. The procedure
  is performed on the old style linkage found on the 94-96 model years.
  The linkage on my car grew very loose and caused a lot of free play in the
  shifter. The ideal approach would have been to install a new linkage
  of the updated design, but with the cost of the new part being $200 USD,
  a free rebuild attempt seemed rather attractive. The rebuild proved
  successful, resulting in a much tighter and more precise shifter feel.</p>

  <p>To remove the linkage, first lock the transmission in fourth gear and undo
  the clamp that connects the linkage to the gearshift rod as described in
  <a href="#/content/saab/20050325-saab-ng900-shifter-alignment">the shifter alignment
  procedure</a>.</p>

  <h2>Tools:</h2>
  <ul>
    <li>13 mm socket;</li>
    <li>long socket extension;</li>
    <li>ratchet handle;</li>
    <li>torque wrench;</li>
    <li>two L-shaped 3 mm Allen keys;</li>
    <li>needle-nose pliers.</li>
  </ul>
  </description>

  <picture name="20050404a.Removal.jpg" title="Removal" date="04.04.2005">
    With transmission locked in 4th gear and the clamp undone, move the shifter
    to the 3rd gear position to disconnect the rod from the linkage. Undo the
    bolt connecting the linkage to the transmission (13 mm).
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050404b.Bushing.jpg" title="Bushing" date="04.04.2005">
    Slide the linkage from the transmission rod towards the firewall. This will
    effectively remove the other side of the linkage from the bushing on the
    engine mount. The bushing is covered by a rubber boot that's attached to
    the linkage. Pull the boot off upwards and remove it together with the
    linkage.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050404c.Linkage.jpg" title="Linkage" date="04.04.2005">
    The linkage on the table. With 267K on the car, it has a lot of play in it.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050404d.Disassembled.jpg" title="Disassembled" date="04.04.2005">
    Undo the locking pins with needle nose pliers and take the linkage apart.
    Clean the dirt and examine the condition of the parts.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050404e.Washers.jpg" title="Washers" date="04.04.2005">
    The plastic plugs appeared to be worn, so I added a thin nylon washer
    in between the plastic and metal parts on each side, and assembled the
    linkage with fresh grease.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050404f.Ready_to_go.jpg" title="Ready to go" date="04.04.2005">
    Put the boot on and install the linkage back on the car. Tighten the bolt
    on the transmission rod to 15.5 ft-lbs. Re-insert the shifter rod into the
    the linkage at the firewall and complete
    <a href="#/content/saab/20050325-saab-ng900-shifter-alignment">the alignment
    procedure</a>.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
</picture-set>
