<?xml version="1.0"?>
<picture-set title="Saab NG900/9-3: Steering Rack Clamp and Brace">

  <description>
  <p>Steering rack clamp and brace installation on the 1996 Saab 900 (applies to all 1994-1998 900 and 1999-2002 9-3).</p>
  
  <p>Parts from <a href="https://www.genuinesaab.com">Taliaferro</a>, Powerflex and MP Performance.</p>

  <h2>Tools:</h2>
  <ul>
    <li>19 mm wrench: lower nut on the Taliaferro clamp;</li>
    <li>13 mm socket: clamp bolts;</li>
    <li>11 mm socket and wrench: brace to fender bolt;</li>
    <li>car jack and stands;</li>
    <li>ratchet handle.</li>
  </ul>
  </description>

  <picture name="20060628a.Clamp_and_brace.jpg" title="Clamp and brace" date="28.06.2006">
    Taliaferro clamp and brace kit. The aluminium clamp eliminates the play
    of the steering rack, and the brace reinforces the attachment so the load
    is not placed on the firewall alone.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050401a.Clamp_and_brace.jpg" title="Clamp and brace" date="01.04.2005">
    An older design by MP Performance, it's not available for sale anymore.
    It also had some clearance problems with the brace (see below).
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050401b.Under_the_hood.jpg" title="Under the hood" date="01.04.2005">
    Raise the car. Locate the top bolt on the steering rack clamp and remove it.
    In theory, the lower nut can also be removed with the front wheels on the
    ground, but it much easier from below (raising the car also gives you the
    access under the fender for the brace). Undo the lower nut and remove
    the clamp.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050401c.Clamps.jpg" title="Clamps" date="01.04.2005">
    Left: a clamp from the 94-96 900. Right: a clamp from the 97-2002 900/9-3.
    Apparently, when the rack design changed in the 1997, Saab kept the clamp
    and increased the size of the bushing. As the result, newer cars have the
    rack attached by a piece of jelly. Below is the MP clamp for
    94-96 900. The clamp for newer cars would be smaller in size and have a
    greater effect on reducing the play in the steering.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050401d.From_below.jpg" title="From below" date="01.04.2005">
    Install the new backing plate and the clamp. The steering rods and hoses
    on top of the rack make it difficult to insert the clamp from above, but
    t's quite easy from under the car. Attach the hose tie -- it used to be
    under the clamp, but it didn't seem to fit well under the MP clamp.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060628g.Lower_nut.jpg" title="Lower nut" date="28.06.2006">
    Shown here is the Taliaferro clamp (the engine is removed on this car ;).
    The clamp is very thick, so it comes with an oddly shaped lower nut to
    accommodate a short stud under the steering rack.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050401e.Rivet.jpg" title="Rivet" date="01.04.2005">
    Locate the top right plastic rivet around the opening for the tie rod. If you can't
    just pull it out, cut it from under the fender,
    and the head will fall out on the engine side.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050401f.Brace.jpg" title="Brace" date="01.04.2005">
    Attach the brace to the clamp using the bolt that's supplied with the
    kit. The bolt is longer than the original to compensate for extra thickness
    of the brace. It also has threadlock on it. Do not tighten the bolt yet.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050401g.Nut.jpg" title="Nut" date="01.04.2005">
    Attach the other end of the brace to the fender and tighten the nut on it.
    It seems like a good idea to apply some loctite on the thread too.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060628h.Brace_installed.jpg" title="Brace installed" date="28.06.2006">
    Tighten the clamp to 18 ft-lbs. This picture also demonstrates
    how the Taliaferro brace is designed for extra clearance above
    the steering rod. The following two images show what happens if there
    is not enough clearance.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050703.Bent_brace.jpg" title="Bent brace" date="03.07.2005">
    If the brace is straight, it cuts right across the steering rod window.
    A couple of months after installing my first brace, I discovered that the
    rod was hitting the brace in sharp turns. The brace had a major clearance
    issue.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050913.Bent_brace.jpg" title="Bent brace" date="13.09.2005">
    Here's the brace off the car. You can see that it's visibly bent and
    seriously scuffed.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060628b.Clamp.jpg" title="Clamp" date="28.06.2006">
    If you want to further firm up the steering, you can replace the driver
    side steering rack bushing. It's located right next to the steering
    column at the firewall, under the fuse box.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060628c.Lower_nut.jpg" title="Lower nut" date="28.06.2006">
    If your car is not all apart like mine, you might find it easier to
    access the bolts through the steering rod opening.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060628d.Rubber_bushing.jpg" title="Rubber bushing" date="28.06.2006">
    Once the clamp is off, pull the rubber bushing that wraps around the
    steerng rack.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060628e.Powerflex.jpg" title="Powerflex" date="28.06.2006">
    Powerflex makes a nice polyurethane replacement for this bushing,
    catalog part PFF66-412 ("Steering rack mounting - flat bottom").
    Note that 9-3s have a 3-bolt bracket here, likely for stronger bracing.
    It's a bit more labor intensive to remove.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060628f.Installed.jpg" title="Installed" date="28.06.2006">
    Apply the grease supplied in the kit and put the bushing on.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060628i.Clamp.jpg" title="Clamp" date="28.06.2006">
    Tighten the clamp to 18 ft-lbs. If you removed BOTH clamps, attach the
    driver side first.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
</picture-set>
