<?xml version="1.0"?>
<picture-set title="9-5: Steering Wheel">

  <description>
  <p>Steering wheel replacement on a Saab 9-5. The worn out original wheel gets
  replaced with a perforated leather sport steering wheel from an Aero.</p>

  <p>Use extra care while working with SRS components. Never drop the airbag.
  Store it in a safe place at room temperature, away from explosive or
  flammable materials. Always store it with the metal casing facing
  downwards to avoid injury if something triggers it by accident.</p>

  <h2>Tools:</h2>
  <ul>
    <li>22 mm socket: steering wheel nut;</li>
    <li>Torx T30 socket: airbag screws;</li>
    <li>needle-nose pliers;</li>
    <li>flat screwdriver.</li>
  </ul>
  </description>

  <picture name="20071020a.Old_wheel.jpg" title="Old wheel" date="20.10.2007">
    Set the wheel straight.
    Make sure the ignition is off before starting the work.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20071020b.Covers.jpg" title="Screw caps" date="20.10.2007">
    Pop the caps on both sides on the steering wheel and undo the Torx screws
    holding the airbag.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20071020c.Airbag.jpg" title="Airbag" date="20.10.2007">
    Tilt the airbag forward and unplug the connector. Use extra care when
    working with SRS components.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20071020d.Connectors.jpg" title="Connectors" date="20.10.2007">
    Unplug the two remaining connectors, lift the airbag and store it in
    a safe place.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20071020e.Nut.jpg" title="Nut" date="20.10.2007">
    Undo the 22 mm nut on the steering column and remove the rubber damper
    with the metal bracket. The wires are fed through the bracket, so take
    care while removing it.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20071020f.Unbolted.jpg" title="Unbolted" date="20.10.2007">
    Hit the steering wheel with a palm of your hand from behind to knock it
    loose. Be careful not to damage the wires if the wheel suddenly comes off
    the column shaft.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20071020g.Column.jpg" title="Column" date="20.10.2007">
    To prevent any damage to the tilting/telescoping joint, make sure the
    adjuster is locked before knocking the steering wheel off.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20071020h.Old_vs_new.jpg" title="Old vs new" date="20.10.2007">
    The replacement steering wheel comes from a 2000 Aero.
    It has perforated leather and nice grips at 10 and 2 o'clock.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20071020i.Fitted.jpg" title="Fitted" date="20.10.2007">
    Place the new wheel onto the shaft, feed the wires through the opening.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20071020j.Nut.jpg" title="Nut" date="20.10.2007">
    Install the bracket (pass the wires through the hole again) and
    tighten the nut to 28 ft-lbs.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20071020k.Damper.jpg" title="Damper" date="20.10.2007">
    Fit the damper, use the pliers to pull the soft rubber grips through their
    holes.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20071020l.Connectors.jpg" title="Connectors" date="20.10.2007">
    Re-connect the horn and stereo control harnesses and attach them to the velcro
    pad on the bottom of the housing. Plug the airbag connector in.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20071020m.Screws.jpg" title="Screws" date="20.10.2007">
    Position the airbag so it matches the guiding holes and tighten the
    screws on the sides.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20071020n.New_wheel.jpg" title="New wheel" date="20.10.2007">
    Insert the screw caps and take a proud look at your new sport steering wheel.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
</picture-set>
