<?xml version="1.0"?>
<picture-set title="Saab NG900: Clarion CD Changer Repair">

  <description>
  <p>The stereo head unit on a 1994-1998 Saab 900 does not have a CD player,
  which is a bit strange for an entry luxury car of the mid-90s.
  However, it does support Clarion C-Bus CD changers. Just plug and play.</p>

  <p>I went on eBay and bought a Clarion RDC605 CD changer for $52.
  Plugged it in... and it didn't play. Here are the symptoms:</p>
  <ul>
    <li>the changer loads the cartridge and checks every slot for CDs;</li>
    <li>when you select "CD" on the head unit, the changer attempts to select
      the first available CD;</li>
    <li>the SID displays
      <pre> CD1 WAIT </pre>
      for a few seconds, and then switches to the radio;</li>
    <li>subsequent attempts to press "CD" on the head unit result in a brief
      message
      <pre> CD1 TRK 01 </pre>
      and then the unit switches back to radio again.</li>
  </ul>

  <p>If you take off the cover and watch the changer trying to load a CD, you
  discover that it would indeed try to pull a CD from the cartridge, load it
  into the player, and then do it again, and again, and then stop after a few
  more attempts.</p>
  </description>

  <picture name="20041222a.Opened.jpg" title="1. Opened" date="22.12.2004">
    When I opened the changer, a small piece of PCB fell out of the box.
    You can see it below the screwdriver, it has a tiny contact switch on it.
    The circuits were obviously torn.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20041222b.Broken_part.jpg" title="2. Broken part" date="22.12.2004">
    Here's where the switch is supposed to be. Every time a changer loads
    a CD, a small metal arm hits the switch and signals the drive to stop the
    movement. I find this to be a poor design, as the edge of the PCB is under
    a stress every time the drive loads, and the board is only a few millimeters
    wide at this location (there's a cut-out to let the wires through).
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20041222c.Reinforced.jpg" title="3. Reinforced" date="22.12.2004">
    I glued two pieces of plastic on either side of the board and tightened
    this "band-aid" with a screw to reinforce the joint. Note the tab on the
    right side of the board (see the next picture).
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20041222d.Assembled.jpg" title="4. Assembled" date="22.12.2004">
    The tab on the right side goes into an opening in the frame to keep the board
    steady. However, there's still a gap between the board and the frame, so
    the metal arm that's hitting the switch would still bend the board and
    eventually break it again.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20041222e.Finished.jpg" title="5. Finished" date="22.12.2004">
    Here's the finished assembly with an extra bump stop to fill the gap and
    the wires soldered on to restore the broken connections. The changer
    works now.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
</picture-set>
