<?xml version="1.0"?>
<picture-set title="Saab Trionic 5 BPC Dissection">

  <description>
  <p>The boost pressure control valve (BPC), also known as the APC
  solenoid valve, is used on most Saab engines to control the turbo
  charging pressure. The valves on Trionic5 models are often prone to
  failure. In some cases it just needs a good cleaning, but sometimes it
  becomes permanently stuck in one position, causing the car to either stay
  on base boost, or go into overboost until it hits the fuel cut. This
  article provides an insight on what could be casing these permanent faliures.</p>
  </description>

  <picture name="20070416a.BPC.jpg" title="BPC" date="16.04.2007">
    The middle outlet (marked "W") is connected to the
    wastegate, the top ("C") goes to the compressor housing of the turbo,
    and the bottom ("R") to the intake. The boost is adjusted by
    alternatively supplying the wastegate actuator with the pressure from
    the turbo or venting it to the intake, thus allowing the wastegate to
    stay closed at pressure levels exceeding the base boost.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070416b.Tester.jpg" title="Tester" date="16.04.2007">
    The valve contains two solenoid coils.
    Sometimes these coils burn out, so testing them is always a good
    first step. It's easy to do right on the car, just unplug the connector.
    The resistance for each
    coil should be 3 Ohm (+/- 1 Ohm) between the
    middle and either of the outer pins. The combined resistance of both
    should be about 6 Ohm between the outer pins.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070416c.Seam.jpg" title="Seam" date="16.04.2007">
    The valve is glued together, you can still see traces of adhesive in the
    seam. You can scrape it off if you're patient. I just used a hack saw.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070416d.Apart.jpg" title="Apart" date="16.04.2007">
    Inside, you will find the solenoid pair with fragile wires leading to
    the harness connector. The top and bottom receiving outlets are sealed
    with rubber O-rings.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070416e.Solenoid.jpg" title="Solenoid" date="16.04.2007">
    The solenoid unit has two electromagnets with a membrane in the middle.
    The ECU pulses the current at 90Hz (or 70 Hz above 2500 RPM), alternating
    between the coils and pulling the membrane to one side or another. This
    allows for precise control of boost pressure.
    <image width="725" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070416f.Membrane.jpg" title="Membrane" date="16.04.2007">
    In this BPC, the membrane cracked from stress. A piece of it was jammed
    on the pressure side of the valve, keeping it open. As the result, the
    wastegate actuator was permanently connected to the compressor, so the
    wastegate always opened when it reached the base boost.
    <image width="799" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070422a.Clamped.jpg" title="Clamped" date="22.04.2007">
    The remaining part of the membrane was still large enough to cover
    the valve opening, so I decided to give it a try. The BPC was assembled,
    glued back together and sealed with automotive adhesive.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070422b.Finished.jpg" title="Finished" date="22.04.2007">
    After the sealant dried up, I installed the valve on the car and found
    it fully functional! This proves that at least some BPCs can
    be repaired.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
</picture-set>
