<?xml version="1.0"?>
<picture-set title="Saab NG900/9-3: Exhaust Manifold">

  <description>
  <p>Exhaust manifold removal and re-installation on the 
  1996 Saab 900 (4 cylinder turbo).
  A 9-3 or 9-5 would be very similar, except for a few minor details.
  The manifold had to come off because there were two broken studs on the
  driver side of the manifold. The gasket needed a replacement too.</p>

  <h2>Tools:</h2>
  <ul>
    <li>13 mm socket: manifold, turbo and steering pump nuts;</li>
    <li>two 13 mm wrenches: manifold, turbo and steering pump nuts;</li>
    <li>10 mm socket: air filter housing;</li>
    <li>7 mm socket: hose clamps;</li>
    <li>Torx T27 socket: PCV line;</li>
    <li>ratchet handle;</li>
    <li>torque wrench;</li>
    <li>long 1/2" socket extension;</li>
    <li>4 mm Allen key;</li>
    <li>drill with cobalt bits and right angle attachment;</li>
    <li>a piece of metal pipe or a hose coupler that fits the stud holes;</li>
    <li>small mirror;</li>
    <li>screw extractors;</li>
    <li>tap wrench (optionally with a 8x1.25 mm tap);</li>
    <li>car jacks and stands or ramps.</li>
  </ul>
  </description>

  <picture name="20050423a.Manifold.jpg" title="Manifold" date="23.04.2005">
    I had a misfortune of having a couple of studs go on the exhaust manifold.
    One day they just disappeared, leaving two gaping holes in the manifold.
    The studs were broken flush with the head.
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050423b.Broken_studs.jpg" title="Broken studs" date="23.04.2005">
    A close-up of the problem area. In my case it was not enough to just drill
    the studs out, because the gasket moved and was partially blocking the
    port (and causing a leak too). Therefore the entire manifold had to come
    off.
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050423c.Intake.jpg" title="Intake" date="23.04.2005">
    The first step is to remove the intake. The airbox cover comes off
    with the intake pipe and the return line from the bypass valve.
    Plug the turbo inlet pipe immediately, you don't want any dirt to
    get in there.
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050423d.Belt.jpg" title="Belt" date="23.04.2005">
    Loosen the belt with a long 1/2" socket extension and lock the tensioner
    with a thin Allen key. Remove the belt from the steering pump pulley.
    This picture shows the airbox still in place, but it's actually better to
    remove it before starting on the pump. The airbox is secured by three
    10 mm nuts.
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050423e.Steering_pump.jpg" title="Steering pump" date="23.04.2005">
    The steering pump bracket is attached to the head with two bolts on the top
    and one under the pulley (use a 13 mm socket or wrench here). The lower
    bolt is a bit of a pain to get to. Unbolting the metal PCV vent pipe from
    the valve cover gives you some extra room.
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050423f.Turbo_studs.jpg" title="Turbo studs" date="23.04.2005">
    The manifold to the turbo nuts are next (13 mm). You can see that all nuts
    have been generously sprayed with rust solvent the night before. That helped!
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050423g.Manifold_studs.jpg" title="Manifold studs" date="23.04.2005">
    The nuts on the remaining manifold studs come next. The three studs in the
    middle are short, while the outer ones are long and have cylindrical spacers
    on them, designed to help with thermal expansion. 
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050423h.Nuts_removed.jpg" title="Nuts removed" date="23.04.2005">
    The leftmost nut took the stud with it, but the rest came off without
    a fight. The WIS calls for complete turbo removal, otherwise there's not
    enough room to get the manifold off the studs on both sides. We chose to
    remove all manifold studs instead, since we planned to replace them
    anyway.
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050423l.Turbo_stay.jpg" title="Turbo stay" date="23.04.2005">
    An extra wiggle room is still required to remove the manifold. It can
    achieved by unbolting the downpipe from the turbo, and the turbo
    stay from the engine block.
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050423i.Hose_coupler.jpg" title="Hose coupler" date="23.04.2005">
    This brass hose coupler has been found at the local hardware store. It was
    a snug fit to the manifold and worked well as a guide for the drill bit,
    helping to ensure that we start drilling at the centre of the stud. A small
    mirror came handy to peek into the hole to observe the results.
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050423j.Drill.jpg" title="Drill" date="23.04.2005">
    The right angle drill extension is needed since there is not enough room
    to fit the drill in front of the head. I initially purchased a set of left
    handed HSS drill bits, but they didn't last long enough as the studs were 
    too hard for them. This set of cobalt bits was much better suited for the
    job.
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050423k.Stud_removal.jpg" title="Stud removal" date="23.04.2005">
    The remaining manifold studs were removed using an old trick with two
    nuts tightened together. The short stud closest to the two previously
    broken ones also broke after we attempted to remove it. Fortunately, it
    left a piece long enough so we could grab it with vice grips and unscrew
    the stud later when the manifold was off.
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050423m.Manifold.jpg" title="Manifold" date="23.04.2005">
    Here's the manifold off the car. You can see than its mating surfaces
    and the gasket are still clean where the nuts were tight, but the fourth
    cylinder area is covered with soot on both sides.
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050423n.INP.jpg" title="I.N.P." date="23.04.2005">
    My father happened to be visiting from overseas and didn't mind getting
    his hands dirty. He helped a great deal and made the job much easier than
    it would have been if I did it alone. Thanks, dad! ;)
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050423o.First.jpg" title="First" date="23.04.2005">
    With the manifold off, it was easy to drill the holes deeper. Then, after
    some struggle with a screw extractor, the first stud came out.
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050423p.Second.jpg" title="Second" date="23.04.2005">
    And then the other one.
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050423q.Extractor.jpg" title="Extractor" date="23.04.2005">
    Here's the remaining part of the broken stud as it came out of the head.
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050423r.Stud.jpg" title="Stud" date="23.04.2005">
    You can see a close-up of the hole we drilled in one of the studs.
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050424a.New_parts.jpg" title="New parts" date="24.04.2005">
    About $60 worth of parts: new gaskets, studs, nuts and washers. The big
    gasket goes its metal side to the manifold, soft side to the head.
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050424b.Turbo_gasket.jpg" title="Turbo gasket" date="24.04.2005">
    Time to clean the metal shavings and dirt, and pull the rug out of the
    turbo housing. The gasket goes on.
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050424c.New_studs.jpg" title="New studs" date="24.04.2005">
    The manifold slides onto the turbo side studs first, and then new studs
    can be screwed into the head. Some were easy to put in, some requred the
    two nut trick again.
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050424d.Nuts_and_washers.jpg" title="New studs" date="24.04.2005">
    After all the studs are in, start putting the nuts on. Do not tighten them
    yet, just put the nuts on both the head and the turbo side. Tighten the
    turbo stay on the engine block.
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050424e.Tightening.jpg" title="Tightening" date="24.04.2005">
    Tighten the nuts on the manifold and the turbo to 16 ft-lbs. Connect the
    downpipe to the turbo.
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050424f.Steering_pump.jpg" title="Steering pump" date="24.04.2005">
    The steering pump bolts are hard to reach, especially the bolt below.
    There's only enough room to turn the wrench 1/12 of a turn.
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050424g.Belt.jpg" title="Belt" date="24.04.2005">
    Put the belt on and attach the vent pipe to the valve cover.
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050424h.Done.jpg" title="Done" date="24.04.2005">
    Install the airbox and enjoy the job well done.
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
</picture-set>
