<?xml version="1.0"?>
<picture-set title="Saab NG900/9-3: Stainless Brake Lines">

  <description>
  <p>Googridge stainless brake line installation on a 1996 Saab 900
  (applies to all 1994-1998 900 and 1999-2002 9-3). This installation was
  prompted by a cracked brake line, but is usually performed to enhance the
  braking performance of the car.</p>

  <h2>Tools and supplies:</h2>
  <ul>
    <li>24 mm wrench: brake line retainer nuts (for Goodridge kit);</li>
    <li>19 mm wrench: brake line nuts (for Goodridge kit);</li>
    <li>17 mm socket: wheel bolts;</li>
    <li>17 mm wrench: brake line nuts (for original rubber lines);</li>
    <li>13 mm flare wrench: hard line nuts in the rear;</li>
    <li>11 mm socket: banjo bolts on front calipers;</li>
    <li>10 mm flare wrench: hard line nuts;</li>
    <li>pliers: brake line retainers;</li>
    <li>DOT4 brake fluid, 600 ml or more;</li>
    <li>pressure bleeder (recommended);</li>
    <li>torque wrench;</li>
    <li>car jack and axle stands;</li>
    <li>breaker bar.</li>
  </ul>
  </description>

  <picture name="20060213a.The_kit.jpg" title="The kit" date="13.02.2006">
    The Goodridge kit for 900/9-3 includes four stainless braided teflon coated
    brake lines, as well as new washers, fasteners and retainers. It is
    designed as a direct replacement for stock rubber lines.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060213b.Broken_line.jpg" title="Broken line" date="13.02.2006">
    When your car is 10 years and 300K km old, pay close attention to your
    brake lines. They might corrode and break off, just like mine did.
    I'm glad it happened on my driveway instead of the road.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060213c.Front_line.jpg" title="Front line" date="13.02.2006">
    Raise the front of the car and remove the wheels (17 mm socket). Find where
    the rubber brake line that goes to the front caliper is attached to the
    green hard line.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060213d.Flare_wrench.jpg" title="Flare wrench" date="13.02.2006">
    It is important to use flare wrenches for all hard line nuts -- they are so
    small and easy to strip with conventional open wrenches. Get a pan to
    catch the brake fluid that will leak out when you disconnect the lines.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060213e.Top_end.jpg" title="Top end" date="13.02.2006">
    The small hard line nut is 10 mm, the bottom takes a regular 17 mm wrench.
    Once the top nut is off, remove the retainer clip and pull the rubber
    line down.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060213f.Bottom_end.jpg" title="Bottom end" date="13.02.2006">
    The banjo bolt on the caliper takes an 11 mm socket. Get ready for more
    brake fluid spillage.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060213g.Banjo_bolt.jpg" title="Banjo bolt" date="13.02.2006">
    The kit came with new banjo bolts which had the wrong thread for my
    calipers, so I reused old bolts with new washers from the kit.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060213h.Caliper.jpg" title="Caliper" date="13.02.2006">
    Attach the stainless line to the caliper so it points upwards but leaves
    sufficient clearance to access the top slider pin and its dust cap.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060213i.Installed.jpg" title="Installed" date="13.02.2006">
    Bolt the top end of the line to the fender (Goodridge uses 24 mm retainer
    nuts instead of clips here), and connect the hard line. Done!
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060213j.Rear_right.jpg" title="Rear right" date="13.02.2006">
    Raise the rear of the car and release the handbrake. Locate the brake
    line by the right rear spring. The clearance is tight, especially near the
    top end. Use a 13 mm flare wrench for the top hard line nut, 10 mm
    for the bottom.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060213k.Unbolted.jpg" title="Unbolted" date="13.02.2006">
    After the hard lines are off, pull retainer clips from both ends.
    The fuel hose gets in the way of removing the top clip, but it's doable.
    Once the clips are off, pull the old rubber line.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060213l.New_line.jpg" title="New line" date="13.02.2006">
    Install the new line. It's easier to bolt the hard lines on before the
    retainers are secured. In addition, the top end nut on new lines was
    too small so it kept slipping through the hole in its bracket, and
    it took some creativity to hold it in place.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060213m.Rear_left.jpg" title="Rear left" date="13.02.2006">
    The other line is found next to the left rear spring, with its top end
    properly blocked by the exhaust pipe.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060213n.Removed.jpg" title="Removed" date="13.02.2006">
    The hard line nut sizes are the same: 13 mm at the top and 10 mm at the
    bottom.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060213o.Done.jpg" title="Done" date="13.02.2006">
    Install the last new line. The retainers on the left side are easier to
    install than on the right: clip on the top end and nut at the bottom.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060213p.Bleeding.jpg" title="Bleeding" date="13.02.2006">
    Connect a pressure bleeder to the brake fluid tank and bleed the brakes
    in the following order: front left, front right, rear left, rear right.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
</picture-set>
