<?xml version="1.0"?>
<picture-set title="Saab 9-5: Rear Trailing Arm Bushings">

  <description>
  <p>Rear trailing arm bushing replacement on a 1999 Saab 9-5. A set of polyurethane
  bushings is being installed to replace the worn out old rubber pieces and
  improve cornering stability.</p>

  <p>Saab sells replacement bushings with aluminium sleeves and supplies a
  set of tools to get them in and out. We're installing aftermarket
  polyurethane inserts, which are much easier to get in, but the old
  bushing still needs to be pressed out of the arm. With no Saab tools
  handy, we will be using the trusty hacksaw and gear puller combo.</p>

  <h2>Tools:</h2>
  <ul>
    <li>21 mm socket: lower shock bolt (optional);</li>
    <li>18 mm socket: bushing housing bolts;</li>
    <li>17 mm socket: wheel bolts;</li>
    <li>16 mm socket: anti-roll bar link bolts;</li>
    <li>10 mm socket: brake line and cable bracket bolts;</li>
    <li>torque wrench;</li>
    <li>car jack and axle stands;</li>
    <li>breaker bar;</li>
    <li>gear puller;</li>
    <li>hacksaw;</li>
    <li>hammer and rubber mallet.</li>
  </ul>
  </description>

  <picture name="20070930a.Jack_stands.jpg" title="Jack stands" date="30.09.2007">
    Raise the car and secure it on jack stands. Take the wheels off. Both wheels
    need to be in the air so the suspension is level.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070930b.Link.jpg" title="Link" date="30.09.2007">
    Detach the anti-roll bar link from the trailing arm.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070930c.Bracket.jpg" title="Bracket" date="30.09.2007">
    Unscrew the bracket supporting the brake line and handbrake cable.
    There should be no tension in the handbrake, so don't forget to release
    it when you raise the car.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070930d.Shock.jpg" title="Shock" date="30.09.2007">
    The Saab Workshop Manual does not mention unbolting the shock, but I
    found that it allows for more freedom to move the arm around. Use a big
    breaker bar to loosen this bolt.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070930e.Jack.jpg" title="Jack" date="30.09.2007">
    Support the trailing arm with a jack so it won't strain the brake line
    when you unbolt it from the car.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070930f.Housing.jpg" title="Housing" date="30.09.2007">
    Undo three 18 mm bolts holding the bushing housing to the car. Carefully
    lower the jack, support the brake line separately.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070930g.Clamp.jpg" title="Clamp" date="30.09.2007">
    Before taking on the bolt that goes through the bushing, clamp the housing
    to the trailing arm. This will make it easier to loosen the nut.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070930h.Bush.jpg" title="Bush" date="30.09.2007">
    Pull the bolt out and slide the housing off the bushing. The housing is
    tied to the handbrake cable, just let it hang off it.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070930i.Gear_puller.jpg" title="Gear puller" date="30.09.2007">
    Push the rubber part of the bushing out using a gear puller or another suitable
    tool.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070930j.Hacksaw.jpg" title="Hacksaw" date="30.09.2007">
    Assemble the hacksaw with a blade inside the bushing and cut through the
    soft aluminium sleeve.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070930k.Sleeve.jpg" title="Sleeve" date="30.09.2007">
    Chisel the sleeve out and discard the old bushing. Clean the inside of the
    hole and all the contact surfaces.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070930l.New_bushings.jpg" title="New bushings" date="30.09.2007">
    New polyurethane bushing from Powerflex. Comes with a stainless inner
    sleeve and a bag of grease.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070930m.Fitted.jpg" title="Fitted" date="30.09.2007">
    Lubricate the bushing, slide in the polyurethane halves first, then the
    inner sleeve.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070930n.Housing.jpg" title="Housing" date="30.09.2007">
    Fit the housing, clamp it to the arm and tighten the nut to 70 ft-lbs
    +60 degrees.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070930o.Lifted.jpg" title="Lifted" date="30.09.2007">
    Lift the trailing arm using a jack until the bushing enters its socket
    on the underside on the car.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070930p.Bolted_on.jpg" title="Bolted on" date="30.09.2007">
    Position the housing as close to the original location as possible and
    tighten the bolts to 66 ft-lbs +30 degrees.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070930q.Bracket.jpg" title="Bracket" date="30.09.2007">
    Re-attach the brake line bracket. These thin M6 screws broke off on both
    sides when I took them out, so I had to re-drill and tap the holes again.
    Put the screws on anti-seize.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070930r.Link.jpg" title="Link" date="30.09.2007">
    Tighten the anti-roll bar link bolt to 40 ft-lbs. Re-fit the lower shock
    bolt if you unbolted it (140 ft-lbs). Tighten the wheels to 81 ft-lbs and
    lower the car to the ground.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
</picture-set>
