<?xml version="1.0"?>
<picture-set title="Saab NG900/9-3: Engine Accessories">

  <description>
  <p>Manifolds, pumps and other accessories on a Saab B204/B234
  family engine. The work was done on a 1995 Saab 900SE turbo, but will also
  apply to any four cylinder 1994-1998 900 turbo and 1999 9-3. Newer cars
  using the B205/B235 engine family are also quite similar.</p>

  <h2>Tools:</h2>
  <ul>
    <li>22 mm wrench: oil thermostat cap, oil pressure sensor;</li>
    <li>19 mm wrench: intake manifold coolant nipple;</li>
    <li>17 mm socket: temperature sender;</li>
    <li>16 mm socket: engine mount, starter;</li>
    <li>13 mm socket: oil filter housing, coolant pump, alternator, exhaust manifold, turbo;</li>
    <li>12 mm socket: thermostat, intake manifold, banjo bolts;</li>
    <li>10 mm socket: coolant pipes;</li>
    <li>8 mm Allen socket: alternator bolts, belt tensioner;</li>
    <li>torque wrench;</li>
  </ul>
  </description>

  <picture name="20060709a.Engine.jpg" title="Engine" date="09.07.2006">
    A freshly rebuilt engine just waiting to go back into the car.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060709b.Engine.jpg" title="Engine" date="09.07.2006">
    Refer to
    <a href="#/content/saab/20060704-saab-b204-b234-engine-assembly">this document</a> for
    more detail on the base engine assembly.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060709c.Oil_filter_housing.jpg" title="Oil filter housing" date="09.07.2006">
    Clean the oil filter housing, the oil thermostat, and get a new filter ready.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060709d.Oil_filter.jpg" title="Oil filter" date="09.07.2006">
    Install the filter housing (13 mm socket), tighten the thermostat cap
    (22 mm). Lubricate the O-ring on the filter and screw it on.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060709e.Thermostat.jpg" title="Thermostat" date="09.07.2006">
    Fit a new seal on the thermostat and clean the thermostat housing.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060709f.Thermostat_housing.jpg" title="Thermostat housing" date="09.07.2006">
    Attach the thermostat housing (12 mm socket).
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060709g.Coolant_pump.jpg" title="Coolant pump" date="09.07.2006">
    The coolant pump is next. Coat new O-rings with vaseline and put them
    on the coolant inlet pipe.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060709h.Coolant_inlet.jpg" title="Coolant inlet" date="09.07.2006">
    Fit the inlet into the slot in front of cylinder #1. Make sure the flap
    on the inlet matches the cut-out on the right.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060709i.Pump_installed.jpg" title="Pump installed" date="09.07.2006">
    Install the coolant pump, check that the outer O-ring on the inlet is not
    jammed. Tighten the bolts.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060709j.Coolant_pipes.jpg" title="Coolant pipes" date="09.07.2006">
    Attach the pipes leading to the heat exchanger and expansion tank. Renew
    the O-ring and the short rubber U-bend if needed. Tighten the 10 mm screw
    on the pump.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060709k.Coolant_pipes.jpg" title="Coolant pipes" date="09.07.2006">
    Secure the pipes on the far side of the engine -- one screw at the
    corner, and two more on the thermostat housing.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060709l.Manifold_studs.jpg" title="Manifold studs" date="09.07.2006">
    Screw in exhaust manifold studs. The factory configuration has longer studs
    in the outer holes, but the benefit of those is debatable since they are
    always the first to break, so I'm using short studs instead.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060709m.Exhaust_gasket.jpg" title="Exhaust gasket" date="09.07.2006">
    Position a new gasket on the studs -- soft side to the head,
    flat side to the manifold.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060709n.Exhaust_manifold.jpg" title="Exhaust manifold" date="09.07.2006">
    Install the manifold, fit the washers and tighten the nuts to 18.5 ft-lbs
    (13 mm socket).
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060709o.Turbocharger.jpg" title="Turbocharger" date="09.07.2006">
    Bolt the turbocharger to the exhaust manifold, use a fresh gasket.
    Install the lower support bar. Connect all coolant and
    oil lines before tightening the banjo bolts. Renew all banjo bolt washers.
    More detail on turbo fitting in <a href="#/content/saab/20051105-saab-ng900-turbo-upgrade">this article</a>.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060709p.Mount_bracket.jpg" title="Mount bracket" date="09.07.2006">
    Install the passenger side engine mount bracket (two 16 mm bolts).
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060709q.Inlet_pipe.jpg" title="Inlet pipe" date="09.07.2006">
    Bolt the inlet pipe to the turbocharger and fit three hoses from
    the boost pressure control valve (BPC). Attach the crankcase vent pipe.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060709r.Lifting_eyes.jpg" title="Lifting eyes" date="09.07.2006">
    Connect the crankcase vent nipple to the valve cover. Install the lifting
    eyes and the wiring harness bracket above the thermostat housing.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060709s.Intake_gasket.jpg" title="Intake gasket" date="09.07.2006">
    Fit the lower part of the oil dipstick tube.
    Insert two studs into the intake manifold mounting holes (you'll be replacing
    them with regular bolts later) and position the gasket on them.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060709t.Intake_manifold.jpg" title="Intake manifold" date="09.07.2006">
    Install the intake manifold and tighten the bolts to 16 ft-lbs (12 mm socket).
    Fit the coolant temperature sensor and the hose nipple if
    you took them out previously.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060709u.Injectors.jpg" title="Injectors" date="09.07.2006">
    Slide the injectors into their sockets and secure the fuel rail with two
    screws.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060709v.Oil_tube.jpg" title="Oil tube" date="09.07.2006">
    Screw in the oil pressure sensor (22 mm wrench), the upper part of the
    dipstick tube and bolt on the intake manifold stay.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060709w.Throttle_body.jpg" title="Throttle body" date="09.07.2006">
    Lubricate the rubber gasket and install the throttle body.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060709x.Hoses.jpg" title="Hoses" date="09.07.2006">
    Fit the vacuum hose to the fuel pressure regulator, and a hose with a check
    valve from the vent nipple (the arrow on the valve should point to the
    throttle body). Attach the throttle body warm-up coolant hoses.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060709y.IAC_valve.jpg" title="IAC valve" date="09.07.2006">
    Install the idle air control valve (IAC) and connect its hoses to
    the throttle body.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060709z0.Wiring_harness.jpg" title="Wiring harness" date="09.07.2006">
    The wiring harness is held by two screws to the fuel rail. Take your time
    fitting all the connectors. Luckily, they are colored, indexed and rather
    hard to plug in incorrectly.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060709z1.Temperature_sender.jpg" title="Temperature sender" date="09.07.2006">
    Attach the temperature sender and the crankshaft position sensor. Plug
    them into the remaining connectors on the harness.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060709z2.Alternator.jpg" title="Alternator" date="09.07.2006">
    Install the intermediate shaft bracket, the alternator
    bracket (13 mm socket) and then two long bolts holding the alternator
    (8 mm Allen).
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060709z3.Starter.jpg" title="Starter" date="09.07.2006">
    Attach the starter motor to the stud on the endplate. Connect the control
    wires and the positive line from the battery.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060709z4.Pulleys.jpg" title="Pulleys" date="09.07.2006">
    Install the belt tensioner (8 mm Allen) and the idler pulleys. The upper
    idler pulley on this picture is the aluminium pulley by Wazee.
    Proceed with engine installation.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
</picture-set>
