<?xml version="1.0"?>
<picture-set title="Saab NG900/9-3: T25 Turbo Replacement">

  <description>
  <p>Garrett T25 turbocharger replacement performed on a 1996 Saab 900. The
  procedure is more or less similar for all Saabs using the B204-B235 engine families.
  Use new copper crush washers for all banjo bolts. It is also a good idea to
  get a new oil feed line, or at least clean the old one from sludge and
  deposits.</p>

  <p>This article describes replacing a stock turbocharger with another OEM
  unit. For upgrade information, refer to
  <a href="#/content/saab/20051105-saab-ng900-turbo-upgrade">this document</a>.</p>

  <b>Tools and supplies:</b>
  <ul>
    <li>13 mm wrench and socket (downpipe and turbo nuts);</li>
    <li>12 mm wrench and socket (banjo bolts);</li>
    <li>10 mm wrench (turbo inlet pipe);</li>
    <li>8 mm socket (shield screws);</li>
    <li>7 mm socket (hose clamps), or flat screwdriver;</li>
    <li>large pliers (oil return hose clamps);</li>
    <li>torque wrench;</li>
    <li>ratchet handle;</li>
    <li>ramps or jacks and stands;</li>
    <li>fresh oil and coolant.</li>
  </ul>
  </description>

  <picture name="20051010a.Shields_down.jpg" title="Shields down" date="10.10.2005">
    Raise the car and remove the lower shields (8 mm hex screws). If you
    have a 9-3, you might be able to access the radiator drain plug without
    removing the shield.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20051010b.Drained_fluids.jpg" title="Drained fluids" date="10.10.2005">
    Drain coolant, engine oil, and remove the oil filter.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20051010c.Downpipe.jpg" title="Downpipe" date="10.10.2005">
    Disconnect the downpipe from the turbo (three 13 mm nuts). If you have a
    subframe brace, you might need to remove that too to allow more room to
    move the downpipe aside.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20051010d.Intake_hose.jpg" title="Intake hose" date="10.10.2005">
    Disconnect the return hose from the bypass valve if you have it (my car
    has a BOV). Remove the rubber elbow between the airbox and the turbo inlet
    pipe.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20051010e.Oil_lines.jpg" title="Oil lines" date="10.10.2005">
    Unbolt the turbo oil feed line from the filter housing (12 mm socket),
    remove the oil return hose and undo the bolt that holds the turbo stay
    to the engine.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20051010f.Coolant_line.jpg" title="Coolant line" date="10.10.2005">
    Undo the banjo bolt on the lower coolant line (12 mm socket). On newer
    cars the line goes to the water pump instead of the block. Put a catch pan
    under the car as there will be coolant dripping.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20051010g.Coolant_line.jpg" title="Coolant line" date="10.10.2005">
    Undo the banjo bolt on the upper coolant line (12 mm socket) on the left
    side of the engine. Don't forget the pan again.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20051010h.Banjo_bolts.jpg" title="Banjo bolts" date="10.10.2005">
    Disconnect all three lines from the turbo (more coolant drips) and remove
    the lines if you can. On my car, I was unable to unbolt the upper coolant
    line.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20051010i.Turbo_hoses.jpg" title="Turbo hoses" date="10.10.2005">
    Remove the intercooler hose from the compressor housing. Unhook the BPC
    hoses. Unbolt the turbo inlet pipe. On T25+B204L, you might need to remove
    the brass BPC hose nipple to gain the access to an inlet pipe bolt.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20051010j.Inlet_pipe.jpg" title="Inlet pipe" date="10.10.2005">
    Remove the turbo inlet pipe together with the metal PCV line (there are
    newer versions that allow you to unbolt the PCV line from the inlet pipe
    instead). Undo the nuts connecting the turbo to the exhaust manifold
    and pull the turbo down.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20051010k.Old_turbo.jpg" title="Old turbo" date="10.10.2005">
    The turbo is removed from the car. You can see some of the lines still
    attached to it.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20051010l.New_vs_old.jpg" title="New vs old" date="10.10.2005">
    The turbo is being replaced with a
    <a href="#/content/saab/20051009-garrett-t25-turbo-rebuild">recently rebuilt unit</a>.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20051010m.Old_vs_new.jpg" title="Old vs new" date="10.10.2005">
    Compare my old style inlet pipe to the new style (this one came from
    a 1999 9-3), which allows an easy access to the PCV pipe bolt.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20051010n.Inlet_pipe.jpg" title="Inlet pipe" date="10.10.2005">
    With my new upgraded inlet pipe, I can bolt it to the turbo prior to
    installation and save myself some hassle. From this moment on, be extra
    clean, as even a tiny grain of sand can ruin your new turbo.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20051010o.Back_in.jpg" title="Back in" date="10.10.2005">
    Put the new turbo back in, and don't forget a new gasket for the exhaust
    manifold flange.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20051010q.Oil_lines.jpg" title="Oil lines" date="10.10.2005">
    Install the oil return hose. Pour some oil into the turbo and install the
    oil feed line.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20051010p.Banjos.jpg" title="Banjos" date="10.10.2005">
    Start connecting the lines to the turbo. Consider new copper washers for
    all banjo bolts.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20051010r.Coolant_line.jpg" title="Coolant line" date="10.10.2005">
    Connect coolant lines to the engine and tighten all six banjo bolts to
    16 ft-lbs.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20051010s.Manifold.jpg" title="Manifold" date="10.10.2005">
    Tighten the nuts on the exhaust manifold (18.5 ft-lbs).
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20051010t.Downpipe.jpg" title="Downpipe" date="10.10.2005">
    Connect the downpipe to the turbo, and re-install the subframe brace if
    you had to remove it.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20051010u.Intercooler_hose.jpg" title="Intercooler hose" date="10.10.2005">
    Fit the intercooler hose on the turbo, intake elbow and the BPC hoses.
    Connect the bypass valve return hose, as well as the PCV line.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20051010v.Oil_filter.jpg" title="Oil filter" date="10.10.2005">
    Refit the oil filter, fill engine oil and coolant. Before starting the car,
    crank it with the ignition cassette harness unplugged to ensure there's
    enough oil in the turbo.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
</picture-set>
