<?xml version="1.0" encoding="koi8-r"?>
<picture-set title="Saab NG900/9-3/9-5: Aluminium Pedals">

  <description>
  <p>Aluminium pedal installation on a Saab 9-5 (also applies to NG900 and 9-3).</p>

  <p>The original pedal pads on the car got torn from heavy use, so I
  decided to replace them with a generic pedal kit from a local auto
  parts store. The mounting hole pattern differs between kits,
  so chose a kit that could be attached to your pedals without having to
  drill into the arm on the back on the pedal. I only had one hole that came
  too close, so I tapped the thread in it instead of using the nut on the back.</p>

  <p>It might be good idea to cover the floor before you start drilling. Getting
  those metal shavings out of the carpet is not easy, even with a powerful
  vacuum cleaner.</p>
  </description>

  <picture name="20071104a.Old_pedals.jpg" title="Old pedals" date="04.11.2007">
    The sorry state of the pedals on a car that's been thoroughly enjoyed for
    almost 10 years and 350K km. You can tell the previous owner did not
    accelerate much, but used the brakes and clutch a lot - the rubber pad on
    the brake pedal is long gone, and the pad on the clutch is coming off too.
    <image width="800" height="595" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20071104b.Aluminium_kit.jpg" title="Aluminium kit" date="04.11.2007">
    A "racing" set of aluminium pedals from a local auto parts store. I
    chose this one because it was all business - three simple pads of plain
    aluminium with riffled surface for extra grip. None of that cheesy nonsense
    like stickers of fake carbon fiber. It was the cheapest too, and it looks the part :)
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20071104c.Pads_removed.jpg" title="Pads removed" date="04.11.2007">
    First, remove the old rubber pads.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20071104d.Drilled.jpg" title="Drilled" date="04.11.2007">
    Then make pilot holes with a thin drill bit.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20071104e.Tapped.jpg" title="Tapped" date="04.11.2007">
    Drill the holes to a larger size. The upper hole on the brake pedal was
    too close to the pedal arm to fit the nut behind it. I just tapped the
    hole instead.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20071104f.Installed.jpg" title="Installed" date="04.11.2007">
    Fit the pads and tighten the screws. The kit came with flat headed screws
    so they would be flush with pedal surface, and nylon locking nuts for
    extra safety.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
</picture-set>
