<?xml version="1.0"?>
<picture-set title="Saab NG900: Line Input">

  <description>
  <p>Head unit modification on a 1994-1998 Saab 900 to add a line input for
  external media player connectivity.</p>

  <p>If you have any kind of suspension modifications, or simply if you drive
  your car hard, you will eventually get tired of your CD changer skipping
  on bumps. Worse even, it does the same with stock suspension.
  An MP3 player sounds like a good alternative, but the stock head unit does
  not have a line input, so you end up using an FM modulator or a cassette
  adapter, which inevitably sacrifices the sound quality. And you probably
  don't want to do that, especially if you just spent a good deal of money
  upgrading the audio components in the car.</p>

  <p>Here's the solution, a relatively easy way to add a direct line input to your
  stock head unit without sacrificing any existing functionality. There is
  a couple of alternative ways, this guide shows how to do it by using the
  tape deck inputs of the internal amplifier.</p>

  <p>Thanks to all SaabCentral forum members who did the research and
  contributed to the installation guide.</p>
  </description>

  <picture name="20060924a.Head_unit.jpg" title="Head unit" date="24.09.2006">
    Remove the head unit from a car. Use a stereo removal tool, or simply
    pop the SID and push the stereo from behind. Make sure you have the
    security code before unplugging the wires!
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060924b.Top_cover.jpg" title="Top cover" date="24.09.2006">
    Start the disassembly by removing the top cover. It's held by two screws
    (you need a small Philips screwdriver).
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060924c.Radiator.jpg" title="Radiator" date="24.09.2006">
    Five more screws, and you can take off the radiator in the rear.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060924d.Face_panel.jpg" title="Face panel" date="24.09.2006">
    The face panel is secured by four latches (two on each side). Unlock
    those and detach the panel - it's plugged into the connector on the
    main board.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060924e.Open.jpg" title="Open" date="24.09.2006">
    Unscrew the top board and pull it up - it's plugged into two small
    connectors at the rear of the stereo.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060924g.Cassette_unit.jpg" title="Cassette unit" date="24.09.2006">
    Take out the screws that hold the cassette mechanism and lift the whole
    unit (its connector is soldered to the bottom of the small vertical board).
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060924i.Rear_board.jpg" title="Rear board" date="24.09.2006">
    Remove the last screws on the rear of the unit, twist the lock in the
    middle of the board and remove the main board out of the case.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060924j.Out_of_the_case.jpg" title="Out of the case" date="24.09.2006">
    The big vertical board can be also detached from the main board. Be
    careful around electric parts, they don't like static electricity.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060924k.Main_board.jpg" title="Main board" date="24.09.2006">
    The underside of the main board has the inputs clearly marked on the
    tape unit connector. You can tap right here, to the "SIGGND", "L" and "R"
    (pins 2-4).
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060924l.Cassette_unit.jpg" title="Cassette unit" date="24.09.2006">
    Alternatively, you can use the tape unit itself - same signals are
    marked on the upper connector ("G", "L", "R", pins 2-4), and the vertical
    board offers lots of room and good soldering spots. Take a note of the
    small switch on the far side, you will need it later.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060924m.Cable.jpg" title="Cable" date="24.09.2006">
    Pull a shielded stereo cable through the holes in the back of the
    case and install the main board.
    <image width="785" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060924n.Soldered.jpg" title="Soldered" date="24.09.2006">
    Solder the stereo cable to the vertical board on the tape unit and secure
    the cable with a zip-tie to protect it from vibration.
    If you're worried about possible interference with the signal from the
    actual ape unit, you can unplug the tape board from the connector
    in the upper left corner (see the previous picture), but I haven't noticed
    any feedback on my unit.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060924o.Circuit_cut.jpg" title="Circuit cut" date="24.09.2006">
    Cut the top lead from the switch and solder a wire on each side of the cut.
    The switch is normally closed (short to ground) when the tape deck is empty
    and open when a cassette is playing. We want to fool the player
    into thinking there's a cassette inside.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060924p.Switch.jpg" title="Switch" date="24.09.2006">
    Install the tape deck and the top board back in place. Connect
    the wires from the cut lead to a momentary switch and fit it between the
    knobs right above the cassette door. The circuit should be normally closed,
    and pressing the switch would interrupt it.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060924q.Assembled.jpg" title="Assembled" date="24.09.2006">
    Assemble the head unit. You will now have a stereo jack sticking out in the
    back. Check the cassette door operation - it should activate the hidden
    switch when you push the door inward.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060924r.Testing.jpg" title="Testing" date="24.09.2006">
    Test the operation in the car. Push the cassette door in to hit the switch.
    The head unit will load the empty tray and activate the cassette input. You
    should hear the sound from your MP3 player connected to the stereo jack in
    the back.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060924s.Installation.jpg" title="Installation" date="24.09.2006">
    Connect the stereo cable and feed it through the centre console into the
    location of your choice. For instance, there's a gap under the left lower
    corner of the ashtray, just wide enough to pull the cable through.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060924t.In_action.jpg" title="In action" date="24.09.2006">
    The line input will be always on now, so you can simply switch from the
    CD or radio to "TAPE" and instantly have your MP3 music on. If you ever need
    to reset the deck (e.g. to play an actual cassette), just press "eject".
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
</picture-set>
