<?xml version="1.0"?>
<picture-set title="Saab 9-5: Line Input">

  <description>
  <p>Head unit modification on a 1999-2005 Saab 9-5 to add a line input for
  external media player connectivity.</p>

  <p><b>NOTE: parts of this guide are outdated, there are much better ways of adding a line input
  to a 9-5 nowadays, without the twin switch hack. Please search Saab forums for more recent
  solutions.</b> You can still use this as a general guide on taking the stereo apart.</p>

  <p>A digital music player is an attractive and convenient source of music in
  the car, but the
  stock head unit does not have a line input. Many people end up using an FM
  modulator or a cassette adapter, which inevitably sacrifices the sound
  quality. Not everyone agrees to this compromise, especally if you have
  a premium Harman Kardon stereo in your car, or a custom upgraded system.</p>

  <p>There are several alternative solutions for direct MP3 player connectivity.
  This guide shows how to do it
  yourself by using the tape deck inputs of the internal amplifier. It is
  a relatively easy and inexpensive way to add a direct line input to your
  stock head unit without sacrificing any existing functionality.</p>

  <p>Thanks to Daniel Giertz of Saabradio fame and all the Saab forum members who did the research and
  contributed to the installation guide.</p>
  </description>

  <picture name="20061126a.Stereo_removal.jpg" title="Stereo removal" date="26.11.2006">
    Remove the head unit from the car. If you don't have a stereo removal tool,
    use a set of knitting needles, or just four long nails. Stick them in and
    pull the stereo out.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20061126b.Mounting_case.jpg" title="Mounting case" date="26.11.2006">
    Press the sides of the mounting cage inward to release the latches and pull
    the cage out. Detaching the wiring harness from the back of the cage will
    make it easier to test the unit later.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20061126c.Head_unit.jpg" title="Head unit" date="26.11.2006">
    The face panel of the head unit is held by four Philips screws (two
    on each side) and hald a dozen plastic latches.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20061126d.Front_panel_removed.jpg" title="Front panel removed" date="26.11.2006">
    Unplug the front panel. The top cover of the CD player module is not
    necessary to remove, but it's easy to pop if you're curious what's inside.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20061126e.CD_player_screws.jpg" title="CD player screws" date="26.11.2006">
    The CD module is secured by three Philips screws.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20061126f.CD_cable.jpg" title="CD cable" date="26.11.2006">
    Before removing the CD module, unhook the ribbon cable from the main board.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20061126g.CD_module.jpg" title="CD module" date="26.11.2006">
    Lift the CD player module and store it away.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20061126h.Tape_module.jpg" title="Tape module" date="26.11.2006">
    Unscrew the tape player module (4 more screws). The little vertical
    board on the right side of the module is plugged into the main board.
    Unplug it with care.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20061126i.Head_board.jpg" title="Head board" date="26.11.2006">
    These two green jumpers lead to the stereo signals from the magnetic head.
    I haven't noticed any feedback or distortion with the circuit uninterrupted,
    but it's highly recommended to unsolder these jumpers to disconnect the
    tape signal amplifier or install a switch to alternate between the deck
    and the aux input.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20061126j.Stereo_signal.jpg" title="Stereo signal" date="26.11.2006">
    Connect the external stereo wires to the connector leading to the main
    board. Ground is pin #1, right channel (red) is pin #2, and left channel
    (white) is pin #3. Some head units (AS2 vs AS3) have a different board
    layout, but the pin-out of the connector is always the same.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20061126k.Tape_control_board.jpg" title="Tape control board" date="26.11.2006">
    The tape control board carries the signals from various tape sensors. The
    load switch ("LOADSW") in the top right is a switch that gets pushed when
    the cassette goes in. The front and rear reel signals ("FRS" and "RRS") are
    the rotation ticks from the tape spindles. And the "INT" signal initiates
    the head engagement.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20061126l.Signal_taps.jpg" title="Signal taps" date="26.11.2006">
    First, tap into the load switch line. Grounding it tells the deck to load
    the cassette tray. Shorting the front and rear reel signals will fool the
    control logic into thinking that both reels are spinning (the downside is
    that it will effectively disable the tape jam protection). Finally, solder
    a wire to the resistor leading to the "INT" pin.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20061126m.Switches.jpg" title="Switches" date="26.11.2006">
    You can opt for an external switch, but I chose to install these two for a
    completely stealthy setup. Note that the one on the right engages
    first, and the left one only clicks when the tape door is at the end
    of its travel. Both switches are normally open, closing them shorts
    to ground (find a local ground source on the face panel board).
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20061126n.Assembled.jpg" title="Assembled" date="26.11.2006">
    Connect the first switch to the "LOADSW" signal, and the second switch
    to the "INT" signal. If you're careful enough, you can even position the
    switches so they are not engaged when a regular cassette hits the door,
    to preserve the cassette playback functionality (sans the jam protection).
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20061126o.Testing.jpg" title="Testing" date="26.11.2006">
    Connect the MP3 player and turn the stereo on. Push the cassette door
    inward to hit the first switch. The stereo will switch to the tape mode.
    Usually, the deck will start right on and show "TAPE PLAY A>" (or "B"),
    playing the music from your MP3 player. If you only see "TAPE" on the
    SID, push the door further to press the second switch for a second or
    two, then release it. The deck will engage the playback and you'll see
    "TAPE PLAY A>".
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20061126p.Complete.jpg" title="Complete" date="26.11.2006">
    Re-install the CD player module and put the head unit back into the car.
    Route the auxillary cable to a convenient location of your choice. Enjoy
    the music. If you find the tape suddenly switching to "FAST FORWARD" after
    a few seconds of playback, disable the fast seek feature by pressing the
    middle of the "SEEK" button on the head unit.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20061126q.Cable.jpg" title="Cable" date="26.11.2006">
    I attached the stereo plug to one of the dashboard blanks.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20061126r.mobiBLU.jpg" title="mobiBLU" date="26.11.2006">
    The tiny <b>mobiBLU</b> player fits
    directly onto the stereo jack and looks right at home at this location.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
</picture-set>
