<?xml version="1.0"?>
<picture-set title="Saab NG900: Hydraulic Clutch Conversion">

  <description>
  <p>Hydraulic clutch conversion on a 1996 Saab 900. The troublesome cable
  clutch on a 1994-1997 Saab 900 can be relatively easily converted to
  hydraulic. In 1999, Saab issued a detailed upgrade document describing the
  conversion, but in essense it's just a direct swap to newer parts used in
  the NG900/9-3 family from 1998 on. You can get a conversion kit from online
  suppliers like <a href="http://www.genuinesaab.com">genuinesaab.com</a>,
  order the necessary parts from your Saab dealer, or just dig them up
  at the nearest scrap yard.</p>

  <p>You need a clutch pedal with a master cylinder, a clutch line to the
  gearbox, a brake fluid feed hose to the brake reservoir, and finally
  a slave cylinder that goes into the transmission replacing the old
  throwout bearing. The latter part requires a transmission removal,
  which is described in
  <a href="#/content/saab/20060121-saab-ng900-manual-transmission-removal">this section</a>.</p>

  <p>In my case, the parts came from a scrap yard, taken off a 1999 Saab 9-3.
  The slave cylinder installation is not covered here, since I was replacing
  the entire transmission, but it's fairly straightforward, and the slave
  bleeding procedure is described in the
  <a href="#/content/saab/20060211-saab-ng900-manual-transmission-installation">transmission installation section</a>.
  After everything is installed, the new clutch system needs to be
  flushed using a pressure bleeder.</p>
  
  <h2>Tools:</h2>
  <ul>
    <li>13 mm socket: cluth pedal nuts;</li>
    <li>13 mm wrench: upper nut on the clutch pedal;</li>
    <li>10 mm socket: lower dash cover, fuse box, coolant tank;</li>
    <li>Torx T25 screwdriver: lower dash cover, fuse panel;</li>
    <li>metal cutting tool: e.g. a rotary tool with a flexible extention
      or a 90 degrees attachment;</li>
    <li>drill with a 3 mm and 9 mm metal drilling bits.</li>
  </ul>
  </description>

  <picture name="20060122a0.Lower_dash.jpg" title="Lower dash" date="22.01.2006">
    Remove the lower dash cover - half a dozen Torx T25 screws and one 10 mm
    bolt.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060122a1.Fuses.jpg" title="Fuses" date="22.01.2006">
    Three more T25 screws to remove the fuse panel.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060122a2.Clutch_pedal.jpg" title="Clutch pedal" date="22.01.2006">
    Remove both lower and upper air vents to get a better access to the
    clutch pedal. Unplug the pedal position sensor.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060122a3.Upper_bolt.jpg" title="Upper bolt" date="22.01.2006">
    Slacken the upper nut on top of the clutch pedal: it's completely
    hidden from view, and you need a short wrench to get it moving.
    The nut to the right of it does not need to be unscrewed, but it might
    help to remove the pedal.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060122a4.Fuse_box.jpg" title="Fuse box" date="22.01.2006">
    Remove the plastic nut down below at the corner of the fuse box. Lift the
    rubber strip along the firewall and unhook the other corner. Lift the
    fuse box and move it aside as far as the wires allow.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060122a5.Clutch_cable.jpg" title="Clutch cable" date="22.01.2006">
    Undo two nuts holding the clutch pedal to the firewall. Inside the car,
    detach the clutch cable from the pedal, and remove the pedal completely.
    From the outside, pull the cable out of the firewall.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060122a6.Cable_and_pedal.jpg" title="Cable and pedal" date="22.01.2006">
    The clutch cable and old pedal on the floor.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060122a7.New_vs_old.jpg" title="New vs old" date="22.01.2006">
    The old clutch pedal is just a lever on a mounting bracket.
    The new one incorporates a hydraulic master cylinder.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060122a8.New_vs_old.jpg" title="New vs old" date="22.01.2006">
    The master cylinder goes through the firewall in a location different
    from the cable.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060122a9.New_vs_old.jpg" title="New vs old" date="22.01.2006">
    One of the mounting bolts for the new pedal is also in a different spot.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060122b0.Drilling_template.jpg" title="Drilling template" date="22.01.2006">
    This is a drilling template from the Saab manual. The upper circle is
    17 mm, while the lower is 35 mm. The mounting hole in the right is 9 mm.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060122b1.Two_templates.jpg" title="Two templates" date="22.01.2006">
    I made a second copy of the template to get a clear picture of the
    cut-out usage.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060122b2.Sticky_tape.jpg" title="Sticky tape" date="22.01.2006">
    The round holes are to be combined into an oval. The double-sided sticky
    tape will be used to attach the template to the firewall.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060122b3.Applied.jpg" title="Applied" date="22.01.2006">
    Attach the template making sure it fits the existing holes. Mark the
    outside shape and peel it off.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060122b4.Rubber_cut.jpg" title="Rubber cut" date="22.01.2006">
    Cut and remove the rubber insulation on the firewall.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060122b5.Marking_a_hole.jpg" title="Marking a hole" date="22.01.2006">
    Now that you've reached the metal, apply the template again and mark the oval
    and the mounting hole.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060122b6.Cutter.jpg" title="Cutter" date="22.01.2006">
    Get a suitable metal cutter. A sheet metal nipper, or a rotary tool with a flexible extention (or
    a 90 degree adapter) should work fine. Eye protection is a must.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060122b7.Hole.jpg" title="Hole" date="22.01.2006">
    Half a dozen cutting discs later, and the oval is finished. The mounting
    hole in the right is easy -- just start it with a thin drill bit
    (e.g. 3 mm), and then do a second pass with a 9 mm.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060122b8.Primed.jpg" title="Primed" date="22.01.2006">
    Sand and prime the cut-out to protect it from rust. Do the same
    on the outer side of the firewall.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060122b9.Painted.jpg" title="Painted" date="22.01.2006">
    Paint the surface. One of the old mounting holes is not needed anymore,
    plug it with a short bolt and tighten the nut on the other side. Plug
    the old cable hole too.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060122c0.New_pedal.jpg" title="New pedal" date="22.01.2006">
    When fitting the new pedal, place a 2 mm washer under the bolt that goes
    into the newly drilled mounting hole. Fit the upper mounting bracket
    and tighten the nuts.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060122c1.Master_cylinder.jpg" title="Master cylinder" date="22.01.2006">
    Tighten the nuts on the outside of the firewall.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060122c2.Brake_reservoir.jpg" title="Brake reservoir" date="22.01.2006">
    Cut the end of the downward pointing nipple on the brake reservoir,
    about 3 mm should be enough. Catch the brake fluid that will leak out.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060122c4.Hose.jpg" title="Hose" date="22.01.2006">
    Attach a hose to the nipple and clamp it tight.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060122c5.Hose.jpg" title="Hose" date="22.01.2006">
    Attach the other end of the hose to the upper socket on the
    master cylinder. Clamp it as well.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060122c6.Sensor.jpg" title="Sensor" date="22.01.2006">
    Fit the air vents and attach the clutch pedal position sensor.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060122c7.Fuses.jpg" title="Fuses" date="22.01.2006">
    Install the fuse panel.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060122c8.Lower_dash.jpg" title="Lower dash" date="22.01.2006">
    Put the lower dash cover back on. It's amusing how much the new
    pedal stands out.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060122c9.Coolant_tank.jpg" title="Coolant tank" date="22.01.2006">
    Remove the nut holding the coolant expansion tank. Lift the tank.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060122d0.Hole.jpg" title="Hole" date="22.01.2006">
    Drill a hole on the edge of the side member for a clamp that will hold the
    clutch line.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060122d1.Clutch_line.jpg" title="Clutch line" date="22.01.2006">
    A new clutch line. The rubber section is there to accomodate the engine
    movement. The 90 degree bend on the right is where the line will be clamped.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060122d2.Clamp.jpg" title="Clamp" date="22.01.2006">
    Route the clutch line between the fender and the ABS unit bracket
    and secure it with a clamp.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060122d3.Master.jpg" title="Master" date="22.01.2006">
    Plug the end of the clutch line into the master cylinder and insert
    the locking clip.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060122d4.Clutch_line.jpg" title="Clutch line" date="22.01.2006">
    The other end of the clutch line will be attached to the slave cylinder
    once the transmission is installed.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
</picture-set>
