<?xml version="1.0"?>
<picture-set title="Saab NG900/9-3: Garrett T25 Turbo Rebuild">

  <description>
  <p>This Garrett T25 turbo is found on 1991-1998 Saab 9000, 1994-1998 Saab 900
  and 1999 Saab 9-3. There are certain differences between the models, but the
  cores are almost identical, so you might find this useful even if your unit
  is somehow different from those pictured. The goal here was to rebuild
  a turbocharger using new seals and bearings from a service kit.</p>

  <b>Tools and supplies:</b>
  <ul>
    <li>14 mm six-point socket (turbine end nut);</li>
    <li>13 mm spanner wrench (exhaust housing bolts);</li>
    <li>10 mm wrench (wastegate actuator);</li>
    <li>8 mm twelve-point socket, did without it (compressor wheel nut);</li>
    <li>Torx T15 screwdriver (thrust bearing);</li>
    <li>small torque wrench with an inch-lbs scale;</li>
    <li>large and small snap ring pliers;</li>
    <li>gear puller;</li>
    <li>engine oil;</li>
    <li>degreaser and cleaning supplies.</li>
  </ul>
  </description>

  <picture name="200510090.Two_turbos.jpg" title="Two turbos" date="09.10.2005">
    These are the two turbos I'm going to use. One has damaged wheels and
    incredibly worn seals, while another has a cracked exhaust housing but
    good internals. I'm hoping to combine them into one working unit.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="200510091.Donor_No_1.jpg" title="Donor No 1" date="09.10.2005">
    A close-up of one of the turbos. This one came from a 1999 9-3. The
    wastegate actuator has been removed earlier.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="200510092.Bolts.jpg" title="Bolts" date="09.10.2005">
    Undo the bolts on the exhaust housing using a 13 mm spanner. The bolts
    are conveniently located so they can be used to press the housing off
    the turbo.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="200510093.Exhaust_housing.jpg" title="Exhaust housing" date="09.10.2005">
    When using the bolts to force the housing off, do it very carefully, half
    a turn at a time. Make sure it is coming off evenly and not jamming the
    turbine wheel.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="200510094.Snap_ring.jpg" title="Snap ring" date="09.10.2005">
    The compressor housing is secured with a big snap ring, you need large
    pliers for that.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="200510095.Compressor_housing.jpg" title="Compressor housing" date="09.10.2005">
    The snap ring takes a few moments to wrestle, and then you can remove
    the compressor housing... carefully.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="200510096.Shaft_play.jpg" title="Shaft play" date="09.10.2005">
    This shot illustrates the enormous amount of shaft play on one of the
    turbos. The thrust bearing was completely destroyed, so the turbine ate
    into the backing plate and ground itself down over 2 mm.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="200510097.Nut.jpg" title="Nut" date="09.10.2005">
    Grab the shaft nut with vise-grips and use a six-point 14 mm wrench on
    the turbine end to undo the nut. Remember, the nut has a LEFT HAND thread.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="200510098.Gear_puller.jpg" title="Gear puller" date="09.10.2005">
    The compressor wheel might just come off, but most likely you'll have to
    use a gear puller to press it off.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="200510099.Wheels_removed.jpg" title="Wheels removed" date="09.10.2005">
    Before pulling the wheels off, even before touching the nut on the shaft,
    mark the position of the wheels relative to each other. You'll have to
    assemble them in the exact same position later to preserve the balance.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20051009a.Sealplate.jpg" title="Sealplate" date="09.10.2005">
    The sealplate is held by another snap ring, and there's a rubber ring
    underneath.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20051009b.Thrust_bearing.jpg" title="Thrust bearing" date="09.10.2005">
    The thrust bearing is held by three Torx T15 screws. The thrust collar is
    the part mainly responsible for shaft play.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20051009c.Snap_ring.jpg" title="Snap ring" date="09.10.2005">
    The journal bearings are held in place by small snap rings. You can remove
    them with tiny needle-nose pliers or just a sharp pick.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20051009d.Journal_bearings.jpg" title="Journal bearings" date="09.10.2005">
    The intake side journal bearing has only one snap ring inside the turbo
    (the outer side is propped by the thrust bearing), while the exhaust side
    bearing has two snap rings.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20051009e.Cleaning.jpg" title="Cleaning" date="09.10.2005">
    Time to clean all the grime and oil from the turbo. Check for sludge in the
    oil passages. Keep all parts free from contaminants from now on.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20051009f.Wheels.jpg" title="Wheels" date="09.10.2005">
    Clean the wheels. Make sure you did not wipe your position marks if
    you used a marker or paint. Remove the old seal ring from the turbine.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20051009g.The_kit.jpg" title="The kit" date="09.10.2005">
    A typical T25 service kit from eBay
    would contain a full set of new bearings, seals, snap rings and fasteners.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20051009h.Journal_bearings.jpg" title="Journal bearings" date="09.10.2005">
    Prepare journal bearings and snap rings. Some kits come with bearings in
    two sizes to suit different trims of the turbo, so pick the right size.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20051009i.Snap_rings.jpg" title="Snap rings" date="09.10.2005">
    Install the inner snap rings on both sides of the central oil passage.
    Make sure they fully fit into their grooves.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20051009j.Turbine_side.jpg" title="Turbine side" date="09.10.2005">
    Dip one of the journal bearings in engine oil and insert it on the
    exhaust side of the turbo. Fit the outer snap ring.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20051009k.Compressor_side.jpg" title="Compressor side" date="09.10.2005">
    Turn the turbo around, dip the second journal bearing in oil and slide
    it in place.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20051009l.Thrust_bearing.jpg" title="Thrust bearing" date="09.10.2005">
    Fit the seal ring on the thrust collar, dip the parts in oil and screw
    on the thrust bearing.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20051009m.Sealplate.jpg" title="Sealplate" date="09.10.2005">
    Install a fresh rubber ring under the sealplate, press the sealplate in
    and secure it with a snap ring.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20051009n.Turbine.jpg" title="Turbine" date="09.10.2005">
    Prepare the seals that go on the turbine end of the shaft.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20051009o.Turbine_seals.jpg" title="Turbine seals" date="09.10.2005">
    The middle retaining ring was completely missing on both turbos. Its
    groove was filled flush with cooked oil, so I had to dig through it.
    The installation of the shaft is a bit awkward since you have the back
    cover plate blocking the view, but sooner or later it snaps in. Just don't
    force it too much.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20051009p.Compressor_wheel.jpg" title="Compressor wheel" date="09.10.2005">
    Slide the compressor wheel on and line up the marks carefully to restore
    the balance. Put on the nut. The torque varies from 20 to 40 in-lbs in
    various sources, plus extra 90-120 degrees. Ideally, you need a small
    12-pt socket for the nut, I just clamped it between two wooden blocks and
    used a torque wrench on the turbine end.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20051009q.Compressor_housing.jpg" title="Compressor housing" date="09.10.2005">
    Fit new rubber ring, put the housing on, and secure that huge snap ring.
    Check the orientation: if you hold the housing so that the intake is facing down, the part
    number plate on the cartridge body (or the stud that's left of it) should
    be facing up.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20051009r.Exhaust_housing.jpg" title="Exhaust housing" date="09.10.2005">
    Fit the exhaust housing, new brackets and tighten the bolts. As usual, make
    sure the turbine spins free.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20051009s.Wastegate_actuator.jpg" title="Wastegate actuator" date="09.10.2005">
    The wastegate actuator has been
    <a href="#/content/saab/20051003-saab-ng900-wastegate-actuator-spring">rebuilt
    and prepared earler</a>, with an upgraded spring from Nordic.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20051009t.Finished.jpg" title="Finished" date="09.10.2005">
    Bolt the actuator to the housing and screw on the arm so it slides
    onto the wastegate arm in the closed position. Shorten the rod an extra 2-3
    turns to obtain a pre-load of 2-3 mm, and tighten the lock nut.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
</picture-set>
