<?xml version="1.0"?>
<picture-set title="Saab NG900/9-3/9-5: Rear Pads and Rotors (Fixed Calipers)">

  <description>
  <p>Rear brake pad and rotor replacement on a 1999 Saab 9-5. The car has the
  early style fixed rear calipers, so this guide will also apply to
  NG900 and 9-3's.</p>

  <h2>Tools:</h2>
  <ul>
    <li>18 mm socket: caliper bolts;</li>
    <li>17 mm socket: wheel bolts;</li>
    <li>10 mm wrench: handbrake cable bracket (9-5 only);</li>
    <li>Torx T30 socket: rotor index screws;</li>
    <li>thin punch and a hammer;</li>
    <li>long socket extensions;</li>
    <li>long flat screwdriver;</li>
    <li>impact driver;</li>
    <li>drill and screw extractor (optional);</li>
    <li>wire brush;</li>
    <li>torque wrench;</li>
    <li>car jacks and stands.</li>
  </ul>
  </description>

  <picture name="20050709a.Wheel_off.jpg" title="Wheel off" date="09.07.2005">
    Raise the rear end of the car, secure it on jack stands and take the wheels
    off (17 mm socket). My cars always manage to turn up dirty just the day
    before I plan to do some work on them. They look much cleaner normally ;).
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050709b.Bracket.jpg" title="Bracket" date="09.07.2005">
    On the 9-5, undo the 10 mm bolt holding the handbrake/brake line bracket
    to the suspension arm. On the NG900/9-3 the brake line is attached with
    plastic clips.
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050709c.Punching_out.jpg" title="Punching out" date="09.07.2005">
    Hammer out the pins on the back of the caliper. A thin punch works well.
    It's amusing that all you need to change the rear pads on a Saab is a hammer.
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050709d.Pins_and_pads.jpg" title="Pins and pads" date="09.07.2005">
    Remove the pins, the spring and the brake pads.
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050709e.Drill.jpg" title="Drill" date="09.07.2005">
    With 160K on the car and the rotors being original, the chances that the
    index screw will come out without a fight are very slim. The screw on
    the right side had to be drilled out. Stock up on spare screws before
    you start this job.
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050709f.Screw_extractor.jpg" title="Screw extractor" date="09.07.2005">
    The screw extractor quickly finishes the job. After the
    <A HREF="#/content/saab/20050423-saab-ng900-exhaust-manifold">exhaust manifold</A>
    job this felt like a piece of cake.
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050709g.Impact_driver.jpg" title="Impact driver" date="09.07.2005">
    The screw on the left side came out with a help of an impact driver,
    no drilling was required. The original screws take a Torx T30 socket.
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050709h.Caliper_bolts.jpg" title="Caliper bolts" date="09.07.2005">
    Undo the caliper bolts. The clearance on the 9-5 is quite tight, there's
    barely enough room for a short 18 mm socket and a flat ratchet handle.
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050709i.Rotor.jpg" title="Rotor" date="09.07.2005">
    Support the caliper so it won't be hanging on the brake line. With the
    caliper out of the way, the rotor comes off (if you're lucky ;).
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050709j.Handbrake.jpg" title="Handbrake" date="09.07.2005">
    Take your time to study the handbrake adjuster. On the right side of the
    car, the star-shaped wheel has to be turned downward to tighten the
    handbrake. Upward on the left side.
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050709k.Old_and_new.jpg" title="Old and new" date="09.07.2005">
    My shiny new Brembo rotors. They came with
    two index screws included.
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050709l.Old_and_new.jpg" title="Old and new" date="09.07.2005">
    The minimum thickness for the rotors is 8 mm. The new ones measure at 10 mm.
    The old ones were only worn down to 9 mm, but they had deep grooves and
    a lot of rust.
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050709m.New_rotor.jpg" title="New rotor" date="09.07.2005">
    Install the rotor, apply some anti-seize to the mating surfaces and the
    index screw. Do not tighten the screw too much, it's just there to position
    the rotor. Tighten the caliper bolts to 59 ft-lbs, put some loctite on
    the thread. Attach the brake line bracket to the suspension arm.
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050709n.Handbrake_adjustment.jpg" title="Handbrake adjustment" date="09.07.2005">
    Now is the good time to adjust the handbrake. Release the brake lever and
    use a flat screwdriver to spin the adjuster wheel until the shoes grab. Then
    unwind the adjuster so the rotor just starts spinning freely. Repeat on the
    other side. If done correcly, the lever should be tight at 3-4 clicks now.
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050709o.New_pads.jpg" title="New pads" date="09.07.2005">
    Pull the new pads out of the box. Apply the lubricant to the back side and inside pin holes, then
    insert them into the caliper. Inspect the pins and the springs, use a new
    set if the old ones became rusty and fragile.
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050709p.Installed.jpg" title="Installed" date="09.07.2005">
    Hammer the pins back in, the spring goes in after the first pin is inserted.
    Install the wheels (81 ft-lbs) and lower the car to the ground.
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
</picture-set>
