<?xml version="1.0"?>
<picture-set title="Saab NG900/9-3: Engine Mounts">

  <description>
  <p>Engine mount replacement on the 1996 Saab 900 (applies to all 1994-1998 900 and 1999-2002 9-3).</p>

  <p> The old mounts were severily
  worn and broken, which caused excessive engine movement and shifting
  difficulty at high boost. To firm things up further, the transmission
  mount has been upgraded with a sport polyurethane mount from
  <a href="https://www.genuinesaab.com/">Taliaferro</a>.</p>

  <h2>Tools:</h2>
  <ul>
    <li>17 mm socket (rear mount);</li>
    <li>16 mm socket (rear and transmission mounts);</li>
    <li>15 mm socket (side mounts);</li>
    <li>13 mm socket (gearshift linkage);</li>
    <li>10 mm socket (throttle body inlet, plastic shields);</li>
    <li>8 mm socket (plastic shields);</li>
    <li>8 mm Allen socket (passenger side mount);</li>
    <li>two L-shaped 3 mm Allen keys;</li>
    <li>long socket extension;</li>
    <li>ratchet handle;</li>
    <li>torque wrench;</li>
    <li>flat screwdriver (throttle body clamps);</li>
    <li>hydraulic jacks and stands.</li>
  </ul>
  </description>

  <picture name="20050816a.Shields_down.jpg" title="Shields down" date="16.08.2005">
    Raise the front end of the car and remove the lower shields under the
    bumper. The wheels are turned to the right to get an access to the
    serpentine belt cover.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050816b.Jack.jpg" title="Jack" date="16.08.2005">
    Support the transmission with a jack (the differential case looks like
    a good jacking point). Don't raise it too high, just make
    sure it takes the weight off the transmission mount.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050816c.Transmission_mount.jpg" title="Transmission mount" date="16.08.2005">
    Locate the transmission mount under the left fender. Slacken the 15 mm
    bolts that secure it to the car body and make sure the jack supports
    the engine/transmission properly.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050816d.Transmission_mount.jpg" title="Transmission mount" date="16.08.2005">
    Remove the bolts attaching the mount to the car body. Unbolt the mount
    from the angle bracket on the transmission (16 mm socket). Remove the mount
    from the car.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050816f.New_vs_old.jpg" title="New vs old" date="16.08.2005">
    The old mount is cracked. Its bracket it so thin I can bend it with my bare
    hands. You can see how much stronger the sport mount is. It has a thick
    metal frame that doesn't allow any flex.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050816e.New_vs_old.jpg" title="New vs old" date="16.08.2005">
    The Taliaferro mount is completely filled with polyurethane, while the
    stock mount has three relatively soft rubber sections. The old rubber
    spacer is no longer needed, you can discard it.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050816g.Transmission_mount.jpg" title="Transmission mount" date="16.08.2005">
    Attach the mount to the bracket, then put in the bolts attaching it to the
    side member. You might need to raise or lower the jack to make it fit. Tighten
    the bracket bolts to 29 ft-lbs.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050816h.Transmission_mount.jpg" title="Transmission mount" date="16.08.2005">
    Tighten the remaining two bolts to 54 ft-lbs. It's a pity such a beautiful
    piece of hardware remains hidden from view.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050816i.Engine_mount.jpg" title="Engine mount" date="16.08.2005">
    The passenger side engine mount is located under the right fender. Support
    the oil pan with a jack and loosen the 15 mm bolts holding the mount
    to the car body.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050816j.Engine_mount.jpg" title="Engine mount" date="16.08.2005">
    There's only one bolt going to the engine bracket, but if the mount is worn
    and sagging, there's a chance the bolt head won't match the hole anymore,
    so you'll have to play with your jack height and hunt inside the mount with a long 8 mm Allen key.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050816k.Old_vs_new.jpg" title="Old vs new" date="16.08.2005">
    All bolts are out, and the mount is removed from the car. You can
    immediately see how deformed it is compared to the new mount. The engine
    sat so low the oil pan was touching the subframe every time the engine
    moved.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050816l.Old_vs_new.jpg" title="Old vs new" date="16.08.2005">
    This shows how the bolt does not match the hole anymore. You can force it
    through, but with a limited clearance under the fender it is not a easy
    task. In fact, with a bit of load placed on the mount, the bolt
    hides from view completely.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050816m.New_engine_mount.jpg" title="New engine mount" date="16.08.2005">
    The torque values for this mount are the same: 29 ft-lbs for the bolt in
    the centre, and 54 ft-lbs for the bolts going to the side member.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050816n.Lower_rear_nuts.jpg" title="Lower rear nuts" date="16.08.2005">
    There are two nuts attaching the rear mount to the subframe from below.
    On my car one of the nuts was 16 mm and another 17 mm. I'm not sure if
    this is always the case, so be prepared.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050816o.Rear_mount_nut.jpg" title="Rear mount nut" date="16.08.2005">
    The third nut attaches the top of the rear mount to the engine bracket.
    You can reach it using a long extention with a U-joint. Removing the throttle
    body inlet pipe just gives you enough room to work. You can see that I took
    this opportunity to clean the throttle body and the IAC valve.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050816p.Rear_mount_nut.jpg" title="Rear mount nut" date="16.08.2005">
    The nut itself is 16 mm. Unfortunately, there's very little room to get to
    it and apply proper leverage, that's why a long extention works better.
    I've also disconnected the gearshift rod from the linkage to get more
    freedom in lifting the engine. If you do that, don't forget to
    <a href="#/content/saab/20050325-saab-ng900-shifter-alignment">align it</a>
    afterwards.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050816q.Jacks.jpg" title="Jacks" date="16.08.2005">
    The engine is now supported with two jacks: under the oil pan and the
    differential. This allows to lift it as much as possible to create enough
    room to remove the mount. When lifting the engine, be careful not to jam
    or break any hoses or other parts. Alternatively, use the engine support bar.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050816r.New_rear_mount.jpg" title="Rear mount" date="16.08.2005">
    Even with the engine tilted to the max, there's barely enough room to
    wrestle the mount in or out. The Saab Manual actually orders you to lower the
    entire subframe instead. For some silly reason it also calls for removing
    the wheels for the side mounts.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050816s.New_vs_old.jpg" title="New vs old" date="16.08.2005">
    This mount was in the worst shape of all -- it was torn completely, and the
    hydraulic fluid apparently leaked long time ago.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050816t.New_vs_old.jpg" title="New vs old" date="16.08.2005">
    The big washer goes on top of the mount with the cut-out facing the rear
    of the car. Put the new mount in, remove the suporting jacks and torque
    all three nuts to 29 ft-lbs. Done!
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
</picture-set>
