<?xml version="1.0"?>
<picture-set title="Saab NG900/9-3: Six-point Subframe Brace">

  <description>
  <p><a href="http://www.genuinesaab.com">Taliaferro</a> six-point front subframe
  brace installation on a 1995 Saab 900. The subframe improves car's handling
  and does a great job in reducing the cowl shake on the convertibles. It fits
  all 1994-1998 900 and 1999-2002 9-3 models.</p>
  
  <h2>Tools:</h2>
  <ul>
    <li>14 mm socket: brace bolts;</li>
    <li>14 mm wrench: threadless nut for rivet compression;</li>
    <li>torque wrench;</li>
    <li>car jack and stands or ramps.</li>
  </ul>
  </description>

  <picture name="20060715a.The_kit.jpg" title="The kit" date="15.07.2006">
    The kit contains the brace itself, installation hardware and new bolts.
    The short strip with a single nut is a spare part to use as an alternative
    to the driver's side rivet (see below).
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060715b.Guides.jpg" title="Guides" date="15.07.2006">
    The long guides with two nuts welded on slide inside the subframe,
    through the control arm bolt window. Align them so both nuts match
    the oval holes in the subframe.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060715c.Rivet_tool.jpg" title="Rivet tool" date="15.07.2006">
    The rivets are supplied to provide the rear mounting points. The round rivet
    goes into the round hole in the rear left corner of the subframe, and the
    tapered one goes into the square hole on the right side. You might need
    a hammer to fit it in. The odd nut and a bolt with washers are only needed
    to install the rivets into the subframe, and are not used for the brace
    itself.
    <image width="734" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060715d.Inserted.jpg" title="Inserted" date="15.07.2006">
    Assemble one rivet as shown, put some grease between the washers. Insert it
    into the subframe and start tightening the bolt while holding the white
    threadless nut with a spanner. The nut will bite into the rivet and prevent
    it from spinning, so the bolt will start deforming the soft rivet as it's
    tightened further. Eventually the rivet will become tightly seated in its
    hole. Remove the bolt and proceed with the second rivet.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060715e.Brace.jpg" title="Brace" date="15.07.2006">
    Fit the brace and tighten the bolts to 30 ft-lbs.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060715f.Shields.jpg" title="Shields" date="15.07.2006">
    The protective plastic shields fit with minimal modifications.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
</picture-set>
