<?xml version="1.0"?>
<picture-set title="Saab NG900/9-3: Front Suspension">

  <description>
  <p>A front suspension upgrade performed on a 1996 Saab 900SE turbo.</p>

  <p>The goal was to replace the old and worn components with new part. The
  pictures show the work done at the right front corner.
  Parts from <a href="https://www.genuinesaab.com">Taliaferro Imports</a>,
  <a href="https://wwws.shox.com">shox.com</a> eBay. See also
  <a href="#/content/saab/20050215-saab-ng900-rear-suspension">the rear suspension
  installation</a>.</p>

  <p>The job took me several days, as you can see from the dates on the
  photos. Unfortunately, I was short on spare time and could only spend
  a couple of hours a day in the evening. With all the tools at hand, proper
  preparations, and without the unexpected interruptions, the work can be done
  in one day. A helping hand would speed things up as well.</p>

  <b>Tools and supplies:</b>
  <ul>
    <li>32 mm (1.25;") socket: hub centre nut;</li>
    <li>24 mm wrench: retainer nut on top of the strut, new outer bushing bolt;</li>
    <li>18 mm socket: tie rod nut;</li>
    <li>18 mm wrench: ball joint nut;</li>
    <li>17 mm socket: wheel bolts;</li>
    <li>16 mm socket: stanchion arm to subframe bolt;</li>
    <li>15 mm socket: control arm to subframe bolt;</li>
    <li>13 mm socket: lower sway bar link nut, strut mount nuts;</li>
    <li>11 mm socket: top of the original damper rod;</li>
    <li>11 mm open wrench: upper part of sway bar link;</li>
    <li>10 mm socket: belt shield screws;</li>
    <li>10 mm Allen key: caliper bolts;</li>
    <li>8 mm socket: belt shield screws;</li>
    <li>7 mm Allen key: top of the Bilstein damper rod;</li>
    <li>5 mm Allen key: ABS sensor screws, rotor index screw;</li>
    <li>Torx T55 key: original stanchion arm to control arm bolt;</li>
    <li>torque wrench;</li>
    <li>pipe wrench (60 mm): strut insert sleeve nut;</li>
    <li>car jack and axle stands;</li>
    <li>ball joint separator or large Pitman gear puller;</li>
    <li>spring compressor;</li>
    <li>C-clamp: for tightening tie rod ends;</li>
    <li>breaker bar;</li>
    <li>vice-grips;</li>
    <li>large screw extractor (6 mm);</li>
    <li>hammer and rubber mallet;</li>
    <li>loctite, anti-seize, silicone/moly chassis grease, rust solvent.</li>
  </ul>
  </description>

  <picture name="20050210a.Centre_cap.jpg" title="Centre cap" date="10.02.2005">
    With the car still on the ground, remove the centre cap from the wheel
    and spray the axle nut with a lubricant.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050210b.Hub_centre_nut.jpg" title="Axle nut" date="10.02.2005">
    Here's a close-up of the axle hut. It might be a good idea to clean the
    thread with a wire brush too.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050210c.Centre_nut.jpg" title="Axle nut" date="10.02.2005">
    Loosen the nut using a 32 mm socket (a 1.25" will do too) and a
    breaker bar.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050210d.Wheel_nuts.jpg" title="Wheel nuts" date="10.02.2005">
    Loosen the wheel bolts too (you'll need a deep 17 mm socket for that).
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050210e.Jacks.jpg" title="Jacks" date="10.02.2005">
    Raise the car, put it on jack stands and take off the wheels. The car is
    filthy: this is what Ontario roads do to your car in winter. I washed it
    just a couple of days ago.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050210f.Centre_nut.jpg" title="Axle nut" date="10.02.2005">
    Remove the axle nut. Take your time spraying all other fasteners with
    your favourite rust solvent.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050210g.Tie_rod_end.jpg" title="Tie rod end" date="10.02.2005">
    Undo the tie rod end nut using an 18 mm socket. Remove the nut completely,
    clean and lubricate the thread, and put the nut back on a few turns to
    provide a base for the next step.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050210h.Gear_puller.jpg" title="Gear puller" date="10.02.2005">
    Use a ball joint separator or gear puller to push out the tie rod end.
    If you didn't fully remove
    the nut prior to that, and it gets stuck, there won't be enough friction
    to turn the nut anymore, it will just spin in the ball joint.
    Guess how I know that ;)
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050210i.Clamp.jpg" title="Clamp" date="10.02.2005">
    If you were unfortunate enough to make this mistake, clamp the tie rod
    end to the strut and undo the stuck nut. You will also need to use the
    clamp when assembling the thing later.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050210j.Sway_bar_link.jpg" title="Sway bar link" date="10.02.2005">
    Disconnect the sway bar link from the control arm. Use a 13 mm socket on
    the nut below, and hold the top with a 11 mm open wrench. The left side
    link on my car snapped when I tried to undo the nut (too much rust).
    A new one was $50 at the dealer.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050210k.ABS_sensor.jpg" title="ABS sensor" date="10.02.2005">
    An engineer who decided to use tiny bolts with a 5 mm Allen head for ABS
    sensors should be prosecuted. With this much rust, the head instantly
    rounds off when you first attempt to unbolt it, and then snaps
    completely when you try to finish the job with vice-grips. To avoid that,
    undo the bolt that holds the sensor bracket instead: it's also a 5 mm Allen,
    but its thread is not exposed to moisture.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050211.The_car.jpg" title="The car" date="11.02.2005">
    This is the car sitting in the garage. Luckily, I didn't have to hurry
    with finishing the work this time as we had the 9-5 to drive around.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050212a.Belt_shield.jpg" title="Belt shield" date="12.02.2005">
    The plastic belt shield has to be removed in order to gain the access
    to the inner control arm bolt. It is held by assorted screws with 8 mm and
    10 mm hex heads.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050212b.Rotor_screw.jpg" title="Rotor screw" date="12.02.2005">
    The brake rotor index screw also has a 5 mm Allen head. Translation
    from Rusty Saab: "with this much surface area, the bolt head will round off
    in no time, so you will need a drill, a screw extractor, and a new $4 bolt
    from the dealer."
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050212c.Caliper_bolts.jpg" title="Caliper bolts" date="12.02.2005">
    The caliper bolts take a 10 mm Allen key. Finally, a hex key big enough
    not to strip the head.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050212d.Caliper.jpg" title="Caliper" date="12.02.2005">
    Compress the caliper so it becomes free from the rotor, pull it away
    and hang on a piece of wire to keep the brake line free from the caliper's
    heavy weight.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050212e.Control_arm.jpg" title="Control arm" date="12.02.2005">
    The control arm bolt is accessible in the opening from below the
    subframe (15 mm socket). I decided to take this route to skip the fight
    with the ball joint on the car.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050212i.Stanchion_arm.jpg" title="Stanchion arm" date="12.02.2005">
    The stanchion arm is bolted to the subframe from below (16 mm socket).
    You don't really need to remove it completely, but I wanted to inspect the
    bushing, and it's also easier to remove the old push nut when the arm is
    off the car.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050212f.Driveshaft.jpg" title="Driveshaft" date="12.02.2005">
    With the control arm disconnected from the subframe, there's enough play
    to pull the driveshaft out of the hub. Once the driveshaft is out
    of the way, you can unbolt the stanchion arm from the outer bushing
    (Torx T55).
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050212g.Stanchion_arm.jpg" title="Stanchion arm" date="12.02.2005">
    Move the stanchion arm away. The strut is now hanging on the upper
    mount.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050212h.Strut_mount.jpg" title="Strut mount" date="12.02.2005">
    Carefully undo the strut mount nuts (13 mm socket) and remove the strut
    assembly from the car.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050212j.Stanchion_arm.jpg" title="Stanchion arm" date="12.02.2005">
    The stanchion arm on the ground. Now you have removed everything there is
    to remove ;).
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050212k.Strut_assembly.jpg" title="Strut assembly" date="12.02.2005">
    With the strut assembly on the floor, it's easy to unbolt
    and separate the ball joint. First, undo the nut (18 mm).
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050212l.Ball_joint.jpg" title="Ball joint" date="12.02.2005">
    Then use a gear puller or a screw-type ball joint separator to break the
    bond. The use of fork-type ball joint splitters is not recommended as they
    often damage the rubber boot.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050212m.Top_nut.jpg" title="Top nut" date="12.02.2005">
    Loosen the retainer nut on top of the strut. You will need a 24 mm
    wrench for the nut and a 11 mm socket to hold the damper rod. Another
    alternative is to use an impact wrench to loosen the nut (the former
    method does not work on 9-3s as they have deeper strut mounts, so
    the nut is harder to reach).
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050212n.Spring_compressor.jpg" title="Spring compressor" date="12.02.2005">
    Do not
    remove the nut completely: the spring is under load, and releasing it
    can cause an injury.
    Attach a spring compressor tool and tighten it until the spring becomes loose
    in the housing. Remove the top nut, the strut mount and other parts,
    then carefully release the tension of the spring.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050212o.Disassembled.jpg" title="Disassembled" date="12.02.2005">
    Clockwise: top nut (do not reuse it!), washer, strut mount, thrust
    bearing, another washer, spring support, bump stop, strut with damper,
    spring. Remember how the washers were fitted: the edges on the top washer
    should point up, while on the bottom washer they should point        down.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050212p.Strut_insert.jpg" title="Strut insert" date="12.02.2005">
    The strut insert is secured by a 60 mm sleeve nut. I didn't have anything big
    enough, so I took it to the nearest mechanic. They put it in a vice and
    used the biggest pipe wrench I've ever seen. Two minutes, and the job was
    done, didn't even take the money.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050212q.Push_nut.jpg" title="Push nut" date="12.02.2005">
    The old push nut in the stanchion arm is no longer needed if you're
    installing the bushings from Taliaferro, which come with a bigger bolt. A few blows with a
    heavy hammer will do the job.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050212r.Inner_bushing.jpg" title="Inner bushing" date="12.02.2005">
    The inner control arm bushing is a simple rubber piece with a metal insert,
    so you can easily press it out with a gear puller.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050212s.Outer_bushing.jpg" title="Outer bushing" date="12.02.2005">
    The outer bushing can also be pressed out, just use a larger gear puller.
    This bushing is of a hydraulic type, so bring a pan to catch the oil.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050212t.Sleeve.jpg" title="Sleeve" date="12.02.2005">
    The metal sleeve of the outer bushing can be pressed out if you have a press.
    If you don't, you can saw cut the sleeve and remove it with a chisel.
    This will destroy it though, but who cares, we have a box full of
    nice new poly bushings ;)
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050213a.Bushings.jpg" title="Bushings" date="13.02.2005">
    The new bushings are a two piece design with a metal insert in the middle.
    Prepare some silicone/moly grease to lubricate them.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050213b.Bushings.jpg" title="Bushings" date="13.02.2005">
    The bushings are very snug, but you don't need a press to put them in.
    Most of the job can be done with your bare hands with a little help
    from a rubber mallet.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050213c.Arms.jpg" title="Arms" date="13.02.2005">
    Put the control and stanchion arms back on, but don't tighten the bolts
    yet. Move the driveshaft out of the way and connect the arms at the
    outer bushing.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050213d.New_bolt.jpg" title="New bolt" date="13.02.2005">
    Insert the new bolt that comes with the bushings and tighten it to 120
    ft-lbs using a pair of 24 mm wrenches. After that tighten the bolts that
    attach the arms to the subframe. Control arm: 85 ft-lbs, stanchion arm:
    78 ft-lbs plus 90 degrees.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050213e.New_vs_old.jpg" title="New vs old" date="13.02.2005">
    Intrax springs have one coil less than the original, so they are
    more than an inch shorter, but also stiffer. Bilstein dampers are only
    a few millimetres shorter, but look much more serious. They come with their own
    dust shield, which does not include a bump stop (this is by design). The
    sleeve nut is also different.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050213f.Strut_insert.jpg" title="Strut insert" date="13.02.2005">
    Here's the new damper fitted into the strut. I didn't have a torque wrench
    that goes up to 160 ft-lbs, so I just put some loctite on the threads and
    tightened it as hard as I could.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050213g.Spring.jpg" title="Spring" date="13.02.2005">
    A spring has to be compressed before it's put back on.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050213h.Thrust_bearings.jpg" title="Thrust bearings" date="13.02.2005">
    Here's a new SKF thrust bearing vs whatever was on the car before. You
    can see the damage on the body of the old bearing. Just a bit more, and it
    would've split in half.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050213i.Assembling.jpg" title="Assembling" date="13.02.2005">
    I used the original spring support and washers, but replaced strut mounts
    and bearings. The new top nut that came with Bilstein dampers is the same
    size as the original, but the grip on top of the rod is different, you
    need a 7 mm Allen key for it.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050213j.Strut_complete.jpg" title="Strut complete" date="13.02.2005">
    Make sure the spring fits both top and bottom supports correctly, with the
    end of the coil against the spring stops. The top nut should be secured
    well enough, but not yet to the spec, you'll need to do that later.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050214a.Strut_mount.jpg" title="Strut mount" date="14.02.2005">
    Fit the strut on the car and put the strut mount nuts on. Note that the
    rearmost nut has a washer, while the other two don't. Tighten the nuts
    alternately at 13 ft-lbs (13 mm socket).
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050214b.Driveshaft.jpg" title="Driveshaft" date="14.02.2005">
    Tilt the strut and insert the driveshaft into the hub. Fit the top washer
    and bushing onto the sway bar link. Prepare a new ball joint nut (do not
    reuse the old one).
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050214c.Ball_joint.jpg" title="Ball joint" date="14.02.2005">
    Insert the ball joint rod into the strut and put the nut on. Jack up the
    base of the strut to force the ball joint in and prevent it from spinning.
    Tighten the nut to 55 ft-lbs (18 mm wrench).
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050214d.Tie_rod_end.jpg" title="Tie rod end" date="14.02.2005">
    Clamp the tie rod end and tighten the nut to 45 ft-lbs (18 mm socket).
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050214e.Sway_bar.jpg" title="Sway bar" date="14.02.2005">
    Put the lower bushing and washer on the sway bar link. Use an 11 mm open
    wrench to hold the link at the top end, and a 13 mm wrench to tighten the
    nut (8 ft-lbs)
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050214f.Brakes.jpg" title="Brakes" date="14.02.2005">
    Fit the ABS sensor and the brake rotor. Clean the hub before fitting the
    rotor and apply some anti-seize to the hub and the rotor index screw.
    Do not tighten the screw too much, unless you want to drill it out again.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050214g.Caliper.jpg" title="Caliper" date="14.02.2005">
    Put the brake caliper back on, apply some loctite to the bolts and
    tighten them to 87 ft-lbs (10 mm Allen key). Bolt on a new hub centre
    nut (do not reuse the old one), but do not tighten it completely yet.
    Stick a screwdriver into the rotor to prevent it from spinning.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050214h.Strut.jpg" title="Strut" date="14.02.2005">
    Attach the belt shield. Fit the wheels and tighten the bolts to 84 ft-lbs.
    Lower the car to the ground.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050215a.Hub_centre_nut.jpg" title="Hub centre nut" date="15.02.2005">
    The hub nut (32 mm) should be tightened at 214 ft-lbs. I don't have a
    torque wrench that goes that high, but 140 lbs of my weight applied to a
    foot-and-a-half long breaker bar should work out about right.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050215b.Final_touch.jpg" title="Final_touch" date="15.02.2005">
    With the wheels on the ground, tighten the upper nut on the damper to 66
    ft-lbs (24 mm wrench and a 7 mm Allen key). Congratulations, you have just
    finished rebuilding your front suspension!
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
</picture-set>
