<?xml version="1.0"?>
<picture-set title="Saab NG900/9-3: Saab Sport Exhaust">

  <description>
  <p>Sport exaust installation on the 1996 Saab 900 (a 1999-2002 9-3 would be the same).
  The old exhaust system is
  being replaced with a "sport" cat-back exhaust from the Saab Catalog. The
  new exhaust is fully stainless, has a straight throught middle pipe and a
  small muffler in the back. It produces a nice rumbling sound at idle and
  a proper aggressive note on acceleration. In the same time it manages to
  remain quiet at cruising speeds.</p>

  <h2>Tools:</h2>
  <ul>
    <li>13 mm socket;</li>
    <li>ratchet handle;</li>
    <li>muffler cement;</li>
    <li>ramps or jacks and stands.</li>
  </ul>
  </description>

  <picture name="20050909a.Old_exhaust.jpg" title="Old exhaust" date="09.09.2005">
    This is the old exhaust system. The muffler sits strangely low, but it's
    always been like this. It's in a good shape, and will go to a fellow club
    member.
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050909b.Ramps.jpg" title="Ramps" date="09.09.2005">
    Raise the rear end of the car.
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050909c.Flex_pipe_joint.jpg" title="Flex pipe joint" date="09.09.2005">
    Undo the clamp at the joint between the flex pipe and the silencer.
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050909d.Silencer.jpg" title="Silencer" date="09.09.2005">
    The silencer is old and has a couple of rust areas. The U-shaped pipe that
    goes around the fuel tank had seen its better days also.
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050909e.Muffler_joint.jpg" title="Muffler joint" date="09.09.2005">
    The other clamp is right in front of the rear muffler. Undo that, and
    remove the old exhaust system from the car.
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050909f.Sport_exhaust.jpg" title="Sport exhaust" date="09.09.2005">
    The sport exhaust as it came out of the box. It is used, I bought it on
    eBay. However, being stainless, it hardly shows any wear.
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050909g.New_vs_old.jpg" title="New vs old" date="09.09.2005">
    Both exhausts on the ground. You can see that the pipes aren't much
    thicker.
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050909h.Old_vs_new.jpg" title="Old vs new" date="09.09.2005">
    The old one consists of two pieces, while the new one has an extra joint in
    the middle.
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050909i.Old_vs_new.jpg" title="Old vs new" date="09.09.2005">
    The old one has an extra silencer, while the sport version is just a
    straight pipe.
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050909j.New_vs_old.jpg" title="New vs old" date="09.09.2005">
    The sport muffler is much smaller too.
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050909k.Mufflers.jpg" title="Mufflers" date="09.09.2005">
    It is odd that the joints on the mufflers are different. Perhaps, it's made
    on purpose to prevent you from mixing old and new parts.
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050909l.Mufflers.jpg" title="Mufflers" date="09.09.2005">
    Even the hangers are stainless, with their ends protected by plastic
    sleeves.
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050909m.Flex_pipe_joint.jpg" title="Flex pipe joint" date="09.09.2005">
    Put the centre pipe on and connect it to the flex pipe.
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050909n.Muffler_joint.jpg" title="Muffler joint" date="09.09.2005">
    Install the rear muffler and join it with the other end of the pipe.
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050909o.Clamp.jpg" title="Clamp" date="09.09.2005">
    Adjust the position of the exhaust system, make sure the pipes are level
    and don't rub against the body or the heat shield. Tighten the clamp on the
    middle joint.
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050909p.Muffler_cement.jpg" title="Muffler cement" date="09.09.2005">
    Clean the front joint from the old sealant and apply some muffler cement.
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050909q.Front_clamp.jpg" title="Front clamp" date="09.09.2005">
    Tighten the clamp. Be careful not to place too much strain on the flex pipe,
    it doesn't like that.
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050909r.Muffler_cement.jpg" title="Muffler cement" date="09.09.2005">
    Apply more muffler cement on the rear joint. You can see how low the Intrax
    springs are. I have perhaps only an inch between the bump stops in the rear.
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050909s.Rear_clamp.jpg" title="Rear clamp" date="09.09.2005">
    Tighten the clamp. This one has a shiny new bolt -- I snapped it
    when removing the clamp and ended up hammering out the old bolt seat and
    using a regular nut with a washer on that side.
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050909t.Muffler.jpg" title="Muffler" date="09.09.2005">
    A close-up of the new muffler.
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050909u.Muffler.jpg" title="Muffler" date="09.09.2005">
    Another view of the muffler. The 22 mm Genuine Saab sway bar is seen in
    the back ;]
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050909v.New_exhaust.jpg" title="New exhaust" date="09.09.2005">
    The new exhaust sits a bit higher and fits the cut-out perfectly. It didn't
    come with a chrome tip, and I won't bother buying one. It has a good
    spartan look, like a proper sleeper should.
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
</picture-set>
