<?xml version="1.0"?>
<picture-set title="Saab NG900/9-3: Manual Transmission Removal">

  <description>
  <p>Manual transmission removal on a 1996 Saab 900 (applies to all 1994-1998
  900 and 1999-2002 9-3). The goal was to install a new clutch and replace
  the transmission with a newer, stronger unit. This article covers
  gearbox removal only, for installation refer to
  <a href="#/content/saab/20060211-saab-ng900-manual-transmission-installation">this section</a>.</p>

  <h2>Tools:</h2>
  <ul>
    <li>22 mm crowfoot wrench: O2 sensors;</li>
    <li>19 mm socket: flywheel bolts;</li>
    <li>18 mm socket: transmission, subframe bolts;</li>
    <li>18 mm wrench: ball joint nuts;</li>
    <li>17 mm socket: wheel bolts;</li>
    <li>16 mm socket: subframe bolts, engine mounts;</li>
    <li>15 mm socket: transmission mount bolts, control arms (optional);</li>
    <li>13 mm socket: exhaust, downpipe, shift linkage, battery;</li>
    <li>13 mm wrench: delivery pipe bolt;</li>
    <li>12 mm socket: pressure plate bolts;</li>
    <li>11 mm socket: flywheel cover bolts, subframe brace nuts;</li>
    <li>10 mm socket: battery base bolts;</li>
    <li>9 mm wrench: battery terminals (13 mm on 9-3);</li>
    <li>8 mm Allen socket: transmission drain plug;</li>
    <li>8 mm hex screwdriver: lower shield screws;</li>
    <li>7 mm hex screwdriver: delivery pipe hose clamps (or a flat screwdriver);</li>
    <li>3 mm L-shaped Allen key: transmission lock;</li>
    <li>engine support beam or engine crane;</li>
    <li>car jacks and axle stands;</li>
    <li>breaker bar.</li>
  </ul>
  </description>

  <picture name="20060121a0.Battery.jpg" title="Battery" date="21.01.2006">
    Disconnect both cables from the battery (negative first!). Unscrew the
    13 mm bolt at the battery base.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060121a1.Battery_base.jpg" title="Battery base" date="21.01.2006">
    Lift the battery and store it in a safe place. Unbolt the battery
    mounting plate (two 10 mm bolts) and remove it from the car.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060121a2.Delivery_pipe.jpg" title="Delivery pipe" date="21.01.2006">
    Release the hose clamp on the lower end of the delivery pipe.
    Unhook the vacuum line from the bypass valve (as well as the return
    hose if you have it).
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060121a3.Delivery_pipe.jpg" title="Delivery pipe" date="21.01.2006">
    Remove the hose clamp from the throttle body side of the delivery
    pipe. Unbolt the pipe from the engine (13 mm wrench).
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060121a4.Delivery_pipe.jpg" title="Delivery pipe" date="21.01.2006">
    Remove the delivery pipe from the car. Plug the intercooler hose and
    throttle body inlet to keep the dirt away.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060121a5.Fourth_gear.jpg" title="Fourth gear" date="21.01.2006">
    Move the shifter into fourth gear.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060121a6.Transmission_lock.jpg" title="Transmission lock" date="21.01.2006">
    Remove the plastic plug on top of the transmission and insert a thin
    L-shaped Allen key to lock it in gear.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060121a7.Linkage.jpg" title="Linkage" date="21.01.2006">
    Use a 13 mm socket with a long extension to loosen the nut on the
    shifter linkage. And yes, this is genuine Canadian snow.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060121a9.Third_gear.jpg" title="Third gear" date="21.01.2006">
    Move the shifter into third gear position to separate the shifting rod
    from the linkage.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060121b0.Cable.jpg" title="Cable" date="21.01.2006">
    If you have a cable clutch, unhook the cable from the lever on top of the
    transmission. If it is hydraulic, pull the clip to detach the clutch line
    from its nipple and quickly plug it to minimize fluid loss.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060121b1.Cable.jpg" title="Cable" date="21.01.2006">
    Pull the cable from its seat on the other end of the transmission.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060121b2.Reverse_switch.jpg" title="Reverse switch" date="21.01.2006">
    Unplug the reverse gear switch.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060121b3.Wheels.jpg" title="Wheels" date="21.01.2006">
    Loosen wheel nuts (17 mm wrench).
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060121b4.In_the_air.jpg" title="In the air" date="21.01.2006">
    Raise the front of the car, remove the wheels, take off the plastic shields
    under the bumper.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060121b5.Brace.jpg" title="Brace" date="21.01.2006">
    Remove the subframe brace if equipped (11 mm socket for MP Performance
    version).
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060121b6.Exhaust_joint.jpg" title="Exhaust joint" date="21.01.2006">
    Unscrew the rear O2 sensor (22 mm crowfoot socket), remove the clamp
    from the exhaust pipe (13 mm socket). Unbolt the two rear engine mount
    nuts sitting in the round holes in the subframe (16/17 mm socket).
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060121b7.Downpipe.jpg" title="Downpipe" date="21.01.2006">
    Unbolt the front O2 sensor (22 mm crowfoot) and detach the downpipe
    from the turbo (three 13 mm nuts).
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060121b8.Downpipe.jpg" title="Downpipe" date="21.01.2006">
    Unhook the rubber hangers and remove the downpipe from the car.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060121b9.Linkage.jpg" title="Linkage" date="21.01.2006">
    Unbolt the linkage from the shifter rod on the transmission (13 mm socket).

    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060121c0.Linkage.jpg" title="Linkage" date="21.01.2006">
    Detach the linkage support arm from the ball pin on the differential
    housing (or pull it from the eye on the mount if you have an old-style
    linkage).
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060121c1.Linkage.jpg" title="Linkage" date="21.01.2006">
    Remove the gearshift linkage from the car.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060121c2.Engine_support.jpg" title="Engine support" date="21.01.2006">
    Unbolt the rear engine mount from the subframe, install an engine support beam on the fenders, attach it to the lifting
    hook on the head and pull up slightly to ensure it takes the weight
    of the engine.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060121c3.Subframe_bolts.jpg" title="Subframe bolts" date="21.01.2006">
    Start removing the subframe bolts. The rear bolts holding the stanchion
    arms take a 16 mm socket, the middle ones are 18 mm.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060121c4.Subframe_bolts.jpg" title="Subframe bolts" date="21.01.2006">
    The bolts in front have a 16 mm head as well. With all bols removed,
    the subframe will be hanging on just the ball joints.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060121c5.Ball_joint.jpg" title="Ball joint" date="21.01.2006">
    You can usually separate the ball joints by unscrewing the nut a bit, and
    hitting the knuckle with a heavy hammer (the weight of the subframe helps
    to release the ball joints).
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060121c6.Jack.jpg" title="Jack" date="21.01.2006">
    If the ball joints cannot be defeated, unbolt the control arms from
    the subframe. Jack it up so it doesn't drop to the ground right away.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060121c7.Subframe.jpg" title="Subframe" date="21.01.2006">
    Lower the subframe to the ground and drag it away. In my case, I succeeded
    in separating one ball joint, and unbolted the control arm on the other
    side.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060121c8.Subframe_bolts.jpg" title="Subframe bolts" date="21.01.2006">
    The subframe bolts left to right: rear, middle, front. Don't lose the
    washers that go between the subframe and the body above the stanchion arms.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060121c9.Transmission_oil.jpg" title="Transmission oil" date="21.01.2006">
    With the subframe out of the way, it's now easy to remove tha drain plug
    (8 mm Allen socket) and drain the transmission oil.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060121d0.Driveshaft.jpg" title="Driveshaft" date="21.01.2006">
    Prop a wide flat chisel against the differential housing and push on the
    other end to pop the driveshaft. It should slide right out.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060121d1.Driveshaft.jpg" title="Driveshaft" date="21.01.2006">
    Suspend the driveshaft (or remove it completely if you unbolted the axle
    nut).
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060121d2.Flywheel_cover.jpg" title="Flywheel cover" date="21.01.2006">
    Unbolt the flywheel cover at the bottom of the transmission
    (two 11 mm bolts).
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060121d3.Upper_bolts.jpg" title="Upper bolts" date="21.01.2006">
    Remove the three upper bolts attaching the transmission to the engine
    (18 mm socket).
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060121d4.Transmission_mount.jpg" title="Transmission mount" date="21.01.2006">
    Detach the small wire on the side of the transmission (13 mm socket).
    Unbolt the transmission mount from the body (two 15 mm bolts), lower
    the engine slightly to free up the mount.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060121d5.Mount_bracket.jpg" title="Mount bracket" date="21.01.2006">
    Unhook the big ground wire from the transmission (17 mm socket). Unbolt
    the bracket from the transmission (and the mount itself from the
    bracket if it helps to remove it).
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060121d6.Rear_bolt.jpg" title="Rear bolt" date="21.01.2006">
    Remove the rear transmission bolt (18 mm socket).
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060121d7.Lowering.jpg" title="Lowering" date="21.01.2006">
    Lower the engine as much as needed to get a good access to the transmission.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060121d8.Jacks.jpg" title="Jacks" date="21.01.2006">
    If you don't have a specialized transmission jack, a couple of regular ones
    will support it from below. Just make sure it's balanced right so it won't
    slide sideways and fall to the ground when you detach it from the engine.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060121e0.Front_bolt.jpg" title="Front bolt" date="21.01.2006">
    Undo the last bolt holding the transmission. If you were lucky enough to
    detach a control arm from the subframe, you can use its bolt as a guiding
    pin in place of the shorter original bolt.
    Gently pry the transmission away from the engine. 
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060121e1.Transmission_down.jpg" title="Transmission down" date="21.01.2006">
    The main shaft will slide right out, but the intermediate shaft might not
    want to separate, so in the worst case you'll have to unbolt it from the
    block under the alternator. Lower the transmission to the ground.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060624a.Crane.jpg" title="Crane" date="24.06.2006">
    A shop crane makes transmission removal much easier. Older gearboxes
    have one hole for a lifting eye, newer ones might have two.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060121e2.Transmission.jpg" title="Transmission" date="21.01.2006">
    Move the transmission away and unbolt the rear engine mount bracket if
    you're planning to transfer it to a new gearbox.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060121e3.Pressure_plate.jpg" title="Pressure plate" date="21.01.2006">
    The flywheel will turn a bit, so you might need to came up with a way to
    hold it in place while unbolting the pressure plate (six 12 mm bolts).
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060121e4.Flywheel.jpg" title="Flywheel" date="21.01.2006">
    If the flywheel is visibly scratched or scored, or has cracks in it, you
    need to remove it from the engine and take to a machine shop for
    resurfacing.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060121e5.Old_clutch.jpg" title="Old clutch" date="21.01.2006">
    The poor clutch shows painful signs of trying to hold stage3 power.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
</picture-set>
