<?xml version="1.0"?>
<picture-set title="Saab 9-5: Rear Suspension">

  <description>
  <p>Rear suspension replacement on a 1999 Saab 9-5. The old and tired original
  shocks and springs are being upgraded with Bilstein Sport dampers and
  Eibach Pro Kit lowering springs.</p>

  <h2>Tools:</h2>
  <ul>
    <li>21 mm socket: lower shock bolt;</li>
    <li>17 mm socket: wheel bolts, Bilstein shock retainer nut;</li>
    <li>16 mm socket: shock housing bolts, OEM shock retainer nut;</li>
    <li>5 mm Allen socket: Bilstein damper rod;</li>
    <li>torque wrench;</li>
    <li>vice-grips;</li>
    <li>breaker bar;</li>
    <li>car jack and axle stands;</li>
    <li>spring compressor.</li>
  </ul>
  </description>

  <picture name="20070930a.Jack_stands.jpg" title="Jack stands" date="30.09.2007">
    Raise the car and secure it on jack stands. Take the wheel off.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070930b.Shock_bolt.jpg" title="Shock bolt" date="30.09.2007">
    Undo the big bolt holding the bottom of the shock to the suspension arm.
    You might need a long breaker bar to wrestle it loose.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070930c.Housing_bolts.jpg" title="Housing bolts" date="30.09.2007">
    Undo the two bottom housing bolts and slacken the two at the top, slide
    the shock down.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070930d.Shock_assembly.jpg" title="Shock assembly" date="30.09.2007">
    Lower the shock to the ground, note if it has any shims installed - you
    will need to reuse those.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070930e.Wire_brush.jpg" title="Wire brush" date="30.09.2007">
    There's a good chance that the retainer nut and the top of the shock will
    be rusted beyond hope. Start by cleaning the threads with a wire wheel.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070930f.Thread_cleanup.jpg" title="Thread cleanup" date="30.09.2007">
    If you have a die set, it could be a big help in restoring the threads.
    The rod has a metric thread of M10x1.5mm.
    <image width="798" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070930g.Retainer_nut.jpg" title="Retainer nut" date="30.09.2007">
    Compress the spring and undo the retainer nut. If you don't have an impact
    wrench, grab the top of the rod with vice-grips and use a 16 mm spanner
    on the nut. Turn the nut back and forth if it gets stuck midway.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070930h.Disassembled.jpg" title="Disassembled" date="30.09.2007">
    The shock apart (counter-clockwise): damper, spring, dust shield with bump
    stop, washer, lower bushing with a sleeve, spring seat, spring bracket,
    upper bushing, washer, retainer nut.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070930i.New_vs_old.jpg" title="New vs old" date="30.09.2007">
    The Bilstein Sport damper has a slightly shorter rod, but looks similar
    to OEM otherwise. The Eibach spring is actually slightly longer, but has a
    number of "barrel" coils that are normally compressed together, while
    the lower coils provide the springing action. The barrel coils are
    thoughfully wrapped in a sleeve to prevent them from scratching each
    other and developing rust. <a href="#/content/saab/20061014-saab-ng900-rear-springs-intrax-vs-eibach">See
    what happens</a> when they're left unprotected.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070930j.Ready_to_go.jpg" title="Ready to go" date="30.09.2007">
    The damper comes with an aluminium lower spring support and a new spacer
    ring that fit at the base of the rod. When you compress the spring, use
    the working coils only, because the upper barrel coils will end up too
    close to each other, so your spring compressor would get stuck. All the
    other parts of the shock assembly are reused here. Make sure that the upper
    coil of the spring matches the recess in the upper spring seat.
    <image width="800" height="599" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070930k.Top_nut.jpg" title="Top nut" date="30.09.2007">
    Tighten the retainer nut to 15 ft-lbs. Use a 5 mm Allen key on the rod
    while holding socket with vice-grips (or use a spanner on the nut).
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070930l.Housing_bolts.jpg" title="Housing bolts" date="30.09.2007">
    Slide the housing up as far as it goes until it's propped against the top
    bolts (use a jack if necessary). Insert the lower bolts and
    tighten all four to 40 ft-lbs.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070930m.Lower_bolt.jpg" title="Lower bolt" date="30.09.2007">
    Insert the lower bolt, rotate the damper if needed to align the holes.
    Tighten to 140 ft-lbs.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070929x.Lowered.jpg" title="Done" date="30.09.2007">
    Install the wheels, tighten the lug bolts to 81 ft-lbs and lower the
    car to the ground. Enjoy a 35 mm lower ride height.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
</picture-set>
