<?xml version="1.0"?>
<picture-set title="Saab 9-5: Hands Free Phone Connection">

  <description>
  <p>This is the first guide I ever published. It was a hands free mobile phone
  kit for a Saab 9-5.</p>
  <p>The installation is pretty straightforward, the whole thing was prepared in a single
  evening and installed the next morning.</p>
  </description>

  <picture name="20030816a.Saab_telephone_harness.jpg" title="Saab telephone harness" date="16.08.2003">
    The first, and the most expensive part you need is the Saab telephone
    harness. Part #30567734, price $17.49. My dealership didn't have it in
    stock, and I was the first customer to ever ask about it. The warehouse
    also had it on back order, so it took them over a week to find the part
    for me. The harness comes in a rather large box and has a manual in
    7 languages containing brief installation instructions and connection
    specifications.
    <image width="720" height="540" />
    
  </picture>
  <picture name="20030816b.A_phone_plug_and_a_switch.jpg" title="A phone plug and a switch" date="16.08.2003">
    Your next stop is Radio Shack. If your phone has a 2.5 mm jack, the
    plug is $3.99. Typically, the tip of the connector is the microphone, the
    middle contact is the output, and the base is the ground. If don't
    want to bother soldering, or if your phone has a proprietary connector,
    just get a cheap earpiece or a hands-free set and cut the wires off.
    Also, if your phone does not support muting the radio, a push-button
    switch will cost you another $4.79.
    <image width="720" height="540" />
    
  </picture>
  <picture name="20030816c.Cell_phone.jpg" title="Cell phone" date="16.08.2003">
    The essential part, a cellular phone. This one can be obtained for free
    with a year subscription from Rogers.
    <image width="720" height="540" />
    
  </picture>
  <picture name="20030816d.Dead_mouse.jpg" title="Dead mouse" date="16.08.2003">
    A dead mouse, $0. I get a long flexible cable, my two year old son gets
    a new toy. He's already got a keyboard of his own, so this would be a logical
    addition.
    <image width="720" height="540" />
    
  </picture>
  <picture name="20030816e.Cradle.jpg" title="Cradle" date="16.08.2003">
    A $10 phone cradle from a local hardware store. It comes with a swivel
    base that sticks to the dashboard.
    <image width="720" height="540" />
    
  </picture>
  <picture name="20030816f.Cradle_dissection.jpg" title="Cradle dissection" date="16.08.2003">
    The cradle is taken apart to cut a hole for the switch.
    <image width="720" height="540" />
    
  </picture>
  <picture name="20030816g.Cradle_with_cable.jpg" title="Cradle with cable" date="16.08.2003">
    The cable has five wires -- three for the telephone (microphone, output and
    ground) and two for the mute button (the signal and the ground). I wonder
    if you can get away with four wires by combining the grounds (they are
    separate on the harness though).
    <image width="720" height="540" />
    
  </picture>
  <picture name="20030816h.Cradle_with_cell_phone.jpg" title="Cradle with cell phone" date="16.08.2003">
    We have two cell phones, one has a headphone jack on the right side, the other
    at the bottom. I had to leave a rather long piece of cable
    attached to the plug to fit both phones (and who knows what we will
    get next).
    <image width="720" height="540" />
    
  </picture>
  <picture name="20030817a.Cradle.jpg" title="Cradle" date="17.08.2003">
    Many phones perform the "answer" or "dial" action depending on the context,
    when you short circuit the microphone signal to the ground. If your unit
    supports this feature, you can install a second (momentary) switch to take
    advantage of that. Out of my phones only one does it, so I didn't bother.
    <image width="720" height="540" />
    
  </picture>
  <picture name="20030817b.ACC_head_removal.jpg" title="ACC head removal" date="17.08.2003">
    To remove the ACC head unit, use a flat screwdriver or another tool to
    gently pry out the edge, then another edge, and then the unit pops out
    easily.
    <image width="720" height="540" />
    
  </picture>
  <picture name="20030817c.Connecting_the_wires.jpg" title="Connecting the wires" date="17.08.2003">
    Unfortunately, you cannot solder your cable to the harness at home since the
    wires have to be pulled through a tiny hole (through the "On Star" button
    socket in my case), and neither it's easy to solder them when in the car.
    I ended up simply twisting wire ends together and wrapping them with
    electric tape. If you have OnStar in your car, there may not be a
    telephone connector available, so you might need a different kind of
    harness or a splitter.
    <image width="720" height="540" />
    
  </picture>
  <picture name="20030817d.Harness_closeup.jpg" title="Harness closeup" date="17.08.2003">
    Before plugging the harness in, note the red locking tab on top of the
    socket -- you need to pull it up before inserting the connector. Connect
    pin 3 (microphone ground) and pin 8 (output ground) together to the ground
    from the telephone. Pin 10 to the microphone signal, and pin 7 to the
    output signal. Pins 4 (ground) and 5 (radio mute) should be connected to
    the wires from the push-button switch (or to the appropriate pins on the
    proprietary phone connector if the phone supports the mute feature).
    <image width="720" height="540" />
    
  </picture>
  <picture name="20030817e.Cradle_base.jpg" title="Cradle base" date="17.08.2003">
    I did not want to damage the wooden trim by sticking the cradle directly
    on it, so I attached the base to a piece of thick transparent plastic
    (which I cut off the packaging of the cradle itself ;).
    <image width="720" height="540" />
    
  </picture>
  <picture name="20030817f.Base_installation.jpg" title="Base installation" date="17.08.2003">
    Then I bent the plastic and inserted it between the wood veneer and the
    dash. There's enough adhesive in between them to hold the cradle well.
    <image width="720" height="540" />
    
  </picture>
  <picture name="20030817g.Base_in_place.jpg" title="Base in place" date="17.08.2003">
    The job is done.
    <image width="720" height="540" />
    
  </picture>
  <picture name="20030817h.Cradle_mounted.jpg" title="Cradle mounted" date="17.08.2003">
    This picture shows the cradle and the wires -- the phone connector hangs
    down freely, and the other end disappears between the button plugs.
    <image width="720" height="540" />
    
  </picture>
  <picture name="20030817i.Passenger_view.jpg" title="Passenger view" date="17.08.2003">
    When you push the button on top of the cradle, the SID displays the
    "TELEPHONE" message, and you can talk on the phone. If you were listening
    to the radio, it will be turned off temporarily. Pushing the cradle button
    off brings back the radio and the information the SID was displaying before
    the call. Curiously enough, it works even when the car is not started --
    the SID wakes up showing the time and the "TELEPHONE" message, you make the
    call and then turn the whole thing off by releasing the cradle button.
    <image width="720" height="540" />
    
  </picture>
  <picture name="20030817j.Driver_view.jpg" title="Driver view" date="17.08.2003">
    The sound quality is quite good, definitely better than through the
    earpiece that came with my phone. I did not have to adjust the microphone
    in the car, and I'm not aware of what setting is it on, high or low.
    The sound on the other end of the line is OK as well. You might also want
    to increase the default volume of the telephone mode -- there's a setting
    in the stereo unit setup mode (you can invoke it by turning the stereo on
    with the "WB" button pressed).
    <image width="720" height="540" />
    
  </picture>
</picture-set>
