<?xml version="1.0"?>
<picture-set title="Saab NG900/9-3: Manual Transmission Installation">

  <description>
  <p>Manual transmission installation on a 1996 Saab 900 (applies to all 1994-1998
  900 and 1999-2002 9-3). The goal was to install a new clutch and replace
  the transmission with a newer, stronger unit. This article covers
  gearbox installation only, for removal refer to
  <a href="#/content/saab/20060121-saab-ng900-manual-transmission-removal">this section</a>.</p>

  <h2>Tools:</h2>
  <ul>
    <li>24 mm socket: transmission fill plug (9-3);</li>
    <li>22 mm crowfoot wrench: O2 sensors;</li>
    <li>19 mm socket: flywheel bolts;</li>
    <li>18 mm socket: transmission, subframe bolts;</li>
    <li>18 mm wrench: ball joint nuts;</li>
    <li>17 mm socket: wheel bolts;</li>
    <li>16 mm socket: subframe bolts, engine mounts;</li>
    <li>15 mm socket: transmission mount bolts, control arms (optional);</li>
    <li>13 mm socket: exhaust, downpipe, shift linkage, battery;</li>
    <li>13 mm wrench: delivery pipe bolt;</li>
    <li>12 mm socket: pressure plate bolts;</li>
    <li>11 mm socket: flywheel cover bolts, subframe brace nuts;</li>
    <li>10 mm socket: battery base bolts;</li>
    <li>9 mm wrench: battery terminals (13 mm on 9-3);</li>
    <li>8 mm Allen socket: transmission drain plug;</li>
    <li>8 mm hex screwdriver: lower shield screws;</li>
    <li>7 mm hex screwdriver: delivery pipe hose clamps (or a flat screwdriver);</li>
    <li>3 mm L-shaped Allen key: transmission lock;</li>
    <li>engine support beam or engine crane;</li>
    <li>car jacks and axle stands;</li>
    <li>pressure bleeder and fresh brake fluid;</li>
    <li>hand pump and a 40..50 cm long piece of clear tubing (if slave bleeding is needed);</li>
    <li>fresh gearbox oil;</li>
    <li>breaker bar.</li>
  </ul>
  </description>

  <picture name="20060211a0.Transmission.jpg" title="Transmission" date="11.02.2006">
    The replacement transmission came from a 1999 9-3. It's an FM55 505 model,
    while the original gearbox on the car was FM55 501.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060211a1.Left_side.jpg" title="Left side" date="11.02.2006">
    The new gearbox came from a scrap yard, so it's a good idea to replace
    both differential seals.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060211a3.Seals.jpg" title="Seals" date="11.02.2006">
    Pry the new seal out using a big screwdriver or a chisel. It's not
    necessary to remove the entire cover, but I find it easier than doing
    it right on the gearbox.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060211a4.Cover_in.jpg" title="Cover in" date="11.02.2006">
    Carefully push the new seal in, use a rubber mallet if needed. Install
    the cover back on and tighten the bolts to 16 ft-lbs with a Torx T40 socket.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060211a5.Right_side.jpg" title="Right side" date="11.02.2006">
    Do the same on the right side of the differential.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060211a6.Seals.jpg" title="Seals" date="11.02.2006">
    The bag shows a GM part number (useful if your dealer uses those, like
    they do in Canada). The Saab part is #8749046.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060211b0.Rear_mount.jpg" title="Rear mount" date="11.02.2006">
    Attach the rear engine mount (30 ft-lbs, 16 mm socket). For a
    later transmission model, the mount bracket might be different -- check the
    compatibility if you're upgrading to a newer gearbox.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060211b1.Pipe.jpg" title="Pipe" date="11.02.2006">
    Time to bleed the slave cylinder. Push the throwout bearing in slowly to
    compress the piston inside it. When you let go, the bearing will spring
    back out, but the piston will remain compressed.
    
    <image width="600" height="800" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060211b2.Brake_fluid.jpg" title="Brake fluid" date="11.02.2006">
    Attach a 40..50 cm piece of clear tubing to nipple on top of the slave
    cylinder. Fill the tube with brake fluid to 3/4 of its height.
    
    <image width="600" height="800" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060211b3.Pressure.jpg" title="Pressure" date="11.02.2006">
    Pump some air into the tube. The slave cylinder will expand, and you will
    see the fluid level dropping. When the cylinder maxes out, the fluid will
    stop and the pressure will go up. Release the pressure and compress
    the slave again. You might see small air bubbles coming out.
    
    <image width="600" height="800" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060211b4.Bleeding_finished.jpg" title="Bleeding finished" date="11.02.2006">
    Repeat the process several times, add more brake fluid if necessary. When
    you don't see the bubbles anymore, detach the hose (careful not to
    spill the fluid all over) and plug the nipple.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060211b5.Ready.jpg" title="Ready" date="11.02.2006">
    Lock the transmission in third gear. Make sure you can undo the fill and
    drain plugs (but keep them in). Lubricate the shaft splines.
    The gearbox is ready for installation.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060211a8.New_clutch.jpg" title="New clutch" date="11.02.2006">
    I am installing a Viggen pressure plate with a SPEC stage2 kevlar clutch
    plate. The clutch conveniently comes with an alignment tool.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060211a7.Flywheel.jpg" title="Flywheel" date="11.02.2006">
    Inspect the flywheel. If it's visibly scratched or scored, or has cracks
    on the surface, you need to take it to a machine shop for resurfacing.
    Torque the bolts to 59 ft-lbs.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060211a9.Alignment_tool.jpg" title="Alignment tool" date="11.02.2006">
    Install the clutch with the pressure plate and put the bolts in hand-tight.
    Insert the alignment tool and make sure the clutch plate it perfectly
    centered. Tighten the bolts alternately to 16 ft-lbs (12 mm socket).
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060211b6.Jacks.jpg" title="Jacks" date="11.02.2006">
    <p>A specialized transmission jack or a shop crane is preferred, but a pair of
    regular hydraulic jacks will do the job. Make sure the transmission is
    balanced, roll it under the car and raise to the engine level.</p>

    <p>P.S. Having done this a few times since, the easiest way is to screw
    a couple of guide pins into the mounting bolt holes, then simply
    bench press the gearbox onto them. It's not THAT heavy.</p>

    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060211b7.Left_side.jpg" title="Left side" date="11.02.2006">
    <p>Push the transmission in. Remember that you have to match the splines on
    the clutch plate and the intermediate shaft in the same time. If necessary,
    turn the flywheel and/or the driveshaft on the right side. Get a helper for that,
    it saves a lot of time.</p>
    
    <p>The picture shows the brake line disconnected, it was a part of
    <a href="#/content/saab/20060213-saab-ng900-stainless-brake-lines">another job</a>.</p>
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060211b8.Fitted.jpg" title="Fitted" date="11.02.2006">
    The transmission should be perfectly level with the engine in order to go
    in. Again, a lower control arm bolt works well as a guiding pin. Once you
    close the gap and the intermediate shaft snaps in on the other side,
    replace the front bolt with a proper one and tighten it.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060211b9.Upper_bolts.jpg" title="Upper bolts" date="11.02.2006">
    The three upper bolts are easily accessible from the wheel well, just use a
    longer extention. Don't forget the fifth bolt in the rear. The torque for
    these is 50 ft-lbs (18 mm socket).
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060211c0.Clutch_line.jpg" title="Clutch line" date="11.02.2006">
    Remove the cap from the slave cylinder nipple and attach the clutch line.
    If you have a cable clutch, attach the cable.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060211c1.Clutch_line.jpg" title="Clutch line" date="11.02.2006">
    Insert a locking clip to secure the clutch line. The nipple in front will
    be used to bleed the clutch once the job is done.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060211c2.Bracket.jpg" title="Bracket" date="11.02.2006">
    Attach the bracket for the transmission mount, as well as the mount
    itself (30 ft-lbs, 16 mm socket).
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060211c3.Support_beam.jpg" title="Support beam" date="11.02.2006">
    Raise the engine until the transmission mount fits its position on the
    side member.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060211c4.Mount.jpg" title="Mount" date="11.02.2006">
    Tighten the transmission mount bolts to 46 ft-lbs (15 mm socket). Attach
    the ground wires to the mount bracket, and to the side of the gearbox
    (17 mm and 13 mm sockets).
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060211c5.Driveshaft.jpg" title="Driveshaft" date="11.02.2006">
    Insert the driveshaft until the snap ring clicks. Plug in the reverse gear
    sensor wire.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060211c6.Flywheel_cover.jpg" title="Flywheel cover" date="11.02.2006">
    Install the flywheel cover (two 11 mm bolts).
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060211c8.Linkage.jpg" title="Linkage" date="11.02.2006">
    Attach the linkage to the gearshift rod on the transmission (13 mm bolt),
    connect the arm to the ball pin and insert the shifter rod into its housing.
    After the entire installation is finished, the shifter needs to be
    <a href="#/content/saab/20050325-saab-ng900-shifter-alignment">aligned</a>.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060211c9.Subframe.jpg" title="Subframe" date="11.02.2006">
    Position the subframe for installation.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060211d0.Front_bolts.jpg" title="Front bolts" date="11.02.2006">
    First, raise the front end and screw the bolts in hand-tight.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060211d1.Washers.jpg" title="Washers" date="11.02.2006">
    Place the washers on the stanchion arm attachment points.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060211d2.Rear_end.jpg" title="Rear end" date="11.02.2006">
    Jack up the rear end, insert the remaining bolts and align the subframe
    so it matches the position it was in before the removal. Connect the
    ball joints and tighten to 55 ft-lbs (18 mm wrench).
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060211d3.Subframe_bolts.jpg" title="Subframe bolts" date="11.02.2006">
    Tighten the four corner bolts using a 16 mm socket: front to 85 ft-lbs
    and rear to 78 ft-lbs + 90 degrees. Tighten the middle bolts to
    141 ft-lbs (18 mm socket). If you had to remove the control arms, they
    need a 15 mm socket at 85 ft-lbs.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060211d4.Rear_mount.jpg" title="Rear mount" date="11.02.2006">
    Tighten the nuts on the rear engine mount to 37 ft-lbs (16/17 mm socket).
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060211d5.Beam_removed.jpg" title="Beam removed" date="11.02.2006">
    Remove the engine support beam.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060211d6.Downpipe.jpg" title="Downpipe" date="11.02.2006">
    Attach the downpipe to the turbo (three 13 mm nuts at 18.5 ft-lbs).
    Install the front O2 sensor (22 mm crowfoot wrench, 41 ft-lbs).
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060211d7.Exhaust.jpg" title="Exhaust" date="11.02.2006">
    Install the rear O2 sensor (22 mm crowfoot wrench, 41 ft-lbs). Seal the
    joint to the flexpipe and tighten the clamp to 15 ft-lbs (13 mm socket).
    Install the subframe brace if equipped.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060211d8.Delivery_pipe.jpg" title="Delivery pipe" date="11.02.2006">
    Install the delivery pipe and tighten the hose clamps. Attach the hoses
    to the bypass valve. Bleed the clutch, shift the transmission to fourth
    gear and
    <a href="#/content/saab/20050325-saab-ng900-shifter-alignment">align</a>
    the shifter linkage.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060211d9.Gearbox_oil.jpg" title="Gearbox oil" date="11.02.2006">
    Fill the gearbox with oil (flush twice if switching to synthetic).
    Install the battery. Attach the lower shields. Fit the wheels (81 ft-lbs)
    and lower the car to the ground.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
</picture-set>
