<?xml version="1.0"?>
<picture-set title="Saab NG900/9-3: Engine Installation">

  <description>
  <p>Engine installation on a 1995 Saab 900 turbo. This would apply to 1994-1998 900 and 1999 9-3.</p>

  <p>Some find it easier to install the engine with the gearbox already attached,
  but it requires a load leveler so you could tilt the assembly, and I didn't
  have it that week. Having tried both, I still find it easier to install the engine separately.
  The room to fit them both is rather tight on the NG900/9-3 compared to a 9-5.</p>

  <p>The transmission can then be bolted on right after the engine is in, and this
  guide actually mixes engine installation with transmission installation
  steps. It is advised that you study the
  <a href="#/content/saab/20060211-saab-ng900-manual-transmission-installation">gearbox
  install guide</a> beforehand.</p>

  <p>When the job is complete, do not start the engine right away. Unplug the 
  direct ignition cassette harness, pull the fuel pump fuse and crank
  the engine with the starter to build up sufficient oil pressure. You need
  a good battery charge for that. Then plug everything back in and start
  the engine.</p>

  <h2>Tools:</h2>
  <ul>
    <li>22 mm wrench: oil cooler lines;</li>
    <li>19 mm wrench: brake booster hose;</li>
    <li>16 mm socket: A/C compressor;</li>
    <li>15 mm socket: side engine mounts;</li>
    <li>13 mm wrench: steering pump bolts, delivery pipe;</li>
    <li>10 mm socket: cruise control unit;</li>
    <li>8 mm socket: MAP sensor;</li>
    <li>7 mm socket: hose clamps;</li>
    <li>Torx T25 screwdriver: BPC;</li>
    <li>long 1/2" extension: belt tensioner release;</li>
    <li>engine support beam;</li>
    <li>shop crane;</li>
    <li>car jacks and axle stands.</li>
  </ul>
  </description>

  <picture name="20060710a.Lowering.jpg" title="Lowering" date="10.07.2006">
    Carefully lower the engine into the engine bay. Make sure it clears
    everything sticking out on its way down.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060710b.Engine_mount.jpg" title="Engine mount" date="10.07.2006">
    Align the engine so the passenger side mount can be attached to the body
    and tighten the bolts to 54 ft-lbs.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060710c.Support_bar.jpg" title="Support bar" date="10.07.2006">
    Install the support bar across the fenders and take the weight off the
    crane. The engine will now rest on the passenger side mount and the
    support bar.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060710d.Transmission.jpg" title="Transmission" date="10.07.2006">
    Now is the good time to
    <a href="#/content/saab/20060211-saab-ng900-manual-transmission-installation">install the transmission</a>.
    It can be done at a later stage, but it's easier without having coolant
    hoses and wires in the way. It also allows to install the subframe right
    away and get rid of the support bar.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060710e.Steering_pump.jpg" title="Steering pump" date="10.07.2006">
    Attach the steering pump with three 13 mm bolts. The bolt location is rather
    awkward, and in most cases there's only enough room for a 1/6 or even 1/12
    turn of a spanner at a time.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060710f.AC_compressor.jpg" title="A/C compressor" date="10.07.2006">
    Bolt the A/C compressor to the engine (three long 16 mm bolts). Plug
    the A/C clutch wire into its connector on the radiator. Attach oil cooler
    lines to the oil filter housing (22 mm wrench).
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060710g.Belt.jpg" title="Belt" date="10.07.2006">
    Lock the tensioner using a long 1/2" extension and a 2 mm pin
    and fit the accessory belt. The picture shows a short belt configuration
    with the middle idler pulley bypassed.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060710h.Airbox.jpg" title="Airbox" date="10.07.2006">
    Install the airbox and connect the ribbed hose to the turbo inlet pipe.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060710i.BPC.jpg" title="BPC" date="10.07.2006">
    Attach the boost pressure control valve to its proper location (two T25
    screws) and route the cable around the airbox.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060710j.ECU_harness.jpg" title="ECU harness" date="10.07.2006">
    Feed the ECU harness back through the hole in the firewall and plug it
    with the rubber grommet.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060710k.ECU.jpg" title="ECU" date="10.07.2006">
    Here's a custom Nordic stage4 ECU I'm using with my freshly built 2.3L
    engine.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060710l.ECU_harness.jpg" title="ECU harness" date="10.07.2006">
    Install the ECU (if you had it removed) and connect the wiring harnesses.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060710m.Fuel_lines.jpg" title="Fuel lines" date="10.07.2006">
    Re-connect the fuel lines, the fuel tank vent line to the throttle body
    and the EVAP valve harness.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060710n.Cruise_control.jpg" title="Cruise control" date="10.07.2006">
    Install the cruise control unit (two plastic 10 mm nuts).
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060710o.Throttle_cable.jpg" title="Throttle cable" date="10.07.2006">
    Attach the cruise control and accelerator cables to the arm on the throttle
    body. Bolt on the brake booster vacuum line.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060710p.MAP.jpg" title="MAP" date="10.07.2006">
    Connect the vacuum hose and the cable to the manifold pressure sensor
    (this picture shows the strut bar installed already).
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060710q.Lower_rad_hose.jpg" title="Lower rad hose" date="10.07.2006">
    Install the lower radiator hose. I'm using a newer style nose here,
    since it needs to clear the turbo hose to the cross-flow intercooler.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060710r.Radiator_hoses.jpg" title="Radiator hoses" date="10.07.2006">
    Attach the remaining coolant hoses: two heater core hoses, upper radiator
    hose, upper and lower expansion tank hoses.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060710s.Intercooler_hose.jpg" title="Intercooler hose" date="10.07.2006">
    Connect the intercooler inlet hose to the compressor housing on the turbo.
    Tighten the clamps well.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060710t.Delivery_pipe.jpg" title="Delivery pipe" date="10.07.2006">
    Install the delivery pipe from the intercooler to the throttle body.
    Tighten the 13 mm bolt that holds it to the engine head.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060710u.Downpipe.jpg" title="Downpipe" date="10.07.2006">
    Bolt the downpipe to the turbo and screw in the O2 sensor (or both if you
    have an OBD II car).
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060710v.Finished.jpg" title="Finished" date="10.07.2006">
    Complete the
    <a href="#/content/saab/20060211-saab-ng900-manual-transmission-installation">transmission-related
    steps</a>, fill the fluids and install the battery.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
</picture-set>
