<?xml version="1.0"?>
<picture-set title="Saab 9-5: Trunk Bag Holder">

  <description>
  <p>Saab accessory bag holder installation on a 1999 9-5. The holder offers
  a convenient way to keep grocery bags in place on those spirited drives
  home from the supermarket. It fits any 9-5 and 9-3 in both sedan and wagon
  trim. The installation is easy and straightforward, but requires some
  drilling. On a sedan you install it on the trunk ceiling, while on the wagon
  it should be attached to the underside of the cargo guard.</p>

  <h2>Tools:</h2>
  <ul>
    <li>Torx T25 screwdriver;</li>
    <li>drill with a 1/8" bit;</li>
    <li>centre punch and hammer.</li>
  </ul>
  </description>

  <picture name="20080914a.The_kit.jpg" title="The kit" date="14.09.2008">
    The kit comes with mounting hardware to install it on all supported car
    trims and includes assorted screws, nuts, washers and plastic screw caps.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20080914b.Inside_the_trunk.jpg" title="Inside the trunk" date="14.09.2008">
    Open the trunk, and optionally lower the rear seat. Find a suitable install
    location close to the outer edge of the trunk.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20080914c.Test_fitting.jpg" title="Test fitting" date="14.09.2008">
    The Saab manual suggests using only two screws on the 9-5, but they supply
    three, and it should really hold better if you add a third one in the
    center.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20080914d.Centre_punch.jpg" title="Centre punch" date="14.09.2008">
    Make sure the holes you marked are well away from the spot welds.
    Use a centre punch on the middle hole. Watch your fingers!
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20080914e.Drilling.jpg" title="Drilling" date="14.09.2008">
    Drill the middle hole using a 1/8" bit. Use a drill stop so it doesn't go
    through the parcel shelf and into the glass.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20080914f.Outer_holes.jpg" title="Outer holes" date="14.09.2008">
    Fit the middle screw and make sure you marked the outer holes correctly.
    Undo the screw and remove the holder.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20080914g.More_drilling.jpg" title="More drilling" date="14.09.2008">
    Punch and drill the outer holes. Again, take extra care as the metal you're
    drilling is quite thin.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20080914h.Installed.jpg" title="Installed" date="14.09.2008">
    Install the holder and tighten all three screws with star washers. The
    hooks should be aimed towards the opening of the trunk.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20080914i.Empty.jpg" title="Empty" date="14.09.2008">
    The hooks can slide left and right along the rail, and you can also
    fold them to about 45 degrees when they are not used.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20080914j.Bag.jpg" title="Bag" date="14.09.2008">
    While the rail is metal, the hooks itself are made of plastic, so they aren't
    strong enough to hold a heavy load. However, if the bags can stand the floor,
    they will be held in place just fine!
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
</picture-set>
