<?xml version="1.0"?>
<picture-set title="Saab NG900/9-3: New Style Shifter Linkage">

  <description>
  <p>A gearshift linkage upgrade on the 1996 Saab 900. The old linkage is replaced
  with a newer design, offering superior shifting feel and curing the difficulty
  of engaging certain gears. The updated linkage is found on 1997-1998 900 and
  1999-2002 9-3, Saab part #4626321. Should you come across this part on
  eBay or a local scrap yard, don't pass the opportunity, it's a worthwhile
  upgrade.</p>

  <p>To remove the linkage, do not forget to lock the transmission in fourth gear.
  For more information, see the
  <a href="#/content/saab/20050325-saab-ng900-shifter-alignment">shifter alignment
  procedure</a> and the
  <a href="#/content/saab/20050404-saab-ng900-old-style-shifter-linkage">old linkage
  removal instructions</a>. The only difference from the above procedures is
  that you need to raise the front end of the car.</p>
  
  <h2>Tools:</h2>
  <ul>
    <li>16 mm wrench;</li>
    <li>13 mm socket;</li>
    <li>Torx T40 socket;</li>
    <li>long socket extension;</li>
    <li>ratchet handle;</li>
    <li>torque wrench;</li>
    <li>two L-shaped 3 mm Allen keys;</li>
    <li>car ramps or jacks and stands.</li>
  </ul>
  </description>

  <picture name="20050808a.Seal_screws.jpg" title="Seal screws" date="08.08.2005">
    Lock the transmission in fourth gear and raise the front of the car.
    Since your car is likely a 94-96, the topmost screw on the differential seal
    retainer will probably be rusted or stuck. Take your time to soak it in
    rust solvent.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050808b.From_below.jpg" title="From below" date="08.08.2005">
    Undo the 13 mm nut securing the linkage to the gear rod at the firewall and
    move the shifter into third gear to pull it out of the linkage. Undo the
    bolt on the transmission end of the linkage and remove the linkage assembly.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050808c.Screw_undone.jpg" title="Screw undone" date="08.08.2005">
    Pull off the rubber boot and the plastic bushing from the engine bracket,
    you won't need them anymore. Unscrew the top bolt on the differential seal
    retainer (Torx T40).
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050808d.Stud.jpg" title="Stud" date="08.08.2005">
    Bolt on a new linkage stud in place of the old retainer screw (16 mm wrench).
    The stud has a little ball joint on its end.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050808e.Bracket.jpg" title="Bracket" date="08.08.2005">
    Inspect the bracket that connects the engine to the rear mount. There's a
    round lug on top of it, which used to be occupied by the plastic bushing
    of the old linkage. Cut the lug off.
    
    <image width="720" height="541" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050808f.Bracket_cut.jpg" title="Bracket cut" date="08.08.2005">
    This is a very tight location even for a hack saw. Be careful not to damage
    any hoses while cutting the bracket. Thankfully, it's made of aluminium,
    which is easy to cut.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050808g.Lug.jpg" title="Lug" date="08.08.2005">
    This little saw is almost as old as I am. My grandfather gave it to me when
    I was learning to work with mechanic's tools as a kid. It belongs to my son
    now. Today, it proved to be a perfect tool for the job ;P.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050808h.New_vs_old.jpg" title="New vs old" date="08.08.2005">
    The ball stud is still pictured attached to the linkage to show the complete
    assembly. It's the same stud you bolted to the differential a few minutes
    ago.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050808i.New_vs_old.jpg" title="New vs old" date="08.08.2005">
    The new linkage has a much more sophisticated design. The tilting movement
    is performed by a separate set of levers, while the base remains centered
    on the transmission rod and attached to the engine on another end.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050808j.New_vs_old.jpg" title="New vs old" date="08.08.2005">
    The result is a much greater movement accuracy and a more precise shifter
    feel.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050808k.Transmission_end.jpg" title="Transmission end" date="08.08.2005">
    Put the new linkage on both the transmission rod and the shifter connection
    rod at the firewall. Tighten the 13 mm bolt on the transmission side.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050808l.Connecting_pin.jpg" title="Connecting pin" date="08.08.2005">
    If you are installing a used linkage, check the condition of rubber
    bushings and clean inside the ball joint sockets on both ends of the
    connecting pin. Put some grease on the balls before installing it.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050808m.Shifter_end.jpg" title="Shifter end" date="08.08.2005">
    The pin connects the far end of the linkage to the ball stud on the
    differential body. It holds the linkage better than the old lug with a
    round plastic bush, while allowing sufficient freedom of movement.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050808n.Tightening.jpg" title="Tightening" date="08.08.2005">
    Finally, <a href="#/content/saab/20050325-saab-ng900-shifter-alignment">align
    the shifter position</a> and tighten the nut on the linkage. Lower the car
    on the ground and go for a test drive to check how the new linkage works.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
</picture-set>
