<?xml version="1.0"?>
<picture-set title="Saab NG900/9-3/9-5: Shifter Alignment">

  <description>
  <p>Shifter linkage alignment on a 1996 Saab 900 (should work for all
  1994-2002 NG900/9-3, and perhaps also 9-5 models). This procedure can cure the rubbery feel of
  the shifter, the difficulty to engage certain gears.</p>

  <h2>Tools:</h2>
  <ul>
    <li>13 mm socket;</li>
    <li>two L-shaped 3 mm Allen keys;</li>
    <li>long socket extension;</li>
    <li>torque wrench;</li>
    <li>ratchet handle.</li>
  </ul>
  </description>

  <picture name="20050325a.4th_gear.jpg" title="4th gear" date="25.03.2005">
    Car on the ground, engine off. Engage fourth gear.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050325b.Plug.jpg" title="Plug" date="25.03.2005">
    Locate the small plastic plug on top of the gearbox and pull the plug out.
    Be careful not to break the plug: it's thin and long (about an inch long).
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050325c.Allen_key.jpg" title="Allen key" date="25.03.2005">
    Insert a locking pin into the opening. A 3 mm L-shaped Allen key works well,
    but it has to be plenty long to enter the pinhole in the shifter rod - a couple of inches deep.
    With the key inserted, make sure that you cannot change gears anymore.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050325d.Clamp.jpg" title="Clamp" date="25.03.2005">
    Locate the clamp that holds the gear rod to the gearbox linkage (close to
    the firewall). There is a 13 mm nut on top of it.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050325e.Extension.jpg" title="Extension" date="25.03.2005">
    Slacken the nut on the clamp. You will need a very long socket extension to
    reach it.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050325f.Shifter.jpg" title="Shifter" date="25.03.2005">
    Pull the gear lever boot up. Tilt the shifter around in all directions to find a
    centered 4th gear position with the bump stop almost touching the reverse catch. Be careful as moving the
    shifter too far into the third gear position will completely disconnect the rod from
    the linkage. It's hard to see, but you should eventually align the pinhole in the
    linkage rod with the hole in the shifter housing.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050325h.Locking_pin.jpg" title="Locking pin" date="25.03.2005">
    Once aligned, insert a second pin to lock the rod position. With both ends of the
    rod aligned and locked, tighten the nut on the linkage clamp
    to 15.5 ft-lbs. Remove the locking pin from the transmission and plug the
    hole. Remove the pin from the shifter housing. Test the gearshift operation.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
</picture-set>
