<?xml version="1.0"?>
<picture-set title="Saab NG900/9-3: Downpipe With Sport Cat">

  <description>
  <p>The downpipe installation procedure for a 1996 Saab 900 (also applies to the
  1999-2002 9-3 models). The pipe is supplied by Jak Stoll.
  It is a 3" aluminized steel downpipe with a Magnaflow catalitic converter,
  one of the cheaper options available back in 2005.</p>

  <h2>Tools:</h2>
  <ul>
    <li>ramps or jack stands;</li>
    <li>13 mm socket or wrench: downpipe to turbo nuts, exhaust clamp bolts
      (a 1/2" worked better in my case due to a tighter fit);</li>
    <li>7/8" open end wrench: O2 sensors;</li>
    <li>flat screwdriver: to release the tab on the O2 sensor connector;</li>
    <li>a heavy tool or a length of pipe to bend exhaust hangers;</li>
    <li>wire brush: to clean the joint between the flex pipe and the cat;</li>
    <li>exhaust sealant: to seal the joint between the flex pipe and the cat;</li>
    <li>torque wrench.</li>
  </ul>
  </description>

  <picture name="20050119a.Downpipe.jpg" title="Downpipe" date="19.01.2005">
    The pipe and the box it arrived in. It was carefully cushioned
    by an immense amount of cardboard and other packing material ;).
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050119b.Downpipe.jpg" title="Downpipe" date="19.01.2005">
    Surprisingly, the pipe weights less than
    you would expect from such a large piece of metal. It's actually lighter
    than the stock part, despite the bigger size.
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050119c.Front_O2_sensor.jpg" title="Front O2 sensor" date="19.01.2005">
    You need to raise the front of the car to do the job (I used ramps).
    First, unscrew the front O2 sensor using an open ended 7/8" wrench.
    A bit of solvent would not hurt first. You might try to attempt the rear
    O2 sensor too, but there's very little clearance around it, so it's
    easier to take care of it later.
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050119d.Exhaust_clamp.jpg" title="Exhaust clamp" date="19.01.2005">
    Undo the bolts on the clamp that connects the intermediate flex pipe to the
    catalitic converter. The bolts are 13 mm or 1/2". The joint would likely
    be sealed, so you will have use a hammer to break the bond after the clamp
    is off. Be careful not to put too much strain on the flex pipe.
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050119e.Front_pipe.jpg" title="Front pipe" date="19.01.2005">
    Unbolt the front section of the downpipe from the turbo. Two nuts are
    accessible from the top, and one from below. A 13 mm socket was a loose fit,
    so I used a 1/2" to escape rounding the nuts off. Two were OK, one was
    very tight, but a bit of solvent did the job.
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050119f.O2_sensor_wire.jpg" title="O2 sensor wire" date="19.01.2005">
    Before lowering the pipe to the floor, unplug the rear O2 sensor (the middle
    connector on this picture). Remove the lower part of the connector from the
    housing and pull it down to let it hang free.
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050119g.Rear_O2_sensor.jpg" title="Rear O2 sensor" date="19.01.2005">
    Lower the downpipe with the cat to the floor (the length of the rear O2
    sensor wire will allow that) and remove the sensor using an open ended
    socket or a 7/8" spanner. The pipe is free now.
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050119h.Old_and_new.jpg" title="Old and new" date="19.01.2005">
    The old downpipe compared to the new one. The flex joint on the old pipe
    rusted so much that it almost separated from the lower section (no wonder I
    had such a leak), and it only took me a slight pull to tear it off
    completely.
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050119i.Hangers.jpg" title="Hangers" date="19.01.2005">
    The hangers were made too wide and took some time to adjust. This was the
    biggest hassle: you need to put the pipe back on the car after each
    adjustment to check if everything fits properly.
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050119j.Fitting.jpg" title="Fitting" date="19.01.2005">
    Once you're happy with the position of the pipe, you can start putting
    everything back together. This is a good time to clean the O2 sensor heads
    with carb cleaner and check if the holes in the sensors are clogged with
    soot. Fit the rear O2 sensor before putting the hangers on. Put some
    antiseize on the threads to make the future removal
    easier. Tightening torque for the sensor: 41 ft-lbs.
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050119k.Front_pipe.jpg" title="Front pipe" date="19.01.2005">
    Once the hangers are on, fit the front end of the downpipe to the turbo.
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050119l.Front_pipe.jpg" title="Front pipe" date="19.01.2005">
    Make sure the the nuts are on evenly, tighten at 18.5 ft-lbs.
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050119m.Exhaust_joint.jpg" title="Exhaust joint" date="19.01.2005">
    Clean the end of the flex pipe with a wire brush and fit it to the
    pipe from the catalitic converter.
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050119n.Sealant.jpg" title="Sealant" date="19.01.2005">
    Apply some exhaust sealant on the joint.
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050119o.Exhaust_clamp.jpg" title="Exhaust clamp" date="19.01.2005">
    Put the clamp on and tighten the bolts to 15 ft-lbs.
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050119p.Front_O2_sensor.jpg" title="Front O2 sensor" date="19.01.2005">
    Fit the front O2 sensor (also 41 ft-lbs, and don't forget the anti-seize),
    clean up and take the car for a test drive.
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
</picture-set>
