<?xml version="1.0"?>
<picture-set title="Saab 9-3/9-5: PCV Fix Kit">

  <description>
  <p>The crank case ventilation fix kit installation. The fix is applied according
  to the Saab service bulletin 210-2417 from Oct'2003, and intended to
  prevent potential oil leaks and decrease oil consumption. The kit is
  supplied by Saab, part #5962428 (Canadian part #30593216).</p>

  <p><b>UPDATE:</b> This fix has been discontinued by Saab as of 14.1.2005 after
  they received numerous complaints about increased oil consumption. If you
  have performed this modification, you need to return the car to the original
  configuration (or at least move the small vent hose from the oil filler
  pipe back to the nipple on the valve cover). A new kit is available from Saab.</p>
  </description>

  <picture name="20040919a.From_below.jpg" title="From below" date="19.09.2004">
    A view from under the car through the front subframe opening. The generator
    cable and the intake manifold stay get in the way, feel free to remove them.
    Disconnect the negative cable on the battery before doing that.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20040919b.Oil_trap_bolts.jpg" title="Oil trap bolts" date="19.09.2004">
    The oil trap comes next. All bolts here are 13 mm. Disconnect two upper
    hoses and one lower hose before pulling the oil trap out.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20040919c.Oil_trap.jpg" title="Oil trap" date="19.09.2004">
    Theoretically, you should pull the hoses out while the oil trap is still on
    the car, but I've found it easier to do them afterwards.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20040919d.Small_hole.jpg" title="Small hole" date="19.09.2004">
    The turbo inlet hose socket has a plug with a small hole in it, about 3 mm.
    The service bulletin suggests drilling it up to 10 mm.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20040919e.Drilling.jpg" title="Drilling" date="19.09.2004">
    Keep the oil trap upside down while drilling to prevent the shavings from
    getting in. Blow clean and wipe it throroughly afterwards.
    
    <image width="540" height="720" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20040919f.Big_hole.jpg" title="Big hole" date="19.09.2004">
    The hole is much bigger now. Install the oil trap back and connect the lower
    hose. Don't forget to reinstall the parts you removed to get to the oil trap.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20040919g.Oil_filler_pipe.jpg" title="Oil filler pipe" date="19.09.2004">
    The next step is to install a nipple on the oil filler pipe. Remove the
    dipstick and unbolt the pipe with a 10 mm socket.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20040919h.20_mm.jpg" title="20 mm" date="19.09.2004">
    The hole should be drilled 20 mm up from the ridge in the pipe, 135 degrees
    from the lip with a mounting hole.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20040919i.More_drilling.jpg" title="More drilling" date="19.09.2004">
    Use a 7 mm drilling bit, remove all the shavings and wipe the pipe after
    you're done.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20040919j.Nipple.jpg" title="Nipple" date="19.09.2004">
    Fit the nipple so the threads just become visible on the inner side.
    The small hole on the nipple should point down.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20040919k.Hoses.jpg" title="Hoses" date="19.09.2004">
    Locate the hose that used to go from the small nipple on the fat hose from
    the camshaft cover to the check valve. It should now be connected to the
    nipple on the oil filler pipe.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20040919l.Hoses.jpg" title="Hoses" date="19.09.2004">
    There's little clearance near the filler pipe nipple, so it might be
    easier to disconnect the hose from the check valve and connect it to the
    nipple first. Pull it between the fuel rail and the wiring harness and
    reconnect it to the check valve then.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20040919m.Cutting_the_hose.jpg" title="Cutting the hose" date="19.09.2004">
    The thick hose that goes from the turbo inlet pipe to the oil trap has to
    be cut at the height level with intake manifold.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20040919n.Check_valve.jpg" title="Check valve" date="19.09.2004">
    Insert the check valve so the arrow on it points upwards when the hose is
    installed. You may notice that the valve is harder to blow through in a
    certain direction, this is supposed to facilitate a different air flow
    within the circuit.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20040919o.Plug.jpg" title="Plug" date="19.09.2004">
    Plug the small nipple on the camshaft cover hose with a cap supplied in
    the kit and install the two remaining hoses on the car.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20040919p.Finished.jpg" title="Finished" date="19.09.2004">
    Here's a summary of changes: a bigger hole in the oil trap, a check valve
    on the turbo inlet hose, a nipple on the oil filler pipe and a new
    attachment of the small circuit hose.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
</picture-set>
