<?xml version="1.0"?>
<picture-set title="Saab 9-5: Auto-Dimming Rear View Mirror">

  <description>
  <p>Auto-dimming mirror installation on a Saab 9-5.</p>

  <p>Some cars came with it,
  some without. You can find it in eBay, on scrap yards, or buy it from Saab.
  It's a direct replacement, you just need to provide the power for the mirror.
  Later cars have an accessory wiring harness to plug the mirror in. If
  the harness is not there, you will need to do the wiring yourself.
  The only tool required is a Torx/flat screwdriver from the trunk.</p>

  <p>If you need to quickly test the mirror, power it up by applying 12V between
  the red wire (pin 5) and the black wire (pin 8). Then cover the sensor on the
  back of the mirror and point a flashlight or another source of the bright
  light at the glass. It takes about 3-4 second to dim, giving the
  image a greenish hue.</p>

  <p>The wiring used in this guide is specified by the Saab manual for early
  style mirrors with no compass and homelink device. It uses an non-switched
  power source. Later style mirrors draw more current, so you need a switched
  power source (e.g. a sunroof lead) to turn the mirror off with the car and
  prevent it from draining your battery.</p>
  </description>

  <picture name="20071007a.Lamp_cover.jpg" title="Lamp cover" date="07.10.2007">
    Use a flat screwdriver to pry off the lamp cover.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20071007b.Screw.jpg" title="Screw" date="07.10.2007">
    Undo the Torx screw holding the housing.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20071007c.Connectors.jpg" title="Connectors" date="07.10.2007">
    Unplug the connectors for the microphone and the temperature sensor.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20071007d.Mirror.jpg" title="Mirror" date="07.10.2007">
    Unscrew the mirror from the ceiling and remove it from the car.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20071007e.Mirrors.jpg" title="Mirrors" date="07.10.2007">
    The auto-dimming mirror is slightly thicker, has a sensor on the back,
    and a wiring harness coming out of it.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20071007f.Wiring.jpg" title="Wiring" date="07.10.2007">
    Attach a 12V power lead to the red wire (pin 5).
    Attach a ground lead to the black wire (pin 8).
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20071007g.Attached.jpg" title="Attached" date="07.10.2007">
    Screw the new mirror to the ceiling. Hide the wires under the headliner.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20071007h.Harness.jpg" title="Harness" date="07.10.2007">
    Unplug the grey harness in the centre of the housing, keep the new wires near.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20071007i.Connected.jpg" title="Connected" date="07.10.2007">
    Tap the power lead into the red/white wire (pin 5), and the ground
    lead into the black wire (pin 8). Re-connect the harness.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20071007j.Done.jpg" title="Done" date="07.10.2007">
    Install the lamp cluster housing, tighten the screw and fit the lamp cover.
    Wait until it gets dark and go for a drive to check your mirror on the road.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
</picture-set>
