<?xml version="1.0"?>
<picture-set title="Saab 9-5: Blend Door Repair">

  <description>

  <p>ACC blend door repair on a 1999 Saab 9-5.</p>

  <p>If your air vents blow cold in the winter, or hot in the summer, if the
  A/C calibration shows error code 08 on the climate control display, then you
  probably have this problem. It's very common, especially on early 9-5s.</p>

  <p>The climate control system has an air mixing flap on each side.
  They mix cold and hot air, so the temperature can be controlled
  separately on the driver and passenger side. Each flap is operated by
  a small stepping motor. The range of movement is limited by a short
  plastic stop arm. Its function is critical, because the mixing flap can
  cross its path with other moving parts if misaligned, and cause
  irreparable damage.</p>

  <p>The ACC can detect when the stop arm is broken and stop the motor.
  Timely repair is important to prevent further damage. Don't put it off
  after the problem presented itself. A cracked stop arm or a broken
  shaft tip can be easily repaired. In more severe cases, the may snap inside
  the unit, which can only be fixed by removing the ACC module from the car
  and taking it apart, which is extremely labour intensive. There are
  various repair kits available from many online Saab parts retailers.</p>

  <p>The only tools you need for the job is a pair of Torx and Phillips screwdrivers.</p>

  </description>

  <picture name="20091012a.Driver_footwell.jpg" title="Driver footwell" date="12.10.2009">
    Undo the Torx screws holding the trim in the driver's footwell.
    <image width="800" height="535" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20091012b.OBD_connector.jpg" title="OBD connector" date="12.10.2009">
    Unscrew the OBD-II connector from the trim panel.
    <image width="800" height="535" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20091012c.Left_motor.jpg" title="Left motor" date="12.10.2009">
    Locate the left stepping motor (it has a large "L" on it). Unplug the
    connector and any other wires in your way. Undo two screws holding the
    motor and pull it out.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20091012d.Shaft_position.jpg" title="Shaft position" date="12.10.2009">
    Make sure the notch on the shaft is pointed upwards. If it's not, plug
    the motor connector back in and run the ACC calibration until the shaft
    is positioned correctly.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20091012e.Broken_arm.jpg" title="Broken arm" date="12.10.2009">
    Old style green plastic stop arms often crack at the base, allowing the
    shaft to spin freely. Newer style white arms have this end reinforced,
    however they sometimes crack at the upper notch instead.
    <image width="800" height="535" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20091012f.Arm_removed.jpg" title="Arm removed" date="12.10.2009">
    Remove the stop arm. Inspect the yellow shaft, make sure it turns and is
    not broken. You can peek through the lower vent, or remove the vent
    completely for easier access to the inner part of the shaft.
    <image width="800" height="535" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20091012g.New_vs_old.jpg" title="New vs old" date="12.10.2009">
    This replacement arm was fabricated by my relative who works at the machine
    shop. It's made out of military grade aluminium, very light and strong.
    There are similar aftermarket replacement arms sold online.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20091012h.Alumimium_arm.jpg" title="Aluminium arm" date="12.10.2009">
    Install the new arm. It will be seated tight, so push it in carefully -
    all the way until the catch clicks. Before re-installing the motor, make 
    sure the shaft profile is aligned with the notch on the motor shaft.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20091012i.Carpet_clips.jpg" title="Carpet clips" date="12.10.2009">
    The passenger side is less prone to failure, but I decided to replace both
    as I had extra parts. Start by pulling the clips out of the carpet trim.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20091012j.Lower_trim.jpg" title="Lower trim" date="12.10.2009">
    Next, undo the four screws holding the lower plastic panel.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20091012k.Glovebox_screws.jpg" title="Glovebox screws" date="12.10.2009">
    Unscrew the lower edge of the glove box.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20091012l.Upper_screws.jpg" title="Upper screws" date="12.10.2009">
    Open the glovebox and undo the remaining screws along the top.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20091012m.Glovebox_removed.jpg" title="Glovebox removed" date="12.10.2009">
    Pull the glovebox, disconnect the vent hose and the electrical connector.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20091012n.Right_motor.jpg" title="Right motor" date="12.10.2009">
    Locate the stepping motor with a large "R" on it, unhook the wires and
    unscrew the motor.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20091012o.Original_arm.jpg" title="Original arm" date="12.10.2009">
    The passenger side arm is connected to a metal rod that operates additional
    vents on the floor.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20091012p.Arm_removed.jpg" title="Arm removed" date="12.10.2009">
    Unhook the rod and pull the stop arm off the shaft. Inspect for damage. My
    arm was starting to develop a crack at the upper notch. 
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20091012q.Rod_fitting.jpg" title="Rod fitting" date="12.10.2009">
    Remove the soft plastic rod bushing from the old arm and insert it into the
    new arm.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20091012r.Installed.jpg" title="Installed" date="12.10.2009">
    Installation is the reverse of removal. Once everything is done, start
    the car and run the ACC calibration by pressing AUTO+OFF.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
</picture-set>
