<?xml version="1.0"?>
<picture-set title="Saab NG900/9-3: Adjustable Short Shifter">

  <description>
  <p>Adjustable short shifter rod installation on the 1996 Saab 900.
  Parts from the now defunct MP Performance.</p>

  <p>To remove the shifter housing, first lock the transmission in fourth gear
  and undo the clamp that connects the linkage to the gearshift rod as
  described in
  <a href="#/content/saab/20050325-saab-ng900-shifter-alignment">the shifter alignment
  procedure</a>.</p>

  <p><b>Update:</b> the shifter has been removed a couple of
  months later due to inadequate performance: the shortening was barely
  noticeable, and the ball kept getting loose despite the locking screw,
  which introduced unwanted slop into the shifting feel. If you plan to
  install this shifter, I'd recommend removing the reverse lockup and
  putting the ball on Loctite or another adhesive for proper effect.</p>

  <p><b>Update 2:</b>
  the adjustable shifter rod used in this guide is no longer produced, an
  alternative (and improved) do-it-yourself modification is
  <a href="#/content/saab/20070617-saab-ng900-short-shifter">available here</a>.
  Both options are inferior to the amazing shifter housing by
  <a href="https://www.genuinesaab.com">Taliaferro.</a></p>

  <h2>Tools:</h2>
  <ul>
    <li>13 mm socket: linkage clamp;</li>
    <li>13 mm wrench: gearshift rod;</li>
    <li>10 mm socket: centre console and shifter housing;</li>
    <li>long socket extension;</li>
    <li>ratchet handle;</li>
    <li>torque wrench;</li>
    <li>flat screwdriver;</li>
    <li>Torx T25 screwdriver;</li>
    <li>two L-shaped 3 mm Allen keys: linkage lock;</li>
    <li>2 mm hex key: shifter adjustment;</li>
    <li>strap wrench and C-clamp: knob removal;</li>
    <li>needle-nose pliers.</li>
  </ul>
  </description>

  <picture name="20050404a.Driver_side.jpg" title="Driver side" date="04.04.2005">
    Remove the lower panel on the driver side (two Torx T25 screws).
    Push the panel towards the front of the car to release the tabs for removal.
    The spring cleaning is due on this car ;).
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050404b.Passenger_side.jpg" title="Passenger side" date="04.04.2005">
    Remove the lower panel on the passenger side (two Torx T25 screws).
    Push the panel towards the front of the car to release the tabs for removal.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050404c.Ashtray.jpg" title="Ashtray" date="04.04.2005">
    Take out the ashtray on the back of the centre console (it just pops out).
    Undo the Torx T25 screw under the ash tray and remove the cover with ACC
    vents and storage compartment lid (pull it up to remove).
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050404d.Nuts.jpg" title="Nuts" date="04.04.2005">
    Undo two 10 mm nuts securing the centre console to the floor.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050404e.Ignition_cover.jpg" title="Ignition cover" date="04.04.2005">
    On the 900, just pry up the ignition lock cover with a small screwdriver.
    On the 9-3, the cover will be bigger and there's a PCB with key antenna
    under it. The antenna can be removed by twisting it sideways and pulling
    it up or by releasing the tabs using a small screwdriver. There's a
    connector at the bottom.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050404f.Window_switches.jpg" title="Window switches" date="04.04.2005">
    Press the tab on the window switch cluster and push it from below through
    the handbrake opening.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050404g.Cover.jpg" title="Cover" date="04.04.2005">
    Pry off the larger cover over the ignition lock.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050404h.Screws.jpg" title="Screws" date="04.04.2005">
    Remove two screws holding the front of the console to the shifter housing
    (Torx T25). Apparently, the previous owner was a huge fan of Cola.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050404i.Light_switch.jpg" title="Light switch" date="04.04.2005">
    Pull out the light switch (if equipped) and disconnect the wires.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050404j.Heater_switch.jpg" title="Heater switch" date="04.04.2005">
    Pull out the rear seat heater switch (if equipped) and disconnect the wires.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050404k.Knobs_out.jpg" title="Knobs out" date="04.04.2005">
    The ACC panel and the seat heater switches come out of the panel, allowing
    you to unplug the wires. The ACC fan has a cap that comes off, and then
    you need to push the fan inside the dash. There are also two connectors
    on the back of the lighter outlet.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050404l.Tabs.jpg" title="Tabs" date="04.04.2005">
    Locate two tabs on the top where the ACC panel was, and remove them (push
    the knob in the middle further in to release the lock). Remove the rear
    half of the centre console (disconnect the tabs from the front part and
    pull it up). Pop the shifter boot from the console, pull it up onto the
    shifter knob and remove the front half of the console.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050404m.Vent.jpg" title="Vent" date="04.04.2005">
    Remove the air vent.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050404n.Housing.jpg" title="Housing" date="04.04.2005">
    Undo four bolts holding the shifter housing to the floor (10 mm socket).
    The clamp on the gearshift linkage should be loosened at this point
    (see <a href="/Auto/20050325.Saab_NG900_Shifter_Alignment/">the shifter
    alignment procedure</a>).
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050404o.Wires.jpg" title="Wires" date="04.04.2005">
    Unplug the clips attaching the wires on the passenger side.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050404p.Harness.jpg" title="Harness" date="04.04.2005">
    Turn the housing on the side and disconnect the ignition lock harness
    (use a flat screwdriver to release the tabs on each side).
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050404q.Removed.jpg" title="Removed" date="04.04.2005">
    With the clamp on the linkage undone, pull the housing, and it should come
    right out. Take your time to clean up inside the console.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050404r.Underside.jpg" title="Underside" date="04.04.2005">
    Undo the bolt at the base of the shifter to detach the long gear selector
    shaft (13 mm wrench). The big black plate next to the base of the rod is
    the reverse lockout mechanism. You can remove it to further shorten
    the shifter action.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050404s.Spring.jpg" title="Spring" date="04.04.2005">
    Use needle-nose pliers to remove the spring, then turn the plastic retainer
    counter-clockwise.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050404t.Stick.jpg" title="Stick" date="04.04.2005">
    Here's the shifter just out of the housing. The plastic gaiter and the boot
    are attached to the knob.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050404u.Knob.jpg" title="Knob" date="04.04.2005">
    Use a strap wrench to twist the knob and break the bond. In my case,
    the knob cover came off first ;). Once the knob is off, remove the knob and
    everything that's attached to it, and put it on the new shifter rod.
    Note the position of the gear markings on the knob.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050404v.New_vs_old.jpg" title="New vs old" date="04.04.2005">
    The new rod next to the old one. You can see that there is not much
    difference in the ball position. With the reverse lockout intact, there
    is actually very little room for adjustment. Both the rod and the ball are
    made of aluminium, and there are two ball bearings at the base (vs
    the plastic biushing on the OEM shifter).
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050404w.Assembled.jpg" title="Assembled" date="04.04.2005">
    Assemble the shifter with fresh grease and bolt on the selector shaft.
    Install the housing back on the car, tighten the bolts and perform
    <a href="#/content/saab/20050325-saab-ng900-shifter-alignment">the alignment
    procedure</a>. You should feel the shorter throws and the marginally heavier
    feel of the shifter.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20050404x.Adjustment.jpg" title="Adjustment" date="04.04.2005">
    The shifter can be adjusted directly on the car, even after everything is
    put back together. All you need to do is pull the boot up, release the
    locking screw on the ball with a 2 mm hex screwdriver and wiggle it until
    the ball rotates to the desired position. Make sure you can reach all gears
    without the rod rubbing against anything inside the housing. Tighten the
    locking screw afterwards.
    
    <image width="720" height="540" />
  </picture>
</picture-set>
