<?xml version="1.0"?>
<picture-set title="Saab NG900: Rear Springs, Intrax vs Eibach">

  <description>
  <p>A comparison of Intrax and Eibach rear springs on the 1995 Saab 900 
  convertible.</p>

  <p>Intrax springs have a barrel design, where it has a number of softer coils
  which are always fully compressed to compensate for a shorter length and
  provide some preload when the car is up in the air. The downside is that
  there's only a couple of coils left uncompressed, which limits the suspension
  travel, and the ride suffers a lot. Eibach, on the other hand, uses a
  progressive design, where the thickess and stiffness of the coils varies
  through the spring length. It employs all of the coils at various stages of
  the suspension travel, which allows for a much more comfortable ride without
  having to make the spring too soft to sacrifice the handling.</p>
  </description>

  <picture name="20061014a.Intrax.jpg" title="Intrax" date="14.10.2006">
    You can see how the spring is almost fully tight under the weight of the
    car, except for the last coil. There's virtually no room for the spring to
    compress further, which means the car will bottom out on every bump.
    I also had to use a thickness spacer to make up for lost ride height.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20061014b.Bump_stop.jpg" title="Bump stop" date="14.10.2006">
    Here's a new trick for removing the bump stop, suggested by Jose De Jesus.
    Compress the rubber piece with a hose clamp, spray it with some soap
    water, and it pops right out.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20061014c.Off_the_car.jpg" title="Off the car" date="14.10.2006">
    The differences in the spring design are apparent from this picture. The
    quality differs a lot too - both springs were on the car for about a year.
    The Intrax is all rusted and peeling, while the Eibach still looks like new.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20061014d.Eibach.jpg" title="Eibach" date="14.10.2006">
    A new spring installed (the installation procedure is described in
    <A HREF="#/content/saab/20070511-saab-ng900-eibach-springs-from-a-9-3">this article</A>).
    From the looks of it, it appears that the ride
    is going to be much more comfortable.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20061014e.Completed.jpg" title="Completed" date="14.10.2006">
    Installation complete. The ride height looks just perfect.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20061014f.Intrax_vs_Eibach.jpg" title="Intrax vs Eibach" date="14.10.2006">
    Here's a direct comparison of both springs installed in the same corner.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
</picture-set>
