<?xml version="1.0"?>
<picture-set title="9-5: Blower Motor Repair">

  <description>
  Climate control fan motor repair on a 1999 Saab 9-5. Blower motors tend
  to fail with age, but they are easy to inspect and service. More often
  than not, they can be brought back to life, which saves quite a bit of
  money (new motors are expensive). Worn brushes and dirty rotor surface are
  among the top causes of motor failures.
  </description>

  <picture name="20060204a.Hood.jpg" title="Hood" date="04.02.2006">
    The motor is located right below the windshield. Start by opening
    the hood and removing the wipers. If they are stuck, use a gear puller
    or another suitable tool.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060204b.Wipers_removed.jpg" title="Wipers removed" date="04.02.2006">
    Pull the rubber strip along the firewall. Take out plastic screws in the
    corners, and remove the cover completely. Be careful not to brake the
    plastic clips holding it to the lower edge of the windshield.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060204c.Cover.jpg" title="Cover" date="04.02.2006">
    Lift the plastic cover in the middle. It's thin, and you can easily
    bend it to pull out.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060204d.Wiper_motor.jpg" title="Wiper motor" date="04.02.2006">
    Unplug the wiper motor harness, undo three 10 mm bolts and remove the
    motor assembly.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060204e.Fan_housing.jpg" title="Fan housing" date="04.02.2006">
    There's a plastic frame around the fan housing. It's fastened by two
    latches.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060204f.Fan_cover.jpg" title="Fan cover" date="04.02.2006">
    Detach the cable from the fan cover, remove the screws and lift the cover.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060204g.Fan.jpg" title="Fan" date="04.02.2006">
    The fan is permanently attached to the motor, so you will have to remove
    them together.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060204h.Fan_removal.jpg" title="Fan removal" date="04.02.2006">
    Wiggle the motor out. If the fit is too tight, unbolt the windshield wiper
    bracket in the middle.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060204i.Motor.jpg" title="Motor" date="04.02.2006">
    Unscrew the motor cover. It's not totally necessary, but it will give you
    more room to inspect the motor.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060204j.Motor_cover_off.jpg" title="Motor cover off" date="04.02.2006">
    Unhook the metal clips that hold the brushes. Be careful, there's a spring
    inside.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060204k.Brush.jpg" title="Brush" date="04.02.2006">
    Pull the brushes and inspect them. This picture shows a brush at 40% of its
    original size. If yours are worn too much, consider replacing them. Your
    nearby alternator shop is a good place to start.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060204l.Rotor_cleaning.jpg" title="Rotor cleaning" date="04.02.2006">
    Clean the rotor contact surface. Cotton swabs and electric contact cleaner
    is a good start. If the rotor surface is scored, use a fine grinding bit
    for your Dremel. Clean and sand the brushes too.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060204m.Testing.jpg" title="Testing" date="04.02.2006">
    Connect the motor and turn on the climate control to verify the operation.
    The installation is the reverse of removal.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
</picture-set>
