<?xml version="1.0"?>
<picture-set title="Saab NG900/9-3: Fuel Filter">

  <description>
  <p>Fuel filter replacement on a 1995 Saab 900. The procedure is the same for
  all 1994-1998 900 and 1999-2002 9-3. 9-5s are also very similar, except that
  the filter is covered by a plastic shield.</p>

  <p>Before starting the work, start the engine and pull the fuel pump fuse.
  The engine will eventually use up all fuel in the lines, choke and stall.
  This is needed to release the fuel pressure and prevent the petrol from
  fountaining from the banjo fittings when you unscrew the filter.</p>
  
  <h2>Tools:</h2>
  <ul>
    <li>27 mm wrench: inlet side of the filter;</li>
    <li>22 mm wrench: exit side of the filter;</li>
    <li>19 mm socket: inlet banjo bolt;</li>
    <li>17 mm socket: exit banjo bolt;</li>
    <li>Torx T30 socket: clamp screw;</li>
    <li>car ramps or jack and stands.</li>
  </ul>
  </description>

  <picture name="20060711a.Under_the_car.jpg" title="Under the car" date="11.07.2006">
    Jack up the right side of the car and locate the filter under the rear door,
    next to the fuel tank. After 11 years and 156K km of
    operation the original filter doesn't look particularly attractive.
    Prepare a pan to catch the fuel that will leak out after you unbolt
    the filter.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060711b.Old_filter.jpg" title="Old filter" date="11.07.2006">
    There's a banjo bolt on each side of the filter. To undo these bolts,
    hold the filter with a spanner wrench and turn the banjo head with a
    ratchet. The fuel will start dripping right after you release the tension,
    a total of 200 ml or more may come out. Unscrew the clamp and remove
    the filter.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060711c.New_filter.jpg" title="New filter" date="11.07.2006">
    A new Bosch filter comes with plastic plugs on both ends to prevent the
    dirt from getting in during shipping. Often when you remove the bolts,
    tiny rubber pieces of old washers get stuck to them. Clean them well -
    you don't want this stuff in your injectors. Get new washers too, you
    need four in total.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060711d.Installed.jpg" title="Installed" date="11.07.2006">
    Install the new filter, fit the clamp and tighten both banjo bolts to 16
    ft-lbs. The engine might take a bit longer to start for the first time,
    but should be fine afterwards.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
</picture-set>
