<?xml version="1.0"?>
<picture-set title="Saab NG900/9-3/9-5: 308 mm Front Brake Upgrade">

  <description>
  <p>Front brake upgrade on a 1995 Saab 900. The guide also applies to all
  NG900 (1994-1998), 9-3 (1999-2002) and 9-5 Linear and Arc models with
  288 mm front rotors (1999+). See the
  <a href="#/content/saab/20070602-saab-9-5-front-brakes">regular brake service guide</a> for
  general suggestions and bed-in procedures.</p>

  <p>The upgrade is achieved by installing 308 mm rotors and matching calipers.
  The rotors are readily available from many retailers, and the calipers can
  be found from wreckers or purchased new from Saab. Suitable models to source
  the calipers from include 1999-2002 9-3 Viggen and 2000-2001 9-5 Aero. If
  you're upgrading a 2002+ 9-5 Linear, you need the calipers from a 2002+ Aero
  or Arc.</p>

  <p>Early 900s (1994-1996) will also benefit from a larger pad size, as the
  original pads on these cars were smaller. Newer cars have the same calipers
  and pads as the Aero, but will require wider support brackets to accommodate
  larger rotors. Finding the brackets separately, however, might prove more
  difficult than complete calipers.</p>

  <p>Another word of caution concerns the hub size on the early 900s (1994-1996
  again). These cars came with slightly larger hubs, which do not fit into
  newer rotors. Measure your hubs and rotors before deciding on the upgrade.
  The old rotors had an inner diameter of 5.5", while the newer ones
  are 5.25". If your
  hubs are too large, you can either cut 5 mm off the rim on a lathe or
  find a pair of hubs from a newer car. Oddly enough, my 1995 900 had small
  hubs that were a perfect fit for new style rotors.</p>

  <h2>Tools and supplies:</h2>
  <ul>
    <li>Torx E20 socket: caliper bolts (2002+ 9-5);</li>
    <li>18 mm socket: caliper bolts (1999-2001 9-5);</li>
    <li>17 mm socket: wheel bolts;</li>
    <li>11 mm socket: brake line banjo bolt;</li>
    <li>10 mm Allen socket: caliper bolts (NG900/9-3);</li>
    <li>7 mm Allen socket: caliper guide pins;</li>
    <li>5 mm Allen socket: rotor index screw;</li>
    <li>Torx T25 socket: dust shield screws;</li>
    <li>impact driver, drill and screw extractor (optional);</li>
    <li>wire brush;</li>
    <li>torque wrench;</li>
    <li>anti-seize grease;</li>
    <li>fresh brake fluid and bleeder;</li>
    <li>car jack and stands.</li>
  </ul>
  </description>

  <picture name="20070809a.Wheel_off.jpg" title="Wheel off" date="09.08.2007">
    Raise the car and secure it on jack stands. Take off the front wheel.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070809b.Index_screw_and_spring.jpg" title="Index screw and spring" date="09.08.2007">
    Remove the caliper retaining spring and undo the rotor index screw.
    If the screw is stuck, you might have to resort to
    <a href="#/content/saab/20050709-saab-9-5-rear-brakes-fixed">more serious measures</a>.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070809c.Guide_pins.jpg" title="Guide pins" date="09.08.2007">
    Take the plastic caps off the guide pins and unscrew the pins using a 7 mm
    Allen wrench.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070809d.C-clamp.jpg" title="C-clamp" date="09.08.2007">
    Suspend the caliper to prevent the strain on the brake line. 
    Use a C-clamp to slowly push the piston back into the caliper.
    It's easier to do while the old pad is still in.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070809e.Fluid_level.jpg" title="Fluid level" date="09.08.2007">
    While compressing the piston, watch the brake fluid level - it will go up
    and may overflow. You might need to extract some before you put the cap
    back on.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070809f.Rotor.jpg" title="Rotor" date="09.08.2007">
    The rotor should be ready to come off, with only the bracket preventing
    its removal. If the rotor is rusted to the hub, hit it with a mallet
    from behind until it comes loose.
    <image width="797" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070809g.Caliper_brackets.jpg" title="Caliper brackets" date="09.08.2007">
    Undo two caliper bracket bolts - 18 mm wrench on 1999-2001 9-5,
    Torx E20 on 2002+ 9-5, 10 mm Allen on NG900 or 9-3.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070809h.Dust_shield.jpg" title="Dust shield" date="09.08.2007">
    The dust shields on older cars are too small for the bigger rotors.
    You can either buy new ones, or bend (cut) the rim outward, or simply
    remove them. The latter is cheaper and easier than anything else, and
    you get better brake cooling as a bonus.
    <image width="800" height="599" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070809i.Pads.jpg" title="Pads" date="09.08.2007">
    New style pads are noticeably taller, which results in larger surface
    area. If your used calipers come with OEM pads that have a good portion of
    material left, you might as well use them while they last. A new set of
    pads will always be better though.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070809j.Rotors.jpg" title="Rotors" date="09.08.2007">
    A new 308 mm Aero rotor next to an old 284 mm version. A whole extra inch
    of size offers more leverage for stopping power.
    <image width="800" height="599" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070809k.Calipers.jpg" title="Calipers" date="09.08.2007">
    The calipers have a similar design, but the Aero version (on the right)
    appears to have a beefier bracket.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070809l.Hub.jpg" title="Hub" date="09.08.2007">
    Ready for installation - the dust shield is removed, the hub is wirebrushed
    and coated with anti-seize.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070809m.New_rotor.jpg" title="New rotor" date="09.08.2007">
    Install the new rotor. Put the index screw on anti-seize and
    don't tighten it too hard if you don't want to fight it the
    next time you're doing your brakes.
    <image width="800" height="599" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070809n.Caliper_bolts.jpg" title="Caliper bolts" date="09.08.2007">
    Install the caliper support bracket. Apply some Loctite on the bolts and
    tighten them to 86 ft-lbs. Lubricate the pad sliding grooves with
    anti-seize to ensure smooth operation.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070809o.Caliper.jpg" title="Caliper" date="09.08.2007">
    Put the new pads in and slide the caliper on. Clean and lubricate the
    guide pins before inserting them. 
    Tighten to 20 ft-lbs, fit the caps. Install the retaining spring.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070809p.Brake_line.jpg" title="Brake line" date="09.08.2007">
    Undo the banjo on the old caliper and detach the brake line. Quickly
    move the line to the new caliper to minimize the fluid loss.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070809q.Banjo_bolt.jpg" title="Banjo bolt" date="09.08.2007">
    Tighten the banjo on the new caliper. Use new copper washers if possible.
    Make sure the line orientation is correct, there are no twists or sharp
    bends.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070809r.Pressure_bleeder.jpg" title="Pressure bleeder" date="09.08.2007">
    Attach the bleeder to the brake reservoir and fill it with fresh fluid.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070809s.Bleeding.jpg" title="Bleeding" date="09.08.2007">
    Open the nipple on the caliper and bleed it until all the air bubbles come
    out, and you see the fresh fluid flowing. Bleed the left side first,
    then the right side.
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20070809t.Installed.jpg" title="Installed" date="09.08.2007">
    Tighten wheel bolts to 81 ft-lbs and lower the car to the ground. Keep
    in mind that you cannot fit wheels smaller than 16" anymore.
    <image width="798" height="600" />
  </picture>
</picture-set>
