<?xml version="1.0" encoding="koi8-r"?>
<picture-set title="Saab B204/B234: Engine Assembly">

  <description>
  <p>Saab B204/B234 engine assembly. This engine is found in all four-cylinder
  Saab 900 and 9000 from 1994 to 1998, as well as 1999 9-3. Newer cars with
  B205/B235 engines have certain differences, but the procedure is largely
  the same.</p>

  <h2>Tools and supplies:</h2>
  <ul>
    <li>27 mm socket: crankshaft pulley, timing chain tensioner;</li>
    <li>19 mm socket: flywheel;</li>
    <li>19 mm wrench: to hold camshafts when tightening;</li>
    <li>16 mm socket: spark plugs;</li>
    <li>14 mm socket: camshaft sprocket bolts;</li>
    <li>13 mm socket: drain plug;</li>
    <li>12 mm socket; chain tensioner plug, upper timing cover bolts;</li>
    <li>Torx E16 socket: head bolts;</li>
    <li>Torx T40 socket: timing cover, oil pan, valve cover;</li>
    <li>Torx T30 socket: endplate, DI cassette, timing and balance chain gear;</li>
    <li>torque wrench (or two - for high and low torque fasteners);</li>
    <li>large snap ring pliers: oil pump cover;</li>
    <li>rubber mallet;</li>
    <li>gasket maker.</li>
  </ul>
  </description>

  <picture name="20060702a.Crankshaft_seals.jpg" title="Crankshaft seals" date="02.07.2006">
    Before starting the assembly, make sure you have all spare parts needed.
    This picture shows the endplate and oil pump cover with a pack of fresh
    seals for them.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060702b.Suspended.jpg" title="Suspended" date="02.07.2006">
    If you are using an engine stand that bolts on to the gearbox mounting
    points, you won't be able to attach the endplate. In this case, suspending
    the engine on a hoist does the job.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060702c.Endplate.jpg" title="Endplate" date="02.07.2006">
    Clean the endplate, tap the new seal in and apply a thin bead of sealant
    to the mating surface.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060702d.Endplate_attached.jpg" title="Endplate attached" date="02.07.2006">
    Fit the plate and tighten the screws (Torx T30 socket). Wipe the excess
    sealant.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060702e.Flywheel.jpg" title="Flywheel" date="02.07.2006">
    Attach the flywheel, apply some threadlock to the bolts and tighten them
    to 59 ft-lbs (19 mm socket). Use a flywheel stop or have a helper
    hold the crank pulley nut on the other end to prevent the crankshaft
    from spinning.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060702f.Back_on_the_stand.jpg" title="Back on the stand" date="02.07.2006">
    Put the engine back on the stand. It might need some extra washers to clear
    the flywheel. Turn the flywheel to match the "0" mark on the endplate.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060702g.Balance_shaft.jpg" title="Balance shaft" date="02.07.2006">
    Lubricate the balance shafts and carefully insert them trying not to
    scratch the bearing surfaces inside the block.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060702h.Shafts_in.jpg" title="Shafts in" date="02.07.2006">
    The shafts are the same, but the sprockets are not. The intake shaft has a
    smaller sprocket marked "INL", while the exhaust side is marked "EXH".
    Tighten the screws (Torx T30).
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060703a.Chain_and_guides.jpg" title="Chain and guides" date="03.07.2006">
    Prepare a new timing chain and plastic guides.
    
    <image width="799" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060703b.Timing_chain.jpg" title="Timing chain" date="03.07.2006">
    Fit the timing chain sprocket and hang the chain off it so the
    colored link matches the notch on the sprocket (there are two other
    colored links on the other end of the chain that will match the camshafts).
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060703c.Chain_guard.jpg" title="Chain guard" date="03.07.2006">
    Attach the chain guard (two Torx T30 screws).
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060703d.Guides.jpg" title="Guides" date="03.07.2006">
    Fit the guides. The fixed guide is held by two long T30 screws, while
    the swivel guide just sits on a big pin.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060703e.Balance_shaft.jpg" title="Balance shaft" date="03.07.2006">
    Turn the balance shafts so the notch matches the mark on the housing.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060703f.Balance_chain.jpg" title="Balance chain" date="03.07.2006">
    Fit the balance chain sprocket, the small swivel guide and the balance
    shaft chain.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060703g.Tensioner.jpg" title="Tensioner" date="03.07.2006">
    Push the piston on the balance chain tensioner in and lock it with a pin
    or a paper clip.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060703h.Tensioner_fitted.jpg" title="Tensioner fitted" date="03.07.2006">
    Attach the tensioner and tighten the screws to 7.4 ft-lbs (the factory
    manual makes a big deal about it).
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060703i.Idle_sprocket.jpg" title="Idle sprocket" date="03.07.2006">
    Fit the balance chain idler sprocket (Torx T40).
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060703j.Upper_guide.jpg" title="Upper guide" date="03.07.2006">
    Attach the upper balance chain guide with two more T30 screws (the engine
    is upside down, so it's at the bottom) and release the tensioner. Turn the
    crankshaft and check if the shaft notches are still in sync with a "0" mark on
    the flywheel after a few revolutions.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060703k.No_chain.jpg" title="No chain" date="03.07.2006">
    If you choose to build the engine without a balancing chain, you can leave
    the shafts and sprockets in to preserve the proper oil flow. Just replace
    the swivel guide with a spacer so it doesn't rattle inside the engine.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060703l.Timing_cover.jpg" title="Timing cover" date="03.07.2006">
    Clean the mating surfaces of the timing cover and apply a bead of sealant.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060703m.Timing_cover.jpg" title="Timing cover" date="03.07.2006">
    Fit the cover and tighten the bolts to 16 ft-lbs (Torx T40 socket).
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060703n.Oil_pump.jpg" title="Oil pump" date="03.07.2006">
    Lubricate and insert the oil pump gears making sure that the marking on the
    oil pump ring gear is facing out and the pump gear with flange facing in.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060703o.Oil_pump_cover.jpg" title="Oil pump cover" date="03.07.2006">
    Tap a new seal into the oil pump cover, put the cover on and secure
    it with a snap ring.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060703p.Oil_tube.jpg" title="Oil tube" date="03.07.2006">
    Fit the oil feed tube and refresh the O-rings on it.
    Screw in the reducer valve.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060703q.Oil_pan.jpg" title="Oil pan" date="03.07.2006">
    Attach the pickup screen and the splash guard inside the oil pan,
    apply a bead of sealant to the flange.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060703r.Pan_fitted.jpg" title="Pan fitted" date="03.07.2006">
    Tighten the oil pan screws to 16 ft-lbs (Torx T40). Fit a fresh drain plug
    washer.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060703s.Crankshaft_pulley.jpg" title="Crankshaft pulley" date="03.07.2006">
    Slide the crankshaft pulley on (mind the oil seal in the oil pump cover)
    and tighten the 27 mm bolt to 130 ft-lbs.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060704a.Top_of_the_block.jpg" title="Top of the block" date="04.07.2006">
    Turn the block upright and clean the upper surface.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060704b.TDC_mark.jpg" title="TDC mark" date="04.07.2006">
    Turn the crankshaft pulley to match the TDC mark.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060704c.Head_and_gasket.jpg" title="Head and gasket" date="04.07.2006">
    Prepare the head with a fresh gasket. Clean the head flange thoroughly.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060704d.Gasket.jpg" title="Gasket" date="04.07.2006">
    Put the gasket on top of the block, make sure it clears the locating dowels.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060704e.Head.jpg" title="Head" date="04.07.2006">
    Set the camshafts to zero (see the markings on the #1 cap) and put the head
    carefully on the block.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060704f.Head_bolts.jpg" title="Head bolts" date="04.07.2006">
    A new set of head bolts is needed to attach a head. The old bolts are
    already stretched and won't provide a proper clamping force.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060704g.Head_bolts.jpg" title="Head bolts" date="04.07.2006">
    Tighten the bolts to 44 ft-lbs in the order shown. Then do a second pass
    and tighten them to 59 ft-lbs. Grab a bigger wrench and do a third pass,
    turning every bolt an extra 90 degrees.
    
    <image width="780" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060704j.Camshafts.jpg" title="Camshafts" date="04.07.2006">
    Fit camshaft sprockets, starting with the intake side. Check that both
    camshafts and the crankshaft remain at their "0" mark. Screw the sprocket
    bolts in but not tighten them yet.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060704h.Tensioner.jpg" title="Tensioner" date="04.07.2006">
    Take apart the timing chain tensioner and clean it. Press on the catch
    and compress the piston completely.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060704i.Tensioner.jpg" title="Tensioner" date="04.07.2006">
    Install the tensioner with a new washer while keeping it in a compressed
    state. Tighten to 47 ft-lbs (27 mm socket). Insert the spring and tighten
    the plug to 16 ft-lbs.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060704k.Sprocket_bolts.jpg" title="Sprocket bolts" date="04.07.2006">
    Rotate the crankshaft clockwise and ensure that zero marks on the camshafts
    and crank pulley are still in sync after a few revolutions. Tighten sprocket
    bolts to 47 ft-lbs (14 mm socket), tighten the two upper timing cover bolts
    to 16 ft-lbs (12 mm socket).
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060704l.Valve_cover.jpg" title="Valve cover" date="04.07.2006">
    Clean the valve cover and renew the upper timing chain guide. Apply
    some soap to the valve cover gasket so it sticks to the groove.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060704m.Valve_cover.jpg" title="Valve cover" date="04.07.2006">
    Fit the valve cover, make sure the gasket fills the half-moon openings
    correctly and is not jammed anywhere. Tighten the bolts to 11 ft-lbs
    in the order shown (Torx T40).
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060704n.Spark_plugs.jpg" title="Spark plugs" date="04.07.2006">
    Gap the spark plugs and tighten them to 20 ft-lbs. NGK BCPR7ES are the
    plugs most recommended for this application.
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
  <picture name="20060704o.DI_cassette.jpg" title="DI cassette" date="04.07.2006">
    Install the ignition module and tighten the screws to 8 ft-lbs.
    Congratulations, you've built yourself an engine!
    
    <image width="800" height="600" />
  </picture>
</picture-set>
